<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Influencers &#8211; Roadmunk Blog</title>
	<atom:link href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/category/influencers/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog</link>
	<description>Product Management and Product Roadmaps</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 19:44:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.7.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/favicon.png</url>
	<title>Influencers &#8211; Roadmunk Blog</title>
	<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Redesigning NBC News Digital from the outside in</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/moritz-gimbel/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2017 16:35:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nick Gray]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moritz gimbel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NBC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NBC News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management career]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[redesign]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ui]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[user experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ux]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3446</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>NBC News is in the midst of a digital transformation. We get all the details from the man behind the initiative: their VP of Product &#038; Design, Moritz Gimbel.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/moritz-gimbel/">Redesigning NBC News Digital from the outside in</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>NBC News is in the middle of a digital transformation. They’re rolling out the best possible content experiences for both the old school and digital-savvy news consumer one step at a time. This initiative is being spearheaded by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mgimbel" target="_blank">Moritz Gimbel</a>, the organization’s VP of Product and Design. Moritz’s goal: continuing NBC News’ mission of serving quality news to every American. (You can read about the creation of new NBC brands <em><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/mach" target="_blank">Mach</a></em>, <em><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/better" target="_blank">Better</a></em> and the soon-to-be-launched <em>Think</em> <a href="https://medium.com/nbc-news-digital/welcome-to-the-new-mach-and-better-64fded55f73e" target="_blank">here</a>.)</p>
<p>It’s been just over a year since Moritz joined NBC, and we spoke to him about his process of redesigning the storied news organization’s digital properties from the outside in, why audience loyalty is his number one KPI and how he’s improving the monetization efforts of sites like <a href="http://www.msnbc.com/" target="_blank">msnbc.com</a> and <a href="https://www.today.com/" target="_blank">today.com</a>. Here’s our interview with Moritz.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3467 size-large" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-1-1024x62.png" alt="Moritz Gimbel - Divider" width="640" height="39" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-1-1024x62.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-1-300x18.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-1-768x47.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-1.png 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>You’ve been at NBC for just over a year now. What first compelled you to join the organization?</big></strong></p>
<p>NBC is an amazing news organization with an amazing legacy, and I think they have an opportunity to build a new and broader digital audience. It was really exciting to join a company that is successful in cable and television and hasn’t, maybe, done quite as much in the digital space yet. We’re building an incredible team under new leadership to advance our digital presence. That’s a thrilling journey to be part of.</p>
<p><strong><big>What specific problems were you brought on to solve?</big></strong></p>
<p>The first six months was very much internal. When I arrived, it was about building a product team, process and structure. That consumed much of my time because publishing companies are very editorial-focused and content-led—and they should be. But it sometimes means product design and technology is not necessarily developed in the way it could be. That was really the first challenge: creating that capability to build better and faster.</p>
<p>We also wanted to create new properties and brands, and broaden the appeal of what we do. Currently in the main digital areas we have, we’re still very much an extension of our TV brands. And that’s a great legacy to be a part of. But we want to reach audiences beyond our regular viewers and build new digital-first brands.</p>
<p><strong><big>One of your mandates is to build audience loyalty across NBC News’ portfolio, and you’ve been experimenting with different tactics by building new brands—namely <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/mach" target="_blank">Mach</a> and <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/better" target="_blank">Better</a>. Can you walk us through your strategy to keep audiences coming back for more content?</big></strong></p>
<p>Our number one business goal is to develop deeper relationships with our customers. Loyalty is so important because if you grow your share of loyal audiences, your daily active visitors will multiply. Conserving readers and watchers is much more valuable for us as a business.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"We want to tell stories that don’t clickbait you into consumption."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22We%20want%20to%20tell%20stories%20that%20don%E2%80%99t%20clickbait%20you%20into%20consumption.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3446' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>If you aim purely for scale and write stories chasing SEO trends or social virality, that gets you distribution—to a degree. But we need to offer true value for people to come back to us and foster a relationship over time. That’s more monetizable (and frankly, better for society). We want to tell stories that don’t clickbait you into consumption.</p>
<p>We don’t—for example—do auto-play. We switched off auto-play over a year ago, because those kinds of growth hacks don’t validate that you’re creating good content and serving your audience. We wanted to know if users were truly engaging with our content, rather than getting content thrown at them.</p>
<p>For our new brands like Mach and Better, we want to build digital-first brands that have a voice, that have an identity, that cover niche topics extremely well. Some of the more digital-first brands started doing this awhile ago; we’re not claiming to invent this. But if you look at Mach—covering science, space and innovation—we found a very specific audience and serve them deeply over time. We did a bunch of testing around this when we first launched pop-up verticals. We didn’t give them a new design and website, but rather, we wrote stories with a particular angle and monitored over time what the consumption patterns were. That’s how brands like Mach and Better evolved.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3472 size-large" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-2-1024x62.png" alt="Moritz Gimbel - Divider" width="640" height="39" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-2-1024x62.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-2-300x18.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-2-768x47.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-2.png 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>How do you balance serving great content experiences with the need to monetize that same content through advertising?</big></strong></p>
<p>Our ambition is to have the best consumption experience for our content as possible. The idea is that our advertising over time should become more immersive and frictionless. We don&#8217;t do pop-ups. As I said, we don&#8217;t do auto-play for video. We&#8217;re trying to balance user experience and monetization, and that&#8217;s why loyalty is so important.</p>
<p>If you build loyalty and people come to you multiple times a day or week, you don&#8217;t have to cram that much monetization into one visit or click. You can look holistically at your revenue per user. It’s a more sustainable way of building business over time.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"The idea is that our advertising over time should become more immersive and frictionless."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22The%20idea%20is%20that%20our%20advertising%20over%20time%20should%20become%20more%20immersive%20and%20frictionless.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3446' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>Better ad units are part of that. Our new designs have much better ad integration, because they have modular page designs. We no longer work in templates with rigid pixel-locked scale; everything is a modular component. Our new ad units respond to the containers around them. So it means we can have many more page layouts, because ads actually scale with layouts.</p>
<p><strong><big>You’re currently in the process of a huge redesign, and I’ve read that you’re taking an approach that you refer to as “designing from the outside in”—why have you chosen this approach?</big></strong></p>
<p>Having done a few redesigns and burned myself by starting with the inside—which is often the home page and article page—I&#8217;ve learned that the reverse is better. Start with the periphery of your portfolio. Take smaller brands that are on the fringe—smaller audience, younger brands.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s less expectation from users on how these things work, so you can introduce new user experiences and design schemas without users freaking out. Because whenever you redesign something, no matter how good you do it, the first reaction generally is, &#8220;I don&#8217;t like it. I was used to this thing that I love.”</p>
<p>By going outside in, taking new brands or smaller parts of your sites and apps, you&#8217;re slowly validating that what you&#8217;re doing is right—and get early data. Then, you work towards the center, which are more frequently consumed content types. Going outside in is a more iterative, discovery- and test-based approach to product launches.</p>
<p>For example, our article page (which will become the article page for everything else we do) we have very good initial data on what&#8217;s working. Where&#8217;s recirculation going? How&#8217;s ad viewability? Now, we can optimize and scale. And then, brand by brand, roll out across the whole network.</p>
<p><strong><big>You’re building and designing new systems for the end-user, but you also need to equally consider the needs of NBC’s staff—your reporters and editors. How are they influencing your product decisions?</big></strong></p>
<p>A publishing company has two products: content and packaging. I&#8217;m in charge of packaging, and the editorial staff is in charge of content, obviously. But these things have to go hand-in-hand.</p>
<p>In an ideal world, all decisions and design discovery are done together. But I think a lot about scale and the editorial staff thinks a lot about speed. They want to iterate minute-by-minute, and for me, it&#8217;s fast to iterate on a day-by-day basis. It&#8217;s a tricky relationship.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"We’re trying to balance user experience and monetization, and that’s why loyalty is so important."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22We%E2%80%99re%20trying%20to%20balance%20user%20experience%20and%20monetization%2C%20and%20that%E2%80%99s%20why%20loyalty%20is%20so%20important.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3446' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>The most innovation is actually driven by observing and working closely with our audience and our editors; bringing them into the design and discovery process as much as possible. For instance, we tested our new article page with editors and audience. We picked key individuals in the newsroom and had them see how members of our audience consume content—what they pay attention to.</p>
<p>And then we observed how editors put an article together and how the article renders with better or worse images, how they put quotes and charts into the article. It&#8217;s very similar to what you would do externally. It&#8217;s really hard to get right and requires buy-in from both product and editorial.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3467 size-large" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-1-1024x62.png" alt="Moritz Gimbel - Divider" width="640" height="39" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-1-1024x62.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-1-300x18.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-1-768x47.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-1.png 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>You built a Slack bot to help reporters access data. Can you tell me about that?</big></strong></p>
<p>We have an integration in our internal Slack, where you can ask basic stats for an article. It’s just a conversational way of getting data that you would get from a dashboard otherwise. It&#8217;s been pretty successful, because when you’re in a reporter’s mindset of communicating in Slack and writing in a document, to go to a third place and understand a dashboard, it&#8217;s a real contextual switch. They just want one specific piece of information, so the Slack bot is a way to just ask for that.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s early days. We&#8217;re actually building out not just for Slack, but for multiple messaging services. We&#8217;re building out an API layer that is between our content management tool and specific clients, which would allow us to easily integrate internal and external bots. Building these services internally that can extract content and data efficiently allows you to then build better user experiences for internal and external users.</p>
<p><strong><big>You’ve built a living style guide as a foundation for your new design system. Based on what I’ve read, you have accessible components in <a href="https://www.sketchapp.com/" target="_blank">Sketch</a> and built a layer onto <a href="https://facebook.github.io/react/" target="_blank">React</a>. Can you give some insight into your approach here?</big></strong></p>
<p>When we first built the new front-end framework, we had to do something very fast with our existing engineering staff. No one had worked in React before, so I brought on someone I worked with at Bloomberg who helped us create a simpler library and framework that is React-like. (Now, we&#8217;re going fully React/Redux.)</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"Going outside in is a more iterative, discovery- and test-based approach to product launches."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22Going%20outside%20in%20is%20a%20more%20iterative%2C%20discovery-%20and%20test-based%20approach%20to%20product%20launches.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3446' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>In terms of the living style guide, this is like designing from outside in. When you redesign so many properties in so many places, you end up with these monster style guides that no one ever goes back to. And they&#8217;re always out of date, because by the time you’ve released or tested something, it&#8217;s already changed three times.</p>
<p>So we basically built a way to map real client code back into a style guide that automatically updates. If you want to find a style and extract that code and build a new version in a different color on a different breakpoint for a different property, that living style guide will always be in sync. There’s no longer this stale paper or digital file that you go to. It’s linked directly with the front-end client.</p>
<p><strong><big>What has been the hardest part of this entire process?</big></strong></p>
<p>The hardest, but also most interesting, part is building one system for all brands. In the past, all our brands had their own CMS, front-end client, design system; they evolved independently. But to build audience loyalty and engagement, we need to circulate content and users through our entire network of sites.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"A publishing company has two products: content and packaging."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22A%20publishing%20company%20has%20two%20products%3A%20content%20and%20packaging.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3446' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>I oversee product for MSNBC, NBC News Properties, Today Digital, new verticals and more. Currently, all of which are somewhat separate. The challenge is bringing MSNBC, Today Digital and the main NBC News sites onto this new platform with a unified design language, front-end client, ad library, analytics, publishing workflow and more. Everything is shared, but these sites don&#8217;t look the same. If you go to Today, which is a lifestyle audience, it’s very different from MSNBC. So obviously, those two brands need to be distinguished visually. But in terms of storytelling tools and publishing there doesn&#8217;t need to be a difference between the article and the way the video player works or how navigation is structured.</p>
<p>Working with multiple newsrooms and multiple brands; getting all of their requirements and ideas; solving their problems, but always rolling it back up into one system, that&#8217;s really the Holy Grail. And if we get that right, we’ll be in a place where everyone in the network has their own unique property that tells their stories and publishes their content in a way they like. It will be a more unified, efficient way of packaging and distributing our content. Getting that right is the hardest and most exciting thing.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3472 size-large" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-2-1024x62.png" alt="Moritz Gimbel - Divider" width="640" height="39" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-2-1024x62.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-2-300x18.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-2-768x47.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/moritz-gimbel_divider-2.png 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>How are you measuring the success of the redesign?</big></strong></p>
<p>I spoke about loyalty and engagement, so those are our business KPIs. And we&#8217;re trying to roll up both content and product analytics into those KPIs. Another challenge of being in product management in publishing is that your data is sort of not clean. If your product is a utility, like a ride sharing app, there&#8217;s maybe weather and time of day or time of year. But those are relatively obvious, predictable things to look at.</p>
<p>For us, news flow changes every hour, every day. Sometimes, you see difference in consumption that you could interpret as differences with your product. But in reality, your product had nothing to do with it. Maybe there was a crazy story, or your video ended up being promoted on a major portal, and that&#8217;s why it spiked. Understanding that analytics challenge is pretty complex. We&#8217;re trying to combat this with having different analytic suites that look at different things, and, as a group, always discussing how both sides affect our performance.</p>
<p><strong><big>What are you most excited about in rolling out this redesign?</big></strong></p>
<p>I&#8217;m super excited to roll out in stages over the next few months. So we&#8217;re not doing one big release. We&#8217;re actually having maybe three, four, five individual releases towards the end of the year, and I think nothing gives a product manager more of a rush than seeing your thing out in the wild and looking at the data of how people interact with it.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m also excited about launching our new article page for our news brands. In the vertical test case, it&#8217;s performing extremely well. People read longer. They scroll deeper. They engage more. They share more. So I&#8217;m eager to launch the article page when we feel comfortable that it&#8217;s ready.</p>
<hr />
<p><em><strong>A Roadmunk reminder: </strong>Managing a major redesign for your own product? We definitely have a <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=moritzgimbel" target="_blank">roadmap template</a> to help you with that. </em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/moritz-gimbel/">Redesigning NBC News Digital from the outside in</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>25 must-read product management articles</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-articles/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 18:27:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Latif Nanji]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[influencer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management reading]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management resources]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management writing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product strategy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3390</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>With so many online resources to help sort through a career in product, here are 25 essential product management articles.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-articles/">25 must-read product management articles</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Throughout my career as both a product manager and startup founder, there’s been one severely underrated skill I credit for much of my success—and that’s reading. (Trust me, when I say I’m an avid reader. Just take a look at </span><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/12925194" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">my Goodreads list</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">!)</span></p>
<p>I’m constantly consuming articles on product management, product culture, startups and entrepreneurship to bolster my career as a product person and leader. So I thought I’d share some of <strong>my favorite reading materials</strong> that have helped me through my career in product—and are still crowding my bookmarks tab.</p>
<p>For this list, I stuck to online posts strictly. (If I listed books, we’d be here forever.) This list is not the be all end all; there are countless ‘must-read’ articles for PMs. <strong>I’ve hand-picked articles that specifically helped me during key moments in my career.</strong> Some sit outside the product domain, but still directly pushed me as a product manager to connect and empathize with other team members.</p>
<p>Let’s get to it. <strong>Here’s my list of favorite online posts for product managers</strong>.</p>
<p><b>1. <a href="http://pmarchive.com/guide_to_startups_part4.html" target="_blank">The only thing that matters<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="http://blog.pmarca.com/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Marc Andreessen </span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">What’s most critical to the success of a startup? That’s a rather&#8230; ambivalent (and annoying) question. But in part 4 of a 9-part series on startups by Marc Andreessen (co-founder of Andreessen Horowitz), there are three factors to startup success identified: your team, product and market.</span></p>
<p>However, Marc argues that it’s actually <strong>market knowledge</strong> (or “user empathy”) <strong>that’s likely the determining factor for your startup</strong>. It’s a compelling and non-BS answer relevant for PMs at any sized-company.</p>
<p><b>2. <a href="https://a16z.com/2017/02/18/12-things-about-product-market-fit/" target="_blank">12 things about product-market fit<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tren-griffin-50582725" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tren Griffin </span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I really love this post because most PMs struggle to conceptualize product-market fit, since it varies from product to product. But in this post, Tren Griffin, Senior Director at Microsoft, sums up the concept succinctly. My personal favorite explanation: </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“<strong>The term product/market fit describes ‘the moment when a startup finally finds a widespread set of customers that resonate with its product.’</strong>” </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">This article should be top of mind when anyone embarks on a new product journey, so they can pinpoint the exact moment when product-market fit is achieved.</span></p>
<p><b>3. <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/relres.html" target="_blank">Relentlessly resourceful<br />
</a></b><b>Author</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/bio.html" target="_blank">Paul Graham</a></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Originally written for founders, by a founder (my man, VC and entrepreneur Paul Graham), this post speaks exactly to <strong>the quality I look for when hiring a PM</strong>. Almost no amount of experience, knowledge of theory or models, or charisma can outshine a PM’s ability to be relentlessly resourceful.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I recall Warren Buffett saying in a speech, “Who is the person in your class most likely to succeed?” Do they have the best grades? Are they the most intelligent? It’s somebody who navigates every problem with determination and grit to get shit done. This post was a great reminder to <strong>keep my own (and my hires’) resourcefulness in check</strong>.</span></p>
<p><b>4. <a href="http://firstround.com/review/The-one-cost-engineers-and-product-managers-dont-consider/" target="_blank">The one cost that product managers and engineers don’t understand<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="http://firstround.com/review/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">First Round Review</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Answer: <strong>The cost of maintaining new code.</strong> The more complex you make your product, the higher the cost of altering that code afterwards. How many times I refer this post to new PMs still surprises me. Yes, I want to know when something will ship in the short-term, but I care 5x more about its maintenance cost in the long-run.</span></p>
<p><b>5. <a href="https://blackboxofpm.com/the-time-value-of-shipping-6deaf8d7d565" target="_blank">The time value of shipping<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="https://ca.linkedin.com/in/brandonmchu" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Brandon Chu</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As a PM you eventually accept that when you put your ‘baby’ out into the world, it’s </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">probably</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> not going to be perfect. Knowing when to pull the trigger on a product release is a necessary, albeit tricky, skill for PMs to develop. So Shopify’s Director of Product, Brandon Chu, developed <strong>a framework to streamline that decision-making process</strong>. A tactical and handy post!</span></p>
<p><b>6. <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html" target="_blank">Maker’s schedule, manager’s schedule<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Paul Graham (told you I was a big fan!)</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This is a post that really informs <strong>how I interact with team members day-to-day</strong>. I’m cognizant that designers and developers generally dive deep into one problem at a time—asking them a question can disrupt their flow. Managers, on the other hand, can be interrupted because their job is to constantly switch between contexts.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I can also thank this article for encouraging me to schedule my own maker time and shifting my regular schedule. I don’t take meetings in the morning (unless I </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">absolutely</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> have to) and I workout from 3:30 to 5 PM, so that I can reflect on what to achieve post-sweat session.</span></p>
<p><b>7. <a href="https://blackboxofpm.com/deadlines-d6925e5c694f" target="_blank">Deadlines<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Brandon Chu</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Yeahhh, you might notice a few go-to writers on this list. In this post, Brandon Chu offers PMs a healthy reality-check about being realistic with deadlines and <strong>the need for balance</strong>. (Trust me, burnout is a </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">very</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> real thing.)</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I have to admit though, as I re-read this post, I got emotionally charged because most people don’t actually understand the PURPOSE of friggin’ deadlines. It’s not about hitting dates; it’s about <strong>changing behavior</strong>. It’s no coincidence when you give deadlines to salespeople, quarter ends usually are the busiest. Keeping insights from this article in your back pocket will do you well as a PM mapping out project timelines.</span></p>
<p><b>8. <a href="https://labs.spotify.com/2014/03/27/spotify-engineering-culture-part-1/" target="_blank">Spotify engineering culture (part 1)<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hkniberg/?ppe=1" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Henrik Kniberg</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fine, this one isn’t a ‘must-read;’ it’s a ‘must-watch.’ But I’ve always been fascinated with Spotify’s famous squad, tribe, Survivor-esque sounding setup—especially as agile becomes status quo for product orgs, and more companies shift to this specific engineering culture. The video delves into the motivation behind the culture and offers <strong>learnings that PMs can apply to their own culture.</strong></span></p>
<p><b>9. <a href="https://medium.com/the-year-of-the-looking-glass/how-to-work-with-engineers-a3163ff1eced" target="_blank">How to work with engineers<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/julie-zhuo-35b11322" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Julie Zhou</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This one’s aimed at designers, but considering the author Julie Zhou, Facebook’s VP of Product Design, is an ex-PM, I’m throwing it on the list. As much time as designers spend with engineers, a PM is sure as hell spending just as much (if not more) time working/communicating/pulling their hair out with their engineering team (<a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/shit-umbrella/" target="_blank">we are shit umbrellas for a reason</a>). Hence, why this helpful cheat sheet for designers is also essential-reading for PMs.</span></p>
<p><b>10. <a href="https://medium.com/the-year-of-the-looking-glass/how-to-work-with-designers-6c975dede146" target="_blank">How to work with designers<br />
</a></b><b>Author</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: Julie Zhou</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We talked working with engineers, now let’s chat <strong>working with product designers</strong>. With just as much time invested in working with your design team (as you do engineering), you might want to brush up on </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-designers/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">how best to manage that working relationship</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> as well. Julie provides another useful cheat sheet, this time specifically dedicated to PMs and engineers.</span></p>
<p><b>11. <a href="https://medium.com/@_tarunc/how-would-you-design-an-interface-for-a-1000-floor-elevator-31fbe5be6470" target="_blank">How would you design an interface for a 1000 floor elevator?<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tarun-chakravorty-20b28833" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tarun Chakravorty</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you’re ever looking for <strong>a think-outside-the-box type of exercise that’ll test your UX chops</strong>, this post is for you. I strongly believe </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-design-principles/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">all PMs should be design-centric</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> (it’s all about that empathy, folks!), so this post allows PMs to put on their product design hats and get thinking like a designer.</span></p>
<p><b>12. <a href="https://blackboxofpm.com/ruthless-prioritization-e4256e3520a9" target="_blank">Ruthless prioritization<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Brandon Chu</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Brandon Chu makes yet another appearance on the list with a different framework; this time to help with prioritization (between projects and within a project). </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A sign that a PM is more junior in their career is the tendency to over bloat, i.e. prioritizing too many things. A seasoned PM knows how to prioritize just enough to get an MVP (or </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-design-principles/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">MSP—minimum sellable product—as I like to encourage</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">). This article can help <strong>junior PMs trying to level-up</strong> AND <strong>senior PMs who want to effectively evaluate more junior team members</strong>.</span></p>
<p><b>13. <a href="https://bothsidesofthetable.com/understanding-how-the-innovator-s-dilemma-affects-you-75563219a58d" target="_blank">Understanding how the innovator’s dilemma affects you<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/marksuster" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mark Suster</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The “innovator’s dilemma” is one of those commonly-misunderstood buzz-terms tossed around the product space. But 2x entrepreneur and VC Mark Suster kindly breaks it down in his post. Beyond defining the term, he goes onto explain what it means for a company—and by extension a PM—whether you’re <strong>a startup aiming to “disrupt”</strong> (another buzzword) the market or you’re <strong>the incumbent</strong> (a.k.a. a leader within your market).</span></p>
<p><b>14. <a href="http://firstround.com/review/dear-pms-its-time-to-rethink-agile-at-enterprise-startups/" target="_blank">Dear PMs, it’s time to rethink agile at enterprise startups<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">First Round Review (or at least someone from there…)</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There’s a common misconception in the product space that </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/agile-roadmap-ebook" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">agile and planning don’t go hand-in-hand</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. As a co-founder of a roadmapping platform, I </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">think</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> you know where I stand on this idea (hint: it’s not true), but don’t just take my word for it; read this post too. This interview with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ogi-kavazovic-9ab68" target="_blank">Ogi Kavazovic</a>, CMO and SVP Product Strategy at Flatiron Health, outlines <strong>a tactical perspective for balancing these seemingly counterintuitive concepts</strong>.</span></p>
<p><b>15. <a href="https://medium.com/the-year-of-the-looking-glass/the-agony-and-ecstasy-of-building-with-data-56215764d67c" target="_blank">The agony and ecstasy of building with data<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Julie Zhou</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Julie’s deconstruction of the perils of data and A/B testing was too on-the-nose to be left off the list. Highlighting <strong>common pitfalls for PMs embarking on data testing</strong>, this is a post I constantly reference when dealing with data. One particular pitfall that constantly brings this article to mind? Making biased decisions based on short-term data. Let’s just say, this article prevented me from making this mistake </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">more than once</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><b>16. <a href="http://firstround.com/review/the-best-advice-we-overheard-at-first-rounds-cto-unconference/" target="_blank">The best advice we heard at First Round’s CTO unconference<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Still unknown, but First Round Review again</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As a PM, you’re surrounded by technical people; hell, you might just be a technical PM. So why not read insights from a bunch of tech leaders discussing, well, tech while crammed into one unconference for a day? Chock-full of <strong>actionable advice on topics ranging from hiring to metrics to diversity</strong>, this post provides multiple perspectives from your everyday techie.</span></p>
<p><b>17. <a href="http://paulgraham.com/ds.html" target="_blank">Do things that don’t scale<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Paul Graham (again)</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Build it and they will come. A commonly frustrating phrase I hear around the product space, that’s often just flawed. People like to believe that startups either succeed or don’t—but that dichotomy is an outdated mentality. Paul Graham explains that in reality <strong>startups excel when founders </strong></span><strong><i>take action</i></strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong> to make them succeed</strong>. Specifically a few <strong>unscalable actions</strong>. PMs, don’t pass up on this article because it’s aimed at startups; these principles are VERY applicable to your product too.</span></p>
<p><b>18. <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/founders.html" target="_blank">What we look for in founders<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Paul Graham</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Last one from Paul—I promise! This one’s written with executive-level people in mind. Listing <strong>five traits that a founder should embody</strong>, this list was something I kept in mind when hunting for </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/technical-co-founder/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">my technical co-founder</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. But these traits shouldn’t be relegated to only founders. <strong>These should be traits you look for in any hire</strong> (I’m looking at you PMs!).</span></p>
<p><b>19. <a href="https://www.quora.com/Product-Management/What-distinguishes-the-Top-1-of-product-managers-from-the-Top-10" target="_blank">What distinguishes the top 1% of product managers from the top 10%?<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Multiple</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Not </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">really</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> an article, but this Quora thread compiles answers from various product leaders about what differentiates the crème de la crème of product management. I want to point you specifically to the response by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ianmcallister/" target="_blank">Ian McAllister</a> (then Director at AirBnB) as he highlights<strong> key traits that PMs should aspire to</strong> and how these qualities (while difficult) should always be on your mind. </span></p>
<p><b>20. <a href="http://blog.idonethis.com/managers-write/" target="_blank">Bad managers talk, good managers write<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/whchen" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Walter Chen</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The gift of gab ain’t all that it’s cracked up to be. We’ve stressed before </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/writing-for-product-strategy-alignment/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">how writing is a vital (and underrated) skill for PMs</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, so I definitely had to include this post about <strong>the superiority of written communication</strong> <strong>over verbal communication</strong> from Walter Chen, Founder and CEO of Animalz. As a PM, take a read to clear any doubts about why those technical docs you’re writing actually matter.</span></p>
<p><b>21. <a href="https://blog.ycombinator.com/navigating-mid-success/" target="_blank">Navigating mid-success<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="https://www.crunchbase.com/person/sam-altman" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sam Altman </span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Product management = juggling and managing many, many, </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">many </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">expectations. President of Y Combinator, Sam Altman, wrote a much-needed reminder that as PMs we must have <strong>conversations with our executives about their expectations</strong> to see if we align on product strategy. Do you really know what you’re signing up for as a PM? </span></p>
<p><b>22. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ReRcHdeUG9Y" target="_blank">Simon Sinek: Why leaders eat last<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/simonsinek" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Simon Sinek</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Alright, I broke the rules again; it’s a video. What starts off as your run-of-the-mill motivational speech about leadership, morphs into a riveting talk about <strong>hidden expectations of leaders</strong>. As a PM, you’ll more often than not, be looked to as a leader. Watch the video to understand deep-seated beliefs of being a leader and <strong>how you can</strong> <strong>gain trust from those you work with</strong>. </span></p>
<p><b>23. <a href="https://www.mindtheproduct.com/2013/07/using-the-kano-model-to-prioritize-product-development/" target="_blank">Using the Kano model to prioritize product development<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="http://martineriksson.com/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Martin Eriksson</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Delighting your users shouldn’t be a nice-to-have; it should be a must! That’s why I root for the Kano model. I don’t even know how many posts there are about this model, but I particularly gun for this post by Martin Eriksson, founder of ProductTank and co-founder of Mind the Product, because he neatly sums up <strong>the model’s central lessons for a PM</strong>. No matter which </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-prioritization-techniques/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">prioritization technique</span></a> <span style="font-weight: 400;">you’ve enlisted, this post makes a case for why you need Kano in your life</span><b>.</b></p>
<p><b>24. <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/customer-feedback-loop/" target="_blank">Creating effective customer feedback loops for product teams<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Roadmunk team</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Yes, this one’s a shameless plug, but I do consider it necessary reading for PMs. At product orgs, customer feedback steers product teams towards a stronger product that users actually </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">want</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. But getting that feedback to and from your product team is a system that needs finessing, otherwise feedback can easily get lost. <strong>Read how our CS team gets the feedback loop perpetually going to ensure</strong> <strong>our product team makes the most of user feedback</strong>.</span></p>
<p><b>25. <a href="https://www.inc.com/justin-bariso/20-years-ago-steve-jobs-demonstrated-the-perfect-w.html" target="_blank">20 years ago, Steve Jobs demonstrated the perfect way to respond to an insult<br />
</a></b><b>Author: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/JustinJBariso" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Justin Bariso</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you haven’t seen this infamous interaction between Steve Jobs and an inquisitive-yet-insulting audience member, this post packages together the biggest learnings from that moment. What could’ve been a seriously awkward encounter, turned into an eloquent and well-articulated lesson for anyone who’s ever released something and faced significant criticism. This post (and video) is <strong>a teaching of patience and humility</strong> for when PMs (or anyone, in fact) is confronted with <strong>those uncomfortable moments of pushback</strong>.</span></p>
<hr />
<p><em>Don&#8217;t just read about product management—get tactical with it! Visit our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=25productmanagementarticles" target="_blank">template library</a> to get roadmapping. </em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-articles/">25 must-read product management articles</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>SaaS product management explained by 6 product managers</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/saas-product-management/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2017 15:06:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tarif Rahman]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[saas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[saas metrics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[saas product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[saas product management metrics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[saas product manager]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3134</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>6 product managers in the SaaS industry break down everything related to SaaS product management from necessary skills to metrics to up-and-coming trends. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/saas-product-management/">SaaS product management explained by 6 product managers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The rise of the SaaS model in the product space has been swift, to say the least. So as product managers, knowing how to manage </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">only</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> traditional, on-premises software no longer cuts it.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We chatted with six experts (i.e. SaaS product managers) to find out how their role differs from an “old-school” software PM—and more importantly, what it really takes to be a SaaS PM. Breaking down everything from must-have skills to </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/saas-product-management-metrics/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">those special metrics</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to up-and-coming trends within the space, these insights from SaaS veterans can prepare any PM looking to enter (or those already in) the SaaS space. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here’s who we spoke with:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#evan"><b>Evan Michner</b></a>, Principal Product Manager at <strong>Atlassian</strong></li>
<li><a href="#jill"><strong>Jill Renwick</strong></a>, Product Manager at <strong>ScribbleLive</strong></li>
<li><a href="#ramin"><strong>Ramin Shokrizadeh</strong></a>, Senior Product Manager at <strong>Zendesk</strong></li>
<li><a href="#allison"><strong>Allison Burnett</strong></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Principal Product Manager at <strong>Oracle</strong></span></li>
<li><a href="#alex"><strong>Olexandr Prokhorenko</strong></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Director of Product Management at <strong>Zuora</strong></span></li>
<li><a href="#sue"><b>Sue Raisty</b></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Product Management Consultant and CEO at <strong>Sure Product Consulting</strong></span></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h1 id="evan">Evan Michner</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-full wp-image-3151 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/saas_product_management-Evan.png" alt="SaaS product management - Evan Michner" width="248" height="260" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Principal Product Manager<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Atlassian<br />
</span><b>Connect with him: </b><span class="username u-dir" dir="ltr"><a class="ProfileHeaderCard-screennameLink u-linkComplex js-nav" href="https://twitter.com/EvanMichner" target="_blank">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/emichner" target="_blank">LinkedIn</a></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>How does SaaS product management differ from traditional software product management?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The nature of SaaS implies that your customer is constantly re-evaluating your product—weekly, monthly, or yearly. Switching has become easier. And for a PM, differentiation becomes more critical. It’s a reminder to go back to the basics of ensuring we’re solving the right problems to create products that customers love.</span></p>
<p><b>If there was one thing a SaaS PM needed (tool, process, skill, etc.) to survive, what would it be?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For any PM, I think it&#8217;s the art of discernment. Looking at a problem carefully from all angles to pave the right path forward. <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/why-all-our-new-hires-do-customer-support-for-two-weeks/" target="_blank">Empathy is critical in that process</a>—putting the customer at the center of your decision.</span></p>
<p><b>As a SaaS PM, how are you measuring success? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When a PM can go on vacation and trust the team to make the right decisions for the customer, that’s success in my book! It means that the PM has done a great job of communicating the problem and metrics of success for that project. </span></p>
<p><b>The data you focus on seems to be a key differentiator in SaaS product management. What’s the top metric a SaaS PM should focus on?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The AARRR framework is always a solid starting point: </span>acquisition<span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span>activation<span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span>retention<span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span>referral<span style="font-weight: 400;"> and </span>revenue<span style="font-weight: 400;">. For example, take referral. Your job as a PM would be to move the business forward by building a product your customers love so much that they’re recommending it to their friends over and over again. A clear goal that impacts business.</span></p>
<p><b>From your time as a SaaS PM, what is a mistake you actively try to avoid today?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">All of the time I wasted chasing the perfect product! I’m a perfectionist. It took me far too long to realize that a team could deliver more value to customers by shipping the first version than by sitting around perfecting it. Cast the vision, build the version. Keep iterating, keep shipping!</span></p>
<p><b>What’s one way to guarantee failure as a SaaS PM? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Never talking to your customers. And treating them as a number…or a dollar sign.</span></p>
<hr />
<h1 id="jill">Jill Renwick</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-full wp-image-3162 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/saas_product_management-Jill.png" alt="SaaS product management - Jill Renwick" width="281" height="238" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b>Product Manager<br />
<b>Company: </b>ScribbleLive<br />
<b>Connect with her: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/dezign" target="_blank">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jillrenwick/" target="_blank">LinkedIn</a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>How does SaaS product management differ from on-premises software product management?</b></p>
<p>I’ve always worked on SaaS products—so I can’t speak to personal experiences on both sides—but there are definitely different revenue considerations. There are also different expectations regarding customizations you can offer.</p>
<p>We’re not creating one-off versions of software; we’re creating scalable, fast solutions. So as a SaaS PM, you want to build open and flexible products. This way different use cases can leverage the same features, but in various ways.</p>
<p><b>You mentioned different expectations regarding customizations. Can you expand on how user expectations differ for SaaS products?</b></p>
<p>For customers more used to enterprise or custom-built software, they might expect one-off customizations or features they can heavily customize. Also, they expect software to release differently. The cadence of how often we release new software—or new features—to clients is definitely different than offering an update to clients a couple times a year. So we need to offer a different level of training and hands-on approach from our client teams too.</p>
<p><b>Walk us through how you measure success as a SaaS PM.</b></p>
<p>There’s a bunch of different ways. To name a few:</p>
<ul>
<li>Overall client sentiment. Are clients seeing value in the platform? Are we solving an actual problem for them? Are we easily replaceable?</li>
<li>Client retention</li>
<li>Overall platform usage. How often are clients logging in and using key features?</li>
<li>Monthly recurring revenue. How much money are you making from the platform?</li>
<li>Feature-specific adoption</li>
</ul>
<p><b>What’s one way to ensure failure as a SaaS PM?</b></p>
<p>I’d say lack of passion for your product. If you don’t care about the product or clients you’re building for, I’d say move on to a different role!</p>
<p><b>What trends are emerging in SaaS product management?</b></p>
<p>The evolution of single-product services or point solutions to larger platforms. Clients are looking to consolidate vendors and have more integrated solutions. For mature startups, this may come through in software acquisitions or new internal product builds.</p>
<hr />
<h1 id="ramin">Ramin Shokrizadeh</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-full wp-image-3166 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/saas_product_management-Ramin.png" alt="SaaS product management - Ramin" width="261" height="205" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b>Senior Product Manager<br />
<b>Company: </b>Zendesk<br />
<b>Connect with him: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/rshok" target="_blank">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ramin-shokrizadeh-95877a24/" target="_blank">LinkedIn</a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>What are the main differences between SaaS product management and traditional software product management?</b></p>
<p>My whole PM career has been in SaaS, so I can’t share first-hand experience on differences. But observing PMs who’ve transitioned, the biggest difference is development speed and frequency of deploying to customers. Also roadmap flexibility. The roadmap changes more often in SaaS, meaning more communication with stakeholders.</p>
<p><b>If you needed a tool or process or skill to survive as a SaaS PM, what would it be?</b></p>
<p>Strong data analysis and understanding of how to query data from databases. Funnel and segmentation analysis is key to SaaS product optimization. Focus on understanding data more generally and teach yourself how to write SQL queries. These skills will pay off tenfold.</p>
<p><b>How should a SaaS PM measure success? </b></p>
<p>Ultimately, a healthy SaaS funnel is one that has a low and sustainable churn rate with customers who are promoters. From emerging startups to medium-sized companies, organic referrals will always be critical to adoption of new features and a business’ overall success.</p>
<p><b>Since metrics are a </b><b><i>big</i></b><b> differentiator in SaaS product management, what would you say is the top metric for a SaaS PM?</b></p>
<p>I manage both web and mobile products, so I approach each slightly differently. For web, I primarily focus on net promoter score (NPS) and its trend over time, broken down by customer segment and persona type.</p>
<p>For mobile, I look at weekly retention rates by cohort to ensure we’re keeping new app users engaged over time. I also closely monitor and respond to ratings/reviews from the App Store and Google Play Store.</p>
<p><b>Let&#8217;s talk trends in SaaS product management. Anything you’re noticing?</b></p>
<p>Business funnels will have new emerging front doors such as conversational experiences on 3rd party platforms, like Facebook Messenger in North America and LINE/WeChat in Asia.</p>
<p>Within constraints of these conversational/bot platforms, copywriting is becoming even more important for feature or product design. Copywriting is not a common skill associated with PMs but it’s a great skill to have and there are some good books to help grow that muscle. (<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Persuasive-Copywriting-Psychology-Influence-Engage/dp/0749473991/" target="_blank">Persuasive copywriting</a> was recommended to me early in my career.)</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<hr />
<h1 id="allison"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Allison Burnett</span></h1>
<p><b><img class="size-full wp-image-3155 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/saas_product_management-Allison.png" alt="SaaS product management - Allison Burnett" width="281" height="259" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Principal Product Manager<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Oracle<br />
</span><b>Connect with her: </b><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/allison-burnett-9733b13/" target="_blank">LinkedIn</a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>How does SaaS product management differ from traditional software product management?</strong></p>
<p>In SaaS environments you need to keep existing customers so they continue to pay for your service. Every release must be easy-to-use, provide value for your customers and not frustrate them. When making significant changes to existing functionality, the PM should understand the customer impact so as not to lose any users.</p>
<p>In my experience, SaaS applications tend to have faster release cycles. You constantly need to talk to your customers and gather data so you can quickly iterate on the product.</p>
<p><strong>What&#8217;s one thing (tool, process, skill, etc.) a SaaS PM needs to survive?</strong></p>
<p>Curiosity and defined overall vision. Always ask questions, don’t make assumptions and do research to make the right decisions for your product area. Know what you’re building and why, so you can quickly adapt to changes and still get valuable features out the door.</p>
<p><strong>How do you measure success as a SaaS PM?</strong></p>
<p>Depends on the goal of your product area, but in general successful adoption plus retention of your product in the market.</p>
<p><strong>How do you guarantee failure as a SaaS PM?</strong></p>
<p>While getting metrics on the product is always key, it’s important to remember ‘the why.’ Why are your customers using the product this way? How are they using the product to do whatever they need to do? Getting data is one thing; understanding the data and your customers is another.</p>
<p><strong>Any key trends you see popping up in SaaS product management?</strong></p>
<p>With recent political developments within the U.S. and the low Canadian dollar, I&#8217;m hearing more tech companies consider opening offices north of the border. And on the flip side, I’m hearing more PMs wanting to stay in Canada.</p>
<p>In the enterprise space, I’m hearing more about the right balance between <a href="https://roadmunk.com/agile-roadmap-ebook?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=saasproductmanagement" target="_blank">agile and a fully defined roadmap</a> (enterprise agile).</p>
<hr />
<h1 id="alex"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Olexandr Prokhorenko</span></h1>
<p><b><img class="size-full wp-image-3159 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/saas_product_management-Alex.png" alt="SaaS product management - Alex Prokhorenko" width="270" height="205" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Director of Product Management<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Zuora<br />
</span><b>Connect with him: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://twitter.com/iwhite" target="_blank">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/white/" target="_blank">LinkedIn</a></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>As a SaaS PM, what is the one tool/process/skill you need to survive?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s not necessarily a tool, but staying sharp with technology and having a holistic view of technologies around you. Your goal as a PM is to offer an end-to-end experience.</span></p>
<p><b>How do you measure success as a SaaS PM?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Profitability and cash growth. My general rule of thumb is if your LTV is at least four times your CAC, you can recover the CAC in less than a year. It varies though and is not a hard-and-fast rule. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">At much bigger, more mature companies, look at profitability per employee, so you don’t overgrow what you can’t afford. With smaller companies, growth should never be a separate entity. It should be a responsibility of every employee to grow the company.</span></p>
<p><b>Looking back at your SaaS PM career, any cringe worthy moments or mistakes you&#8217;d avoid today?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hiring mistakes. I try not to fall in love with logos, pedigrees, that kind of stuff. But sometimes you might end up hiring somebody just for the “Google” name on the resume and they end up not meeting the expectations.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Also, I’m currently working on the pricing model here at Zuora. There is no one-size-fits-all; it’s an ongoing exercise. You cannot price it and then fight your way to get pricing right. Keep iterating. </span></p>
<p><b>How can a SaaS PM set themselves up for failure?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This applies to any PM, but forgetting the fundamental thing you’re solving. It resonates with “build it and they will come.” Don’t. Because they won’t come. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Also scope creep. You can build the biggest thing ever and end up with the biggest failure ever. You’re not going to build something 100% right. 80% (or even less sometimes) is good enough.</span></p>
<p><b>Any significant trends in SaaS product management?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I do see vertical and horizontal SaaS scaling. Companies are going into specific industries (real estate, finance, etc.) or establishing themselves as role-specific (marketing, sales, etc.). Many start from the intersection of these two orientations and try to capture the whole area.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Also, it’s a little early, but I see a lot of interest in UI-less SaaS platforms. Trying to use already existing channels such as bots, messengers, emails, calendars, as primary delivery communication mechanisms. SaaS businesses aren’t concentrating on single entry points.</span></p>
<hr />
<h1 id="sue"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sue Raisty</span></h1>
<p><b><img class="size-full wp-image-3169 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/saas_product_management-Sue.png" alt="SaaS product management - Sue Raisty" width="269" height="207" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Product Management Consultant and CEO<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sure Product Consulting<br />
</span><b>Connect with her: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://twitter.com/sueraisty" target="_blank">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sueraisty/" target="_blank">LinkedIn</a></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>What’s the difference between SaaS product management and traditional software product management?</strong></p>
<p>From my perspective—and I work mainly in B2B enterprise software—SaaS product management is now traditional. The B2B world has been mostly web-based since 2000, but customers managed servers in their own data centers. Nowadays, customers subscribe to cloud-based services and servers are managed by us.</p>
<p>With SaaS, I work with DevOps. I rarely think about simplifying the upgrade and migration process of server products because DevOps handles it; customers don&#8217;t have to. Before I used to track a giant matrix of what operating system-database-application server combinations were &#8220;supported&#8221; configurations for our product. I still do this a little, but it’s so much easier.</p>
<p><strong>Is there a specific metric a SaaS PM should focus on to measure success?</strong></p>
<p>I have different types of clients so it’s different for all of them. But when I help a Head of Product decide which metrics they should monitor, I suggest tracking the number of meaningful customer contacts each PM has per week. It fundamentally changes PM behaviour. Usually they’re not tracking it, so measuring it gets PMs prioritizing listening to customers.</p>
<p><strong>Looking back at your time as a SaaS PM specifically, any cringe worthy moments you feel like you could avoid today?</strong></p>
<p>Yeah, of course! If you’ve read <a href="http://blog.sueraisty.com/" target="_blank">my blog</a> it’s full of many of my cringe worthy moments, I’m sure.</p>
<p>Specific to SaaS, there’s the mistake where you roll out an incorrect change. With SaaS, once you roll out a change everybody has it, right? So it’s more of an emergency than if you just published the link to the latest download. In SaaS, sometimes you think you’ve tested the heck out of something and then immediately you’re rolling it back.</p>
<p><strong>What trends are popping up in the SaaS product management space?</strong></p>
<p>User experience is becoming ever more important (a welcome change for enterprise B2B products, where the UIs were often horrible!).</p>
<p>I also see SaaS PMs think about how to analyze the large amounts of data their products collect. Sometimes this analysis can be so valuable to customers that you can charge for it as a new product.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>SaaS or traditional, any product manager can benefit from a roadmap. Our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=saasproductmanagement" target="_blank">template library</a> makes it simple to align your entire organization on product strategy—whatever your delivery model.</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/saas-product-management/">SaaS product management explained by 6 product managers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Product velocity is as much emotional as tactical</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/anna-marie-clifton/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2017 17:35:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[anna marie clifton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[influencer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product delivery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product velocity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yammer]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2694</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>It's not just on-paper processes impacting product velocity—interpersonal factors matter too. Anna Marie Clifton, Product Manager at Yammer, discusses a people-first approach to product delivery. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/anna-marie-clifton/">Product velocity is as much emotional as tactical</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here’s a word we didn’t expect to hear in a conversation about product velocity: “voodoo.” Although velocity can be considered a hard measure of time, the factors that </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">impact</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> velocity are a lot more mercurial. And during our chat with Yammer product manager </span><a href="https://twitter.com/tweetannamarie" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Anna Marie Clifton</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, she made it clear that product delivery is </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">not</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> just a function of a well-oiled dev team. “It’s easy to consider velocity a thing that your engineers do or don’t do,” she says, “but it’s a much, much, much bigger problem than that.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s been more than a year since Anna Marie joined Yammer, where she currently leads the growth initiative. She also hosts a podcast, </span><a href="http://www.clearlyproduct.com/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Clearly Product</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, with Quibb founder </span><a href="https://twitter.com/sandimac" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sandi MacPherson</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, and shares a mix of personal insights and meaty product reads on </span><a href="https://medium.com/@tweetannamarie" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">her Medium account</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet tw-align-center" data-lang="en">
<p dir="ltr" lang="en" style="text-align: left;">Prepping the next episode of <a href="https://twitter.com/ClearlyProduct">@ClearlyProduct</a>—a discussion on Andy Grove&#8217;s classic book: High Output Management. Super excited to share soon!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">— Anna Marie Clifton (@TweetAnnaMarie) <a href="https://twitter.com/TweetAnnaMarie/status/866465602352721920">May 22, 2017</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
<p><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/8-product-managers-share-trends-goals-2017/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">We recently chatted with Anna Marie about her goals for the coming year</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, and her answer was all about building a sense of </span><b>psychological safety</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> with her team. Her approach to velocity is an extension of that </span><b>people-first thinking</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: achieving and maintaining velocity is as much an emotional question as a tactical question. How you talk to colleagues, how you approach uncertainty, the energy you bring to the project—all of these factors can unlock or impede velocity as much as your on-paper processes.</span></p>
<p><strong><big>First of all, give us some context. What does velocity mean to you?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think about velocity in terms of: how long does it take from deciding that something is possible to getting it in front of customers? What is that total time? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There’s the velocity of idea iteration on that early side. How quickly do you validate or invalidate ideas with your research team? Or with your data analytics team, before you even bring an idea into the design phase? And then how quickly do you work with the designer to drive towards the goal and get to a point where you’re comfortable presenting your designs for review with the head of product?</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"The reason velocity is so important is because it’s literally survival for your company."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22The%20reason%20velocity%20is%20so%20important%20is%20because%20it%E2%80%99s%20literally%20survival%20for%20your%20company.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2694' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And then how quickly do you get your engineering team up to speed on what it is you’re trying to accomplish and why. How bought-in are they to those goals? Because that can derail your velocity later on.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And then there’s always the question of, what happens during project execution? What does it take to get that final mile out to customers? Are you doing messaging? Is there any change management? Did you think about that enough in advance? So really when I think about velocity I’m thinking about laying down the tracks in front of your team, and making sure you’ve thought of and uncovered a bunch of things before your team hits them.</span></p>
<p><strong><big>Jussst in case it’s not obvious: why is velocity so important to a product org?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s one of those heartbeats of the company. The question of how much you’re going to get in front of customers. How viable you’re going to be, how quickly you’re going to be able to respond to market trends. And you only have so many resources. Every single organization in the world feels like they’re understaffed and they don’t have enough resources to approach the problems they want to approach. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The reason velocity is so important is because it’s literally survival for your company. Velocity and direction are the two things that control whether or not you’ll be around in a few years. First of all, there’s the entire product direction: where are you going, your thesis, why is this the angle that you’re betting on? The combination of those two will determine if you survive. It determines if your competitor is going to outpace you or go in a better direction than you and acquire all the customers.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2766" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-confused_emojis.png" alt="Anna Marie Clifton - Confused emojis divider" width="384" height="128" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-confused_emojis.png 384w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-confused_emojis-300x100.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 384px) 100vw, 384px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>Can you tell me about a time you really struggled with velocity on a project? What happened?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Really early on when I first joined Yammer, I was working on a project that was, engineering-wise, not that expensive. It was a pretty small UI change. We were trying to promote a different type of behaviour and a different flow in the product. But the visual design of it was a really big piece. And I didn’t have a lot of clarity with my designers around what the goal was. And because of that, we floundered for a little while trying to land on a design that everyone was happy with.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We came to a head at one point, where I was like, “Okay, people are frustrated, I’m frustrated, designers are frustrated.” We peeled it back and uncovered that the reason why everything was stuck was that we had two competing goals that were kind of antithetical. And the designers didn’t know how to prioritize between those goals. We wanted users to both feel a sense of completion and we wanted to give them the next thing to do. And those are antithetical goals.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s really easy to look back and talk about that, but at the time I had no idea what was going on. I had no idea that the goals were unclear. I didn’t even really internalize that the goals were antithetical. It took a serious moment of, “Oh fuck, this is about to go real south.” And then we sat down and talked about: what’s going on? And through those conversations, figured out that goals weren’t being clearly established, prioritized and communicated. </span></p>
<p><strong><big>It sounds like it can be really hard to see the things that could impede velocity when you’re in the moment. Is this a skill—or “spidey sense”—you’re constantly working on?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s something that I’m learning about every single week. I’m in probably 8 different projects right now in various stages, and so every single week each of those projects is in a different stage. I can lean into what I’ve learned from one early stage project as I start the next one. I don’t think you ever resolve or finish or uncover or unlock velocity. I think one of those things you have to constantly work towards.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"I don’t think you ever resolve or finish or uncover or unlock velocity."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22I%20don%E2%80%99t%20think%20you%20ever%20resolve%20or%20finish%20or%20uncover%20or%20unlock%20velocity.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2694' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I just made an ongoing list in my brain of things that have gone wrong before. And so as you encounter those problems, you add them to your shitlist. And then you can also have an institutional list that other people have reference points for. “Hey, remember how this goes wrong?” One of the things I’ve done is try to bring in touchpoints into our process that remind us to think about the things that have gone wrong with other projects. Because that can save you a lot of time in the long run if you uncover it early.</span></p>
<p><strong><big>You’ve worked at high-growth companies like Yammer and Asana. How have they paved the way for a healthy amount of product velocity?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">At Yammer a major motivation that we tap into is motivation from autonomy. We have a really strong mode of working where we expect that whoever is closest to the problem should be the one to call what the answer is going to be. I’d had this problem where I had a project team where we wanted to do something, and I had a product manager say, “I don’t think that’s a good idea.” I was like, “Look, I’ve looked into this, I’ve done a lot of work on the ground floor, and I think it’s a good idea, and we’re going to do it.” And he was like, “Okay, cool. I don’t think it’s a good idea, but you’re closer to the problem, so go ahead.” So making sure people who are closest to the problem are the ones who make the calls about what to do.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the things that Asana leans into to promote velocity is that they have a lot of transparency about who’s doing what and when. And that’s by nature, since their product is a tool to figure out who’s doing what. The product you’re building internally is going to have a lot to do with how you operate. Especially when you’re building a workplace collaboration tool. Asana was also very much aligned with the expectation that whoever is closest to the problem should solve it. And they have a lot of explicit transparency into who is supposed to be solving what problems, because every problem is listed in Asana and every Asana task has an assignee. That’s how their product works, and so that’s the way the organization works.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2767" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-angry_emojis.png" alt="Anna Marie Clifton - Angry emojis divider" width="384" height="128" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-angry_emojis.png 384w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-angry_emojis-300x100.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 384px) 100vw, 384px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>We’ve talked about the importance of direction and clarity for velocity. What are some less common pain points you’ve experienced when trying to increase or maintain velocity?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here’s one that’s not very obvious. We have a localized product, which means we have 37 different languages that our product can be used in, and the UI is translated. That means that whenever we add a new piece of UI that has a copy addition, we need to get that localized into 37 different languages. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These are problems that you face at scale; this is not a problem that startups have. But in order to get something shipped, if we want a last-minute copy change, we have to go through our translation service. One of the things you can do as a PM is have your copy really thoroughly vetted, and make sure you get all the right eyes on it and no one’s going to say, “I didn’t see this. I think it needs a few tweaks.” Because a little change like that can mean a couple weeks of delay.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the jobs of the PM is to consider all these different inputs and make sure that you, as you kick off the project, are thinking about what other teams need to get involved. Our engineers run the project management of the actual engineering themselves, but there are a lot of other inputs in user research and analytics and copy design and translation. We could bring in someone to do an accessibility audit too late, and then find there’s a whole bunch of voiceover missing or some elements of the UI aren’t accessible. It’s important to get the right people to consider your feature earlier on in the process. Because if you have to go back and redesign something because someone who only uses a keyboard can’t use it, that’s going to put a huge, huge slowdown on the project.</span></p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><strong><big>With so many inputs and stakeholders to consider, how can interpersonal issues affect velocity?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As we discussed, one of the things that’s been an issue on some of my teams is ambiguity about what to do. If no one knows what you should do about a problem, the whole team will just kind of halt. That’s one of the big roles of a PM: making sure to shelter your team from ambiguity.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sometimes issues comes up where I’m like, “Huh, I have no idea what we should do about that.” If it’s not obvious, I’ll be very explicit about the fact that we’ll handle this at a future point. Then I make a point of figuring out when it’s going to become a blocking issue, versus how many things we’re working on that we would do the same, no matter what we do about this issue. Then I’m like, “Okay, up until next Friday, we can continue working on the project as we were working on it, because everything we’re doing right now does not impact this issue, and no matter how we deal with it, we’d still have to do this other work anyway. So carry on, don’t worry about this one right now. But I’ll be bringing this up in a product team meeting, or I’ll get user research involved, or maybe I’ll dig into analytics and figure out what the answer is or what the answer should be.” And then come back to the team with, “Hey, here’s what we should do.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think it’s a big, big problem if you, as a PM, sit in a meeting and are like, “Yeah, I don’t know what we should do.” I’ve done that before, and I’ve seen my team totally lose all their mojo.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2768" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-happy_emojis.png" alt="Anna Marie Clifton - Happy emojis divider" width="384" height="128" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-happy_emojis.png 384w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-happy_emojis-300x100.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 384px) 100vw, 384px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>So is a big part of velocity giving people a sense of comfort that they’re not going to be wasting time, or making people feel a sense of security?</big></strong></p>
<p><center class="aligncenter"></center><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here’s the thing. A lot of the stuff that we do in software development is really uncertain. And that’s kind of nerve-wracking. Like, I don’t know if this feature is going to be well-received. That’s one level of uncertainty. I don’t know if this feature is going to accomplish what we want to accomplish. I don’t know if the way I’m building this feature is the best way. I don’t know if this is actually going to work in this way. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are so many different things that people on your team don’t know, and it can be debilitating. So whenever something looms up, and it looks like it’s going to threaten my team’s ability to have confidence in what they’re doing, I try and absorb as much of that and deal with that on the PM side. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It comes back to what we said earlier about how it’s so imperative for the PM to align the whole team around the goals. Because those goals will be a guiding light in those times. And there really aren’t right answers; that’s the uncomfortable truth about product management. There are “best guesses” and “probably rights” and “mostly rights,” but there’s not “definitely rights.” And that’s something that is very, very emotionally difficult for a lot of people. I think that’s one of the challenges that you sign up for as a PM, is dealing with that existential angst. One of your jobs is to absorb it away from the team, so they feel confident in moving forward.</span></p>
<p><strong><big>It seems like velocity is as much an emotional question as a tactical question. What “soft skills” are important to velocity?</big></strong></p>
<p><b></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Energy and optimism. That’s so imperative to have on the team, and it doesn’t necessarily have to come from the PM. But the more optimism and energy you have inherent in the humans you’re working with, the more oomph there is to take to a challenge. It’s also really nice to balance the team with a few pessimists so you find those problems.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"That’s one of the big roles of a PM: making sure to shelter your team from ambiguity."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22That%E2%80%99s%20one%20of%20the%20big%20roles%20of%20a%20PM%3A%20making%20sure%20to%20shelter%20your%20team%20from%20ambiguity.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2694' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But a single optimist on the team can bring that energy for everyone. I think there’s a lot of voodoo around that. And that’s something that I’m still spending a lot of time focusing on and trying to understand and lean into a bit more. One of my personal strengths is having a whole bunch of energy. There are always tradeoffs. But it’s a strength that I’m trying to find the best sides of and bring them to my team.</span></p>
<p><strong><big>What are the emotional consequences if velocity just isn’t there?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There’s the compounding issue where it can give you a moral feeling of delay. And that’s really sticky, because you’re not working with contractors, you’re not working with a one-time crew, you’re working with people you’re going to keep working with. And it’s really important to keep thinking about, whatever you do with this project, if it feels like it slowed down a lot at the end, then they’re going to feel that way about you and about your projects and working with you moving forward. You have to manage the feelings as much as anything else.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2769" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-worried_emojis.png" alt="Anna Marie Clifton - Worried emojis divider" width="384" height="128" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-worried_emojis.png 384w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-worried_emojis-300x100.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 384px) 100vw, 384px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>Let’s get tactical. What are the concrete ways you try to enhance velocity?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We’ve already talked about uncovering problems in advance. There’s a system that I like to use here. We have a meeting that we run with our engineers shortly after we kick off work on a project called the edge case bash. And we sit the whole team in a room and have a list of edge cases that have been problems in the past. And then we go over all of the edge cases and we think about, “Okay, how could this edge case affect this product?”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I’ll give you an example. We start with the empty case. And we think about, “What are all the different ways that, if there’s no data here, this could impact this feature?” What happens if someone doesn’t have an image? Or what if they don’t have their name; they just have their email address? Or what if there’s no content in this group yet? Or what if this is a brand new network and they don’t have any groups?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We have a list of about 25 types of edge cases that we go through as a team. And we think about, “How could this be a problem in our project?” And we usually end up with 30 or 40 different edge cases that we come up with in that one hour meeting. And then the PM will go back and consider, okay, how likely are these edge cases to happen, and how bad are they if they do?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You’ll always, always be finding more issues as you go. But this is a super-charged way to uncover as many ugly issues as you can at the beginning. </span></p>
<p><strong><big>What other essential boxes do you check to maintain velocity?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the things a PM can do early on is bring in people from other product domains and bring in issues that might surface.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"You have to manage the feelings as much as anything else."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22You%20have%20to%20manage%20the%20feelings%20as%20much%20as%20anything%20else.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2694' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We have someone who is an accessibility guru and champion internally. I always schedule a meeting with that person really early in the ideation phase to just go over what I’m planning to build and see if there’s anything we should consider. Because what happens at the end of the project is if you didn’t do an accessibility audit early on, someone will come by and be like, “Hey, these are accessibility issues.” And you’ll have to address them and you’ll think you’re about to launch and then you end up delaying a couple weeks because you have to go back and rethink something.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the other things I try to do really studiously is that whenever anything changes during the execution phase, I make the point of surfacing that information as quickly as possible up the chain in product, in case there’s some chance that there’s something I don’t know about, or product may have a competing reason why we shouldn’t do that. So just in case something is going to be a problem, they can surface it early. </span></p>
<p><strong><big>You mentioned the “final mile” in getting a feature to market. What are some of the challenges around velocity in that final mile, and how do you alleviate them?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So much of what we’ve been talking about has been: how do you anticipate problems, and then get them in front of the right people in time so it’s not going to end up delaying your engineers? Your engineers are on one track of work, but there’s a whole bunch of other stuff that happens on other tracks. And the point is, kick those off as early as you can. So that by the time that train comes to the end of the station from an engineering perspective, you don’t have other trains that are still pushing along from accessibility or copy or marketing getting the right messaging out, or things like that. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So the tactical solution there is just, constantly be messaging with your partners in other teams, or partner teams, around what you’re working on or what your timelines are. And make sure you’ve gotten that information to them so you know how much time they need to react.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"One of the ways you can promote velocity best is just by exhibiting it internally."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22One%20of%20the%20ways%20you%20can%20promote%20velocity%20best%20is%20just%20by%20exhibiting%20it%20internally.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2694' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When you join a new team, it’s figuring out, do I need to talk to marketing? Who’s the security person that I talk to about security concerns? Figuring out what all those steps are is a big part of PM onboarding. And every time you run a project, I find something else that I want to add to my list of things that I check for next time. There’s really something about having tenure at an organization that can help you understand what you should be kicking upwind in order to make sure that things don’t drag on at the end. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">My advice there is just that PMs should lean on PMs; shadow other PMs’ projects well into your tenure at a new company. Go to their weekly meetings and listen to the challenges that they’re bringing up and stock that away in your mind when you’re running your projects. </span></p>
<p><strong><big>What is the #1 thing you do to promote velocity in your day-to-day?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the ways you can promote velocity best is just by exhibiting it internally. People see what you do and they watch how you do it. When you come to a project with a lot of energy, and when you’re knocking things off and treating it as a priority, and ensuring that you get back to people quickly, close those loops fast, that communicates to other people what’s reasonable. What your baseline expectations are. They see that that’s what you’re doing for yourself. The biggest signal you can send to people is how you operate.</span></p>
<hr />
<p><em><strong>Shameless self-plug: </strong>One way to stop impeding product velocity? Try one of our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=annamarieclifton" target="_blank">roadmap templates</a> to align the right people on your strategy ahead of time.</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/anna-marie-clifton/">Product velocity is as much emotional as tactical</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Agile roadmap strategies from 5 product managers</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/agile-product-managers/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 16:25:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tarif Rahman]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[agile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[agile product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[agile product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[agile product roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[agile roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[agile roadmap best practices]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[agile roadmap planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[agile roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[what is an agile product roadmap]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2324</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>We pick the brains of five super cool agile product managers to find out how they're approaching their agile roadmapping strategies in real-life. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/agile-product-managers/">Agile roadmap strategies from 5 product managers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many opinions have been expressed (voiced rather strongly?) about agile roadmaps. We’ve heard that </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-roadmaps-counterintuitive-to-agile/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">agile and roadmapping don’t belong together</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, there are certain ways agile roadmaps </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">absolutely must look</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, and even that agile roadmaps are just plain confusing (partially why we offer <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/agile-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=agileproductmanagers">customizable agile roadmap templates</a>). But we had enough of the confusion. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We picked the brains of </span><b>five super cool product managers </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">to find out the reality of agile roadmaps. How are real-world, goal-crushing, </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><del>eternally stressed out</del></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> PMs approaching their agile roadmap strategies? Sharing their roadmapping processes, as well as irksome agile roadmap myths and challenges, these PMs clear the confusion. Here’s who we chatted with:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#breanna"><strong>Breanna Hughes</strong></a>, Senior Product Manager at <strong>League Inc.</strong></li>
<li><a href="#catherine"><strong>Catherine Shyu</strong></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Product Manager at </span><strong>FullContact Inc. </strong></li>
<li><a href="#ahsan"><strong>Ahsan Nanji</strong></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Director of Product Management at </span><strong>Electronic Arts (EA)</strong></li>
<li><a href="#sarah"><strong>Sarah Pyo</strong></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Product Manager at </span><strong>Expedia</strong></li>
<li><a href="#jessica"><b>Jessica Johnson</b></a>, Senior Product Manager at <strong>Goodreads</strong></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h1 id="breanna">Breanna Hughes</h1>
<p><b><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2337 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Breanna.png" alt="Breanna Hughes" width="338" height="345" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Breanna.png 338w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Breanna-294x300.png 294w" sizes="(max-width: 338px) 100vw, 338px" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b>Senior Product Manager<br />
<b>Company: </b>League Inc.<br />
<b>Industry:</b> FinTech<br />
<b>Tweet at her: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/unbrelievable" target="_blank">@unbrelievable</a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>What do you think of when I say agile product roadmap? Go!</b></p>
<p>I guess it would be like a theme-based roadmap. At a high-level, it’s a problem-based roadmap that outlines the central problem. It’s not a roadmap of features and building. It&#8217;s a direction of where you want to go, but being comfortable to iterate as you go.</p>
<p><b>What’s your approach to your agile roadmap?</b></p>
<p>Based on business goals and KPIs we define problems we want to solve for the quarter through discovery. From those discoveries comes a list of features to build or tests to try.</p>
<p>Throughout the quarter we evaluate and reconvene. We take a look on a weekly basis with the product team and a monthly basis with the leadership team and ask, “Hey, do we even bother doing this?” That’s where the agile nature comes in.</p>
<p><b>What’s the biggest misconception around agile and roadmapping that you’ve heard?</b></p>
<p>That timelines don’t exist. There’s always a timeline. There needs to be! You need some sort of frame of reference to say how much you’re willing to invest in this thing—at least in startups. The reality for most startups is you need to know when this is good enough; when do we move on to a different strategic initiative.</p>
<p><b>What do PMs need to know before creating an agile roadmap?</b></p>
<p>KPIs. Definitely need to know why you’re doing it. What is the business impact and your goal for the quarter? You should also know what other teams’ goals are. Make sure you’re not in conflict of one another.</p>
<p>Also, gather tons of feedback. Based on the goals and the areas of the business I want to impact, I’ll talk to stakeholders and customers. Talking to your team is really important too—like your designers and developers. They have great ideas too. Talking to people is the best thing you can do.</p>
<p><b>What is the biggest challenge when creating an agile roadmap?</b></p>
<p>The biggest challenge I think is knowing the potential impact of what you release. You can have all the complex formulas and data scientists in the world helping you, but it’s an educated guess at best. Build small first and then build on top of that. It allows you to better predict what the impact is going to be.</p>
<hr />
<h1 id="catherine"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Catherine Shyu</span></h1>
<p><b><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2339 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Catherine.png" alt="Catherine Shyu" width="338" height="345" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Catherine.png 338w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Catherine-294x300.png 294w" sizes="(max-width: 338px) 100vw, 338px" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Product Manager<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">FullContact Inc.<br />
</span><b>Industry:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Software<br />
</span><b>Tweet at her: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/cthrin" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@cthrin</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>What do you imagine when I say agile product roadmap?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think of a loosely planned roadmap for the future of the product. Ideally it has an underlying structure and product principles the company wants to follow, but the exact items (and timing) have the flexibility to change. </span></p>
<p><b>Walk me through your own agile roadmap. How do you approach this process?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I&#8217;m a visual person, so my roadmap has different swimlanes for each platform. It functions more as a peek into the product vision and where it’s going, so it doesn&#8217;t have dates or sizes attached to it. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Once we start planning for the next quarter, the appropriate roadmap items will move into a new document where engineering can size them. We&#8217;ll end up with an overarching &#8220;Q# List&#8221; of items that product and engineering commit to together. </span></p>
<p><b>What’s the biggest misconception you’ve heard about agile roadmaps?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The biggest misconception I hear is that the words &#8220;agile&#8221; and &#8220;roadmap&#8221; shouldn&#8217;t even go together. Working in agile doesn&#8217;t mean you no longer have to plan ahead. It just signifies a mindset that lets you change direction faster based on incoming feedback from the customers, the market, and so on.   </span></p>
<p><b>What does a PM need to know before starting an agile roadmap?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">An agile roadmap should be directional, and not so detailed that it goes out of date as soon as you share it with people. Unplanned work will always pop up, and there will be projects that other departments need done too. In practice, adding dates to a roadmap often means you&#8217;ll have to update it anytime a date or scope changes. It can quickly become a burden. </span></p>
<p><b>What do you find is the biggest challenge when you’re creating an agile roadmap?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Trying to marry a vision for the future with the reality of time—while not having to update it every day. Roadmaps communicate:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Where a product is going </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Timing of features</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Level of effort required for features</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How features are interconnected and more</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We&#8217;re likely overloading this one document and trying to fit too much detail in there, which then can become out-of-date. The roadmap tries to do so much, and is consumed by so many different stakeholders that every company&#8217;s roadmap is a little different based on their needs.</span></p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<hr />
<h1 id="ahsan"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ahsan Nanji</span></h1>
<p><b><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2341 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Ahsan.png" alt="Ahsan Nanji" width="338" height="345" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Ahsan.png 338w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Ahsan-294x300.png 294w" sizes="(max-width: 338px) 100vw, 338px" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Director of Product Management<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Electronic Arts (EA)<br />
</span><b>Industry:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Gaming<br />
</span><b>Tweet at him: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/DarthEsso" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@DarthEsso</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>When I say the term agile product roadmap, what comes to mind?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">To me an agile product roadmap is one where the actual timeline and ordering of things aren’t necessarily set in stone, but are oriented around customer responses and requests. An agile product roadmap is kind of done with the intention of change being planned into the process. </span></p>
<p><b>Tell me about your own agile roadmap. How does it look?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So what we have is a timeline view of the product that gets broken down into a few different views. One view shows which internal scrum team is working on each feature and which client team adopts which features. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">At a high-level, we always have a clear plan two quarters out, with a detailed release schedule over the next 12 weeks. And then we have a vision that goes at least two fiscal years out from today. We’re really just looking at one single, big roadmap with detailed deliverables and feature specs for one to two quarters. Everything that’s beyond is more aspirational.</span></p>
<p><b>What’s the biggest myth you’ve heard about agile and roadmapping?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think a lot of people assume that agile means there’s not much planning involved. I would say there’s more planning and more communication involved. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">People think that roadmaps handle communication by themselves, and that’s not the case because you’re assuming everyone is monitoring your roadmap as closely as you might be. So you need to actively communicate any roadmap changes and track who might be affected. </span></p>
<p><b>What does a PM need to know before starting an agile roadmap?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are so many ways to answer that! They should definitely know what the dependencies are for work to be completed. They should have a good sense of the estimates for the work that they’re committing to (for anything being delivered in the short-term). They should also really understand what their customers want or need, and in what order.</span></p>
<p><b>What’s your biggest challenge when creating an agile roadmap?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Getting the estimate fidelity and certainty of the schedule, because I know that tends to be the one thing in agile versus waterfall that is a difficult balance to strike. Also, having clear workback plans that give you the confidence that you’re going to actually meet the commitments that you’re making.</span></p>
<hr />
<h1 id="sarah"><span style="font-weight: 400;"></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sarah Pyo</span></h1>
<p><b><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2342 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Sarah.png" alt="Sarah Pyo" width="338" height="345" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Sarah.png 338w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Sarah-294x300.png 294w" sizes="(max-width: 338px) 100vw, 338px" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Product Manager<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Expedia<br />
</span><b>Industry:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Travel &amp; Hospitality<br />
</span><b>Tweet at her: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/spyo" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@spyo</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>When I say agile product roadmap, what do you think of?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I immediately think of timelines and deliveries. Because to me an agile methodology is about getting a team together to continuously deliver in certain timelines. So I really just think of a timeline that can communicate back to my stakeholders within that timeframe.</span></p>
<p><b>Tell me about your own agile roadmap. How do you approach it?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">My team’s approach is more of a hybrid. In order to communicate to my non-technical stakeholders, I need to break it down into swimlanes that are more simplified—and not so engineering focused. So we break up our swimlanes by themes that we’re targeting. These are like customer, marketing and product feature goals we have. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We obviously don’t plan for a full year with agile, so when I put together my roadmap I think 120 days ahead. So tackling what we can deliver in four months and breaking that up by themes and overall goals for our customers. That’s how I break it up. </span></p>
<p><b>How do you plan for your agile roadmap?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I’m really proud of our process over here. Our teams do the daily stand-ups of course. But we also do grooming sessions with just the product team and our technical product manager. (We’ll also have our UX leads in the room.)</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I really rely on those meetings to articulate my thoughts and problems to our leads. Before I can even make an investment, I need to see if it’s something our customers want. We do a lot of discovery before we ship to ensure our use cases are all understood by product. </span></p>
<p><b>What is the biggest obstacle when creating an agile roadmap?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think it comes down to setting expectations for your stakeholders outside of your engineering or UX teams. I know it’ll always be challenging to evangelize what agile is to non-technical teams (there’s a knowledge gap), but it comes down to incorporating those other teams to understand agile processes. </span></p>
<p><b>Do you find having an agile roadmap there helps align those psychologies of time better?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Yeah, it does. We do a few steps when we do our roadmap planning. We do high-level numbers and goals for our target months—that 120 days. Which cycle will we hit this? This is what we’re aiming to do. So we set expectations early-on.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Having that visual of the high-level of what we need to do sets that tone for the team so that they know what they want to complete—the goals they want to achieve.</span></p>
<hr />
<h1 id="jessica">Jessica Johnson</h1>
<p><b><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2334 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Jessica.png" alt="Jessica Johnson" width="338" height="345" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Jessica.png 338w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Agile_PM-Jessica-294x300.png 294w" sizes="(max-width: 338px) 100vw, 338px" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b><br />
Title: </b>Senior Product Manager<br />
<b>Company: </b>Goodreads<br />
<b>Industry:</b> Social “cataloguing”<br />
<b>Tweet at her: </b>She doesn&#8217;t tweet, so <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jessjo/" target="_blank">connect on LinkedIn</a>!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>What do you think of when I say the term agile product roadmap?</b></p>
<p>Having your cake and eating it too. Everyone wants the speed of agile work but the predictive visibility of a roadmap. While agile on its own is great, I’ve yet to see a larger company be comfortable running totally agile—so you definitely need to find middle ground.</p>
<p><b>Tell me about your own agile roadmap. How does it look?</b></p>
<p>I’m a big fan of hybrid approaches. I like roadmaps that use swimlanes to talk more about allocation to a problem than predicted results.</p>
<p>Sure, some major projects with set requirements end up more waterfall, but when you have a problem with no clear end goal, it’s useful to know how much time you can devote. Saying, “Let’s see what we can do in two sprints” is way more accurate than, “It will take us two sprints to get to x outcome.”</p>
<p><b>Do you think there are best practices in place for creating an agile roadmap?</b></p>
<p>I think there’s constantly a healthy tension about how much clarity you can create versus how much flexibility you need. On a perfect product team it should adapt. Sometimes becoming more predictable and sometimes giving more slack depending on the scope of the problem.</p>
<p><b>What’s the biggest myth you’ve heard about agile roadmaps?</b></p>
<p>That you don’t need a roadmap if you’re agile! The larger your team gets and the more coordination you need across teams, the more important a roadmap becomes. Sure roadmaps are imperfect, but without them coordination is impossible.</p>
<p><b>How do you plan for your agile roadmap?</b></p>
<p>There’s a lot of background work in figuring out the priority and dependencies of initiatives. It’s unseen work, but it’s so critical. Digging into data and research; understanding how much time problems might take; coordinating and negotiating with stakeholders. If you don’t do this in advance, you won’t have the right roadmap. After this, it’s just a matter of making the pieces fit with your team’s resources.</p>
<p><b>What do you find is the biggest challenge when you’re creating a roadmap in agile?</b></p>
<p>Knowing that even the best laid plans go awry! Despite knowing in advance, it’s hard to be honest and reconcile when you don’t have the time you thought for that pet project.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/agile-product-managers/">Agile roadmap strategies from 5 product managers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Inside Breather: Working in product at a rapidly scaling startup</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/christine-montgomery/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 16:46:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[growth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management career]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[startup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[startup culture]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2258</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Since starting as employee 100 at Breather, Christine Montgomery has seen the startup double in size. She chats with us about her first year as a product manager at a rapidly scaling startup.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/christine-montgomery/">Inside Breather: Working in product at a rapidly scaling startup</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Christine Montgomery was employee 100 at <a href="http://www.breather.com" target="_blank">Breather</a>, a Montreal-based startup that rents on-demand, <em>Architectural Digest</em>-esque workspaces by the hour. In the year since Christine joined the company, Breather’s headcount has doubled. And their product has expanded to new markets across North America and around the world.</p>
<p>That’s a lot of growth. And with that much growth comes huge opportunity—but also way more complexity. After years working in product at a legacy media company, where processes were deeply entrenched, Christine traded tried-and-true for chaotic-but-way-more-creative. She shares some observations from her first year as a product manager at a rapidly scaling startup.</p>
<p><strong><big>Why did you want to join Breather?</big></strong></p>
<p>It was one of those things where I went to the website and immediately understood what they were trying to do. It clicked right away. But I was particularly attracted to working with a physical product and working in the realm of service design where software actually meets the way people interact with space. And I was really attracted to the idea of working with an interior design team. Immediately when I saw Breather, it clicked.</p>
<p><strong><big>Coming from a corporate background, were there any “habits” you had to break?</big></strong></p>
<p>At my last company, despite it being large, the digital team very much worked in an agile environment. We were almost in a silo for a good portion of when I was there. We were heavily, heavily processed, but that process worked very effectively. And when I came to Breather, we did not have any process at all. I was used to having a partner and a scrum master. I had to readjust and embrace the chaos of a startup. And figure out how to deliver value in that environment.</p>
<p>And the other thing, which was so extremely positive, was I think when you work in large companies, there’s almost a manipulation of the facts. At Breather, there are so many really strong people who work here who want a really honest understanding of how effective our product is. I like the upfrontness of a startup. That was super refreshing.</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><strong><big>What are biggest product lessons you’ve learned since you started at Breather?</big></strong></p>
<p>So the first one, as I was touching on before, is to embrace chaos, be comfortable with vagueness, and focus on value. If I had to pick one thing, it’s absolutely that. It’s really challenging. But you always have to be thinking: what’s the most valuable? It’s okay that we don’t have a process for this. It’s okay that we’re still figuring it out, because we know what the mission is, and we’re going to find what’s valuable.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"I have no idea what this is. And I have to lead this team. And everyone knows more than me."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22I%20have%20no%20idea%20what%20this%20is.%20And%20I%20have%20to%20lead%20this%20team.%20And%20everyone%20knows%20more%20than%20me.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2258' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>Another thing is: treat everything you build like it could be thrown out. In product management now everyone has really embraced this MVP and fast delivery culture, which is amazing. And you really need to be able to live and breathe that, because we’re still discovering what our product is. So everything we do must be fast and unprecious.</p>
<p><strong><big>What are some of the ways you focus on value amid chaos?</big></strong></p>
<p>I try not to worry too much about frameworks. I do think they’re important, and becoming increasingly important as we grow. But one of the mistakes we made as a product org in the past year is to be very focused on process, versus people-focused.</p>
<p>It can definitely be challenging to focus on value when you’re a scaling startup. In my last position, it was very easy to be data-driven because it was a legacy product where we knew everything about it, we had a very established API. We had all of our tools in place to measure. Whereas at a startup, we’re still building those things. You really have to focus on how well an initiative aligns with the mission of the company and the key strategies.</p>
<p><strong><big>Are there business advantages that come out of chaos?</big></strong></p>
<p>The advantage of chaos in a scaling business is speed and independence. There are times when it’s been unclear what’s going on, or who owns what, but the benefit is that innovation can come out of that. It gives people autonomy to try new things.</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-2309 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.20.32-PM-copy-300x182.png" alt="" width="874" height="530" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.20.32-PM-copy-300x182.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.20.32-PM-copy-768x465.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.20.32-PM-copy-1024x620.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.20.32-PM-copy.png 1076w" sizes="(max-width: 874px) 100vw, 874px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>What are the hardest parts of being on a product team at a company that’s growing so quickly?</big></strong></p>
<p>One major challenge for us is that Breather became international very quickly. We have spaces in Canada, in the UK, all over the US, and we’re expanding elsewhere very soon. So ensuring there’s strong communication and a strong feedback loop when you get international so quickly is definitely a challenge. We have people all around the world who really understand the business and especially understand it on the ground in their city. And keeping those communication lines open has been a challenge that we’ve had to overcome.</p>
<p>I think you go through a bit of a pendulum when you’re scaling. We have gone from being very, very centralized and very slow as a product team, but very thorough, to being very chaotic. We did this whole cross-functional transformation that made us very, very tied with the engineering team. We were going a lot quicker, but then we suffered on the communication side.</p>
<p>So now we’ve swung the pendulum another way towards being an engineering-focused product team. I think a big challenge has been that pendulum back-and-forth. We’ll probably continue to swing, but that’s what the job is.</p>
<p><strong><big>Can you map out more specifically how your product org has evolved since you started at Breather?</big></strong></p>
<p>When I started, we had an independent product team, and we very much worked in a waterfall. We had a pretty dry backlog, and it was very heavy in terms of actually getting to the point where we would work with the delivery team. We recognized this as a problem, and said, “What can we do about it?”</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"You can’t solve communication, but oftentimes the answers to improving it are quite simple."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22You%20can%E2%80%99t%20solve%20communication%2C%20but%20oftentimes%20the%20answers%20to%20improving%20it%20are%20quite%20simple.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2258' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>So we went cross-functional. And we just went headfirst into it. And then we had product managers very integrated into delivery teams, but we did not maintain the centralized function of a product org at that time. At this point we did not have dry backlogs anymore, but coordination suffered and vision suffered, and being able to connect the work to the mission was also something that we had to work through. So Breather right now is moving into this dual-track product discovery methodology where we maintain a centralized product org, who collectively think about the delivery of our product and the whole customer journey.</p>
<p><strong><big>How do you stay close to the customer when also dealing with the pressures (and chaos) of rapid growth?</big></strong></p>
<p>We have a user research team here. We have an insights team that leads the charge on ensuring that we know our personas and that we’re doing analysis on qualitative and quantitative data. But we’re still figuring out how to account for local nuances. I see that as a challenge that we’ll always have.</p>
<p>When you go into new countries, there are certain things that we didn’t think about in terms of product. We’re used to certain kinds of search methods, whereas in a different country they’re actually used to a very different pattern. Payment methods differ from country-to-country. So it’s great to have global teams embedded and to be listening to them, because they provide a great feedback loop for us in terms of: what are the major considerations we need to bring to the product to be able to understand localization?</p>
<p><strong><big>What are some of the strategies you put in place to improve communication?</big></strong></p>
<p>One thing we’re working on right now, it sounds really simple, but it’s release checklists and communication checklists. I was reading a book recently—this was kind of how this came about—called <a href="http://atulgawande.com/book/the-checklist-manifesto/" target="_blank">The Checklist Manifesto</a>. It’s written by a surgeon who talks about implementing checklists in surgery. Surgeons, because they have such a complicated job and they have so much to consider, often forget about the basics. They don’t remember the patient’s name. This happens when you work in complex environments. People always think that simple things are redundant. But I’m trying to find those simple wins.</p>
<p>I really believe communication will never be solved by anybody in a company. It will never be perfect. You have to repeat things a hundred times. You can’t solve communication, but oftentimes the answers to improving it are quite simple.</p>
<p><strong><big>Are there any other processes you would like to put in place to help manage growth?</big></strong></p>
<p>On the delivery side, I’m a huge fan of self-organizing, agnostic, cross-functional teams. I actually am not super keen with developers being associated to a function. I think they should first and foremost form small teams based on people they think they work well with. Then you have teams that are made up of people who like working with each other, and those are always the most successful teams.</p>
<p>What I’ve seen in the past is that you end up having certain teams that like the more business-as-usual, administrative stuff. And there are other teams who want to do the crazy, hacky stuff. And you let them float there. So I would love to see that happen.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"Everything we do must be fast and unprecious."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22Everything%20we%20do%20must%20be%20fast%20and%20unprecious.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2258' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>The other one, which I’m very keen on, is this idea of iterative research. We’ve gotten really, really good at rapid delivery. And understanding MVP and getting small chunks of software out that provide incremental value. We’re so good at that. But I think where the product community still has so much opportunity to grow is applying the same methodology to how we research and how we understand what our products are. So we get away from the point where we’ve done a 4-month project on building user segments and those are our segments for the next year. It’s like, “How do we break that up?” We can learn a lot from MVP, agile delivery methods and be a lot more iterative about research.</p>
<p><strong><big>How would iterative research manifest in reality?</big></strong></p>
<p>I think an example of that would be, let’s say you’re building your personas. You don’t need to wait until you know exactly who your personas are and you’ve synthesized the data and done all the quantitative and qualitative analysis to understand your persona. You can do an interview and ship it and that becomes part of it. And then you can do a survey, put it out there, and iterate again. You don’t have to wait until all the pieces are together.</p>
<p><strong><big>From a personal perspective, what’s been your most stressful moment and your most gratifying moment from the past year?</big></strong></p>
<p>In terms of personal chaos, I moved into an operations role in the company having no idea what I was doing. My boss was like, “I think this would be an amazing focus for you, I think it really complements your skill set. As product manager, communication and organization are some of your strong suits, so I think you’ll be really good at this.” And I was like, “What is he talking about? I have a demand background. I come from a content and marketing space, I have no idea what this is. And I have to lead this team. And everyone knows more than me.”</p>
<p>It ended up that my most stressful moment is my most gratifying, because I actually did end up loving it. And found out that it was something that worked really well for me. And it was gratifying in the sense that I got to learn about this entirely new side of the business that I had no familiarity with, but that I’m actually super interested in and very excited about.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone wp-image-2311" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/14294732_168958650175365_4510570780198699008_n-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="360" height="360" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/14294732_168958650175365_4510570780198699008_n-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/14294732_168958650175365_4510570780198699008_n-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/14294732_168958650175365_4510570780198699008_n-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/14294732_168958650175365_4510570780198699008_n-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/14294732_168958650175365_4510570780198699008_n-1.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 360px) 100vw, 360px" />  <img class="alignnone wp-image-2312" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.18.25-PM-300x300.png" alt="" width="360" height="360" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.18.25-PM-300x300.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.18.25-PM-150x150.png 150w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.18.25-PM-768x765.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.18.25-PM-1024x1020.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.18.25-PM.png 1077w" sizes="(max-width: 360px) 100vw, 360px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>Looking forward to the next year, how do you see your product team and yourself as a product manager evolving to meet the needs of growth?</big></strong></p>
<p>I think as we grow what I’m really looking forward to is focus. You wear many, many hats as a product manager in a scaling startup, and you do a lot of different roles that are outside of what you would traditionally consider product management. And that’s awesome. It’s really cool to be able to do that, but I also look forward to focusing on long-term product initiatives. And just as I said you have to treat everything like you can throw it out in a minute, it’s going to be awesome as well to do some long-term thinking.</p>
<p>We have some room to think about these really cool, innovative, R&amp;D-oriented product things. And because we work with physical space and software, there’s going to be a lot of really interesting things coming out of Breather in next year or two in terms of product that are very—for the lack of a better word—futuristic.</p>
<p>What fun. What more could a product-and-technology-oriented person want than to be working on the latest things and to be working on innovation?</p>
<hr />
<p><em><strong>Note from Roadmunk: </strong>If you&#8217;re an organization experiencing rapid scaling, a roadmap miiight be just what you need. Check out our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=christinemontgomery" target="_blank">template library</a> to start aligning that growing headcount.</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/christine-montgomery/">Inside Breather: Working in product at a rapidly scaling startup</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How 6 product designers tackle friction with product managers</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-designers/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2017 17:26:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tarif Rahman]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product designer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product strategy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ui]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ux]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1765</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>We chat with 6 super-talented product designers about what they think product managers can do to reduce friction with their design team. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-designers/">How 6 product designers tackle friction with product managers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">At successful product organizations, </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/jeremy-bailey/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">product and design teams work together like a perfect couple</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. But even for the most picture-perfect couples, friction is inevitable. The product manager-product designer duo can be particularly guilty of contention thanks to high-stress scenarios and major product decisions. If you’re a PM finding tension in your relationship with your design team, you </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">might</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> not be communicating with your designers enough. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We chatted with</span><b> six super-talented product designers </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">to find out the most enjoyable and not-so-enjoyable parts of working with a PM, and the communication strategies they think PMs should implement to reduce friction with their designers. Advice from these designers ranges from defining the heck out of your problem, to looking beyond direct competitors for design ideas, to squashing design assumptions by interacting with real-live users. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These product designers aren’t just here to make your product pretty; their advice will help you better understand and connect with your design team. Here’s who we spoke with:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong><a href="#catt">Catt Small</a></strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Product Designer at </span><strong>Etsy</strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="#alvin">Alvin Hsia</a></strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Experience Designer at </span><strong>Airbnb</strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="#lydia">Lydia White</a></strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Product Design Lead at </span><strong>Tumblr </strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="#janko">Janko Jovanovic</a></strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Senior User Experience Designer at </span><strong>Contentful</strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="#sanette">Sanette Tanaka</a></strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Product Designer at </span><strong>Vox Media, Inc.</strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="#diogenes">Diógenes Brito</a></strong>, Product Designer and Engineer at <strong>Slack</strong></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h1 id="catt">Catt Small</h1>
<p><b><img class="alignleft wp-image-1935 size-medium" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Catt-300x201.png" alt="Catt Small" width="300" height="201" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Catt-300x201.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Catt.png 418w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></b></p>
<p><b><br />
Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Product Designer<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Etsy<br />
</span><b>Industry:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> E-commerce<br />
</span><b>Tweet at her: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/cattsmall" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@cattsmall</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>What do you enjoy most about working with a PM on a product’s design?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">PMs have a strategic mindset with a heavy focus on where the product is headed. And that’s great because, as a product designer, I’m thinking about the user’s perspective and how that fits into the business line. So when we get together, it’s much better for the direction of the product. </span></p>
<p><b>What is the main source of friction when working with a PM on a product’s design? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The biggest source of friction I’ve found is giving designs the time they need to be refined, but also ensuring we’re meeting timelines. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There’s this attachment designers get where we have this amazing thing we’ve considered, but often this &#8216;okay&#8217; state gets released. It sometimes is better to just get something out and then improve upon it. So it can be a positive, but you have to actually iterate upon things because sometimes those ‘halfway’ designs release and they never get looked at again.  </span></p>
<p><b>What are some tactical things about product design you think all PMs can do to better communicate with designers? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">PMs should go into projects without assumptions. Based on larger numbers, one can say, “Oh, on average this is how people are.” But when you talk to individuals and gather qualitative data on people’s reasoning, you realize the many different user segments. It can be harmful to think of your users as a monolith. Once you abandon that way of thinking you can become a better, tactical strategist.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Also, participate in a design sprint. After we did a design sprint for a project, everyone was just more excited about design—especially the PMs. You’ll feel a lot closer to your designers and find it easier to communicate.</span></p>
<p><b>What’s one communication strategy you think PMs should adopt?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Asking more questions of designers. The best PMs I’ve worked with have asked of me directly instead of planning for me, or speaking for me, or saying “Hey Catt, we figured out this thing, now make it look nice.” It leads to this feeling of autonomy and ownership.</span></p>
<p><b>In your opinion, a PM can make a product designer’s life easier by…?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Trusting them. Trusting that where product designers are coming from is a place of genuine care for the users. And trusting that we have a special expertise that somewhat overlaps with product management but has its own perspective and is just as important. </span></p>
<p><a href="http://cattsmall.com/portfolio/" target="_blank"><b>Check out Catt’s design work here.</b></a></p>
<hr />
<h1 id="alvin">Alvin Hsia</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-medium wp-image-1943 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Alvin-300x200.png" alt="Alvin Hsia" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Alvin-300x200.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Alvin.png 418w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><br />
Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Experience Designer<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Airbnb<br />
</span><b>Industry:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Travel &amp; Hospitality<br />
</span><b>Tweet at him: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/alvinhsia" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@alvinhsia</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>When working with a PM on a product’s design, what&#8217;s the most enjoyable part?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I enjoy working with my PM to create the one-pager ahead of a project. Being super clear about why you&#8217;re doing something and how it improves the user experience and/or achieves business objectives helps guide decision-making down the road. </span></p>
<p><b>On the flip side, what is the biggest challenge when working with a PM on a product’s design? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Thankfully this hasn&#8217;t happened in a while now, but my biggest pet peeve is when a PM says something along the lines of, &#8220;I did all the wireframes and now I just need you to design it.&#8221; It&#8217;s totally OK to give specific design feedback and whiteboard together, but when a PM is spending a ton of time in prototyping tools, that&#8217;s usually a red flag.</span></p>
<p><b>I can see how that’d be frustrating. How do you alleviate situations like this? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I find the healthiest way to resolve product design disputes is to prototype and user test. As a designer, you should be willing to explore multiple solutions even if you&#8217;ve found the &#8220;right&#8221; one. As a PM, you should be able to discard previously held assertions in light of new evidence. </span></p>
<p><b>What’s one tactical thing about product design you think all PMs should learn? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Know when to bring in user research. If you don&#8217;t have a researcher, get one. If you really can&#8217;t get one, come up with a research plan together. When evidence is lacking, decisions can easily be made by the loudest voice in the room. You can save a lot of time and energy by talking to real users. </span></p>
<p><b>What’s one strategy you think PMs can adopt to better communicate with product designers?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It&#8217;s important for PMs to keep the team progressing against goals, which requires scoping and prioritization. Sometimes this means saying &#8220;no&#8221;, but the best PMs will say, &#8220;Yes—love that. Now let&#8217;s figure out how to get there.&#8221; Of course you won&#8217;t get to everything, but you can get a rough estimate of impact and effort along key milestones.</span></p>
<p><b>Complete the phrase. PMs can make a product designer’s life easier by…?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Creating a structure for the entire team (engineering, research, data science) to ideate and solve together. It gets buy-in across all functions earlier on and people end up feeling more invested in their work. Magic happens when art and science come together.<br />
</span><br />
<a href="http://portfolio.alvinhsia.com/" target="_blank"><b>Check out Alvin’s design work here.</b></a></p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<hr />
<h1 id="lydia">Lydia White</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-medium wp-image-1945 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Lydia-300x201.png" alt="Lydia White" width="300" height="201" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Lydia-300x201.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Lydia.png 418w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><br />
Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Product Design Lead<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tumblr<br />
</span><b>Industry:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Social networking<br />
</span><b>Tweet at her: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/lydiawwwhite" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@lydiawwwhite</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>What do you like most about working with a PM on a product’s design?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I would say the best relationships I’ve had with PMs are very collaborative. The whole idea of working together to push each other and figure out the right questions to ask is probably the most enjoyable part. </span></p>
<p><b>Can you give us an example of when you and a PM had clashed over a product design? How did you you resolve the situation?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Design works best when you’re given a problem to solve instead of a specific execution. In the past, I’ve been given a specific execution that’s narrow in scope, versus addressing the overall problem. That can be problematic because when you execute on that and even if you propose other solutions, there’s a stubbornness to execute a certain way.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">To resolve this, it comes back to seeing data and seeing results. Being able to know more through user testing, A/B testing, etc. lets you gauge what was working and judge from there. </span></p>
<p><b>What’s one tactical thing about product design you think all PMs should do to better collaborate with designers? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">PMs should expand their world of references. This might be because I work at a social networking site, but it seems like every other day I’m asked to do something because someone saw it on Facebook, Instagram, or LinkedIn. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Certainly you can learn from these industry leaders, as they’ve A/B tested each button into oblivion. But it doesn&#8217;t mean it&#8217;s right for our users and it certainly won&#8217;t help us innovate. I appreciate when PMs expose me to new things (another app, physical product, or even a way of thinking) that help us approach our thinking differently. </span></p>
<p><b>Do you think there are strategies PMs can adopt to better communicate with product designers?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Oh, yes! Communicate often. Over-communicate everything. Document everything. Hold kick-off meetings when you’re starting a project that clearly defines what the problems are. Go over what central blockers might be, what are we trying to sell for our users, what do we already know, etc. And when reviewing things, have a clear idea about the goal and feedback.</span></p>
<p><b>A PM can make a product designer’s life easier by…?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">By clearly defining the problem. And the problem not only for the business, but what it is we are trying to solve for the user.  </span></p>
<p><a href="http://lydiaw.net/" target="_blank"><b>Check out Lydia’s design work here.</b></a></p>
<hr />
<h1 id="janko">Janko Jovanovic</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-medium wp-image-1947 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Janko-300x200.png" alt="Janko Jovanovic" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Janko-300x200.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Janko.png 418w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><br />
Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Senior User Experience Designer<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Contentful<br />
</span><b>Industry:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> IT<br />
</span><b>Tweet at him: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/jankowarpspeed" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@jankowarpspeed</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>What’s your favorite part about working with a PM on a product’s design?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I really enjoy the concept of co-ownership when it comes to strategic planning. At the end somebody has to make a call, but if we work together towards a shared goal, I think it makes life easier for both sides. </span></p>
<p><b>What is the biggest obstacle when working with a PM on a product’s design? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think it’s challenging to determine who makes a decision, who’s flexible, who makes the plan for it, and so on. I think PMs feel comfortable making those decisions, but UX people can wear multiple hats and often that overlaps. </span></p>
<p><b>How do you solve for that overlap?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Again I will go back to co-ownership. To me that’s the one that worked—not with everybody though. It can be hard to communicate your point of view to PMs, but if you get them to understand the benefits of UX, that’s definitely helpful when sharing goals. </span></p>
<p><b>What’s one tactical thing regarding product design you think all PMs should learn to better communicate with designers? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I really believe that PMs who want to be good at their jobs should be educated about user-centric design or design thinking—especially if they’re not coming from that design field. I have a PM here that has an </span><a href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/book/the-encyclopedia-of-human-computer-interaction-2nd-ed/human-computer-interaction-brief-intro" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">HCI background</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">; it’s so smooth to work with him. I feel that there are a lot of online courses that are not that expensive that can help with the basics.</span></p>
<p><b>A PM can make your life as a product designer easier by…?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Apart from educating themselves, by being involved in the creative process. In many instances PMs don’t want to be part of the creative process, which is such a waste. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think it’s also on our plates as designers. We can’t expect that they should just know what they should be doing. We should be inviting them to a design studio, asking for their feedback and explaining things to them. </span></p>
<p><a href="http://www.jankoatwarpspeed.com/work/" target="_blank"><b>Check out Janko’s design work here.</b></a></p>
<hr />
<h1 id="sanette">Sanette Tanaka</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-medium wp-image-1949 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Sanette-300x201.png" alt="Sanette Tanaka" width="300" height="201" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Sanette-300x201.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Sanette.png 418w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><br />
Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Product Designer<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Vox Media, Inc.<br />
</span><b>Industry:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Media<br />
</span><b>Tweet at her: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/ssktanaka" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@ssktanaka</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>What’s the most enjoyable part about working with a PM on a product’s design?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A good PM can be a designer&#8217;s best ally in making the product’s design as good as possible. I really enjoy working with PMs who have a strong vision for the product and understand the importance of advocating for the user. </span></p>
<p><b>Can you provide an example of an instance when you and a PM butted heads over a product design and how you resolved the situation?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I once worked with a PM who settled on a product solution very quickly. The solution wasn’t bad, but it hadn’t been subjected to a design process, and I didn’t feel that we had done enough explorations to back the solution. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I raised my concerns, but we were already too far into the project to backtrack. We eventually agreed to build in extra time for testing and iterating on that solution. It wasn’t ideal, but we made it work.</span></p>
<p><b>What’s one thing about product designers you would want all PMs to learn?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This sounds basic, but you’d be surprised how many PMs see all designers as more or less interchangeable. Depending on the company, product designers can be responsible for research, visuals, the user experience, code, interactions, motion, and so forth. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">PMs should take the time to speak with their designers to learn about their areas of expertise in order to understand their strengths and working style.</span></p>
<p><b>What’s one communication strategy you think PMs should adopt when working with product designers?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The top communication strategy I think all PMs should learn is how to give good feedback to a designer. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The golden rule of design is that every product decision should be intentional. So designers give feedback by asking questions (“Have you considered… ?” “Why did you… ?” “What happens if… ?” ). This invites conversation and helps us learn the context of the other person’s work. Likewise, PMs would do well to critique a design by asking questions.</span></p>
<p><b>Finish the thought. PMs can make life for a product designer easier by…?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Setting a clear vision of why we’re building a product, and what problem we are trying to solve.</span></p>
<p><a href="http://www.sanettetanaka.com/" target="_blank"><b>Check out Sanette’s design work here.</b></a></p>
<hr />
<h1 id="diogenes">Diógenes Brito</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-medium wp-image-1951 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Diogenes-300x200.png" alt="Diogenes Brito" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Diogenes-300x200.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Product_designers-Diogenes.png 418w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><br />
Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Product Designer and Engineer<br />
</span><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Slack<br />
</span><b>Industry:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> SaaS<br />
</span><b>Tweet at him: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/uxdiogenes" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@uxdiogenes</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>What do you enjoy most about working with a PM on a product’s design?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Well, it’s a pretty different experience depending on who you’re working with and where you’re working, but in an ideal world it would be focusing more completely on design-specific problems and less on cross-functional communications and project management aspects. </span></p>
<p><b>What do you find to be the biggest challenge when working with a PM on a product’s design? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The lack of uniformity in how different PMs do their job is the biggest hill to climb. There’s a lot of syncing up on expectations from both sides and figuring out what they think their job is and what they think my job is and how we can work together. </span></p>
<p><b>So how do you climb this hill?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">By having an explicit conversation early on. Asking questions like: “What is your process?” “What do you expect from a designer?” And then stating: “Here’s what I expect.” “Here’s where I think we can communicate and check-in.” It’s about making explicit the things you would normally not even think to say aloud and you would naturally assume. </span></p>
<p><b>What’s one tactical thing about product design you think all PMs should do? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When evaluating designs, PMs should go back to the goals upfront. That way the stage is set for the right kind of feedback, in the right order. That’s something I think PMs can use additional training for, so that they can get good design out of designers. </span></p>
<p><b>What strategies do you think PMs can adopt to better communicate with product designers?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I always look to see if there&#8217;s a single place to go to determine what the deal is with the project and what’s upcoming. I think making things concrete and laying them out where everyone can see is important for PMs to do. I should be leaving every meeting with an understanding of the next steps. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I also look for clear information about decision-making. What sort of decisions are we able to make on our own? Are we expected to consult with everyone before making a decision? </span></p>
<p><b>PMs can make a product designer’s life easier by…?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Making sure that the problem and why we’re doing it is always clear to everyone. Especially if it’s been changed recently from above or there are rumours about it changing for some cross-functional reason or constraint. That has to be always super, super clear. </span></p>
<p><a href="http://uxdiogenes.com/projects/" target="_blank"><b>Check out Diógenes’ design work here.</b></a></p>
<hr />
<p><strong><em>Tip from Roadmunk:</em></strong><em> One way to manage friction between PMs and designers is through alignment. Our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=productdesigners" target="_blank">20+ customizable roadmap templates</a> can help get everyone on the same page (and ease any tension). </em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-designers/">How 6 product designers tackle friction with product managers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Self-disrupting with Wattpad&#8217;s head of emerging products</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/tarun-sachdeva/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 16:30:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product strategy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tarun sachdeva]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wattpad]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1844</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>We chat with Tarun Sachdeva, Head of Emerging Products at Wattpad, about his lab-style, experimental process for self-disruption and what that disruption actually looks like in the real world. Spoiler: It’s not just about making cool shit.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/tarun-sachdeva/">Self-disrupting with Wattpad&#8217;s head of emerging products</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For early-stage companies, reaching product-market fit is an enormous milestone. But it’s hardly the finish line. Every product—even a young, shiny, super-popular product—is at risk of disruption.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tarunsachdeva/" target="_blank">Tarun Sachdeva</a> leads the Emerging Products team at <a href="http://www.wattpad.com" target="_blank">Wattpad</a>, a Toronto startup that’s built a massive platform for storytellers. Wattpad is a thriving community of creative folks. And while they’re going strong—almost 50 million users strong (!)—they’re taking a proactive approach to potential disruption. <strong>Tarun’s team was specifically created to preempt new players in their market.</strong></p>
<p>But while Tarun engages a lab-style, experimental process, his team is not conducting &#8220;maybe someday&#8221; experiments. They are explicitly driven towards solving real problems for their current and new markets. We chatted with Tarun about what self-disruption actually looks like in the real world (i.e. for real users).</p>
<p><strong>Spoiler:</strong> It’s not just about making cool shit.</p>
<p><strong><big>Tell us about your role. How are you self-disrupting?</big></strong></p>
<p>My role at Wattpad right now is head of emerging products and partnerships. The team was formed with the objective to find new markets and value networks for Wattpad. If you’re familiar with the <a href="http://www.claytonchristensen.com/key-concepts/" target="_blank">Clay Christensen school of thought</a>, you know what that means: trying to find a way to disrupt Wattpad from within Wattpad.</p>
<p>When we look at Wattpad’s growth over the last five years, we’ve seen us get to <strong>almost 50 million users across the world</strong>, and we’ve done a really great job in building this incredible community of storytellers and audiences and brands that are interacting with each other.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><hr /><p><em>"My role explores what else is out there, based on a hypothesis that things will change."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22My%20role%20explores%20what%20else%20is%20out%20there%2C%20based%20on%20a%20hypothesis%20that%20things%20will%20change.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1844' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></span></p></blockquote>
<p>And now, in some senses, we’re seen as the incumbent.<strong> And we want to make sure we are constantly exploring the next frontiers.</strong> We’re constantly reevaluating how we achieve our vision to connect and entertain the entire world through stories, but with the tools and the technology that are available to us today. So if Wattpad were reinvented today, would it look the same as it does right now? Probably the answer to that is “no.”</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><strong><big>Wattpad is still a startup. How did you realize it was already time to think about self-disruption?</big></strong></p>
<p>We’ve started to see—and this is true not just for Wattpad, but for a lot of products—the market around us has started to move. There are new capabilities in terms of what phones can do today. And those are different, obviously, than what was available when Wattpad started. There are new technologies like machine learning and artificial intelligence that are making it possible to interact with technology in new and interesting ways.</p>
<p>The ways in which we’re interacting with technology is becoming more frictionless, and the concept of us going to technology to accomplish a task is becoming less and less relevant. It’s more that we speak to our technology; we live in our technology. It’s also very immersive, so we’re noticing a lot of these larger trends that are happening around us: new platforms, new technology, that have forced us to say, “Hey, let’s take a step back and explore what that next frontier of storytelling looks like.”</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1908 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/TS_divider-2.png" alt="Round-bottom flask - divider" width="128" height="128" /></p>
<p><strong><big>So is your central question: &#8220;If we were to start all over, what would we do?&#8221;</big></strong></p>
<p>It’s more that we always look to our vision as the North Star. Which is to entertain and connect the world through stories. So we think about: how can we do that based on what is available today? We built a really, really incredible product and community, and a really great operation to support that and make sure that continues growing.</p>
<p>My role explores what else is out there, based on a hypothesis that things will change. <strong>The world around us will change whether or not we like it. It’s our choice to respond to that actively or to let it happen to us, and react to it.</strong> So what we’ve decided to do is choose the former path, and take an active stance in exploring that, understanding it better, trying a lot of different things, and seeing what sticks.</p>
<p><strong><big>Tell us about some of the “different things” you’re trying.</big></strong></p>
<p>We’re trying a lot of things along a few different horizons. One of the horizons is looking at new platforms of computing—things like new consumer technologies like Alexa and Echo. There are these new consumer products that people have started to interact with that didn’t exist before. What is the role of storytelling in those products?</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"Ultimately, our goal as an organization is to make sure that we’re continuing to innovate."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22Ultimately%2C%20our%20goal%20as%20an%20organization%20is%20to%20make%20sure%20that%20we%E2%80%99re%20continuing%20to%20innovate.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1844' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>There’s looking at existing platforms like mobile, and looking at new ways that you can enable storytelling on those platforms. And it’s also thinking about—because Wattpad is a network and we believe strongly in community—how people share and network around stories today. It’s effectively trying out new mediums of storytelling in existing networks and existing mediums, and trying out new mediums altogether.</p>
<p><strong><big>Is there any particular structure or constraints you have around your processes of exploration?</big></strong></p>
<p>There is always a purpose to what we are doing. And we want to make sure that we’re not just building for the sake of building. We are building based on a specific hypothesis. We work under this umbrella of <strong>hypothesis-driven development</strong>, where we make a hypothesis around what effect we believe a certain trend is going to have, or how this platform is going to grow. We make that hypothesis, and then we test that out. If you build without that, you don’t really know what success looks like. You build something, and then you’re like, “Okay, well, what was the objective?” What were you actually trying to prove or disprove?</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1915 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/TS_divider-5.png" alt="Test tubes - divider" width="128" height="128" /></p>
<p>And by consistently making sure we have a hypothesis, that helps us make sure that we don’t end up—I don’t want to call it pointless, because I think there’s a place for directionless exploration. But we want to make sure we avoid that being the modus operandi. We’re not the kind of organization that just builds cool shit for the sake of building cool shit.</p>
<p><strong><big>How can a PM ensure they’re self-disrupting in a way that adds real-world value?</big></strong></p>
<p>There’s a couple things I would say here. The first is to try to adopt what Elon Musk coined as the <a href="http://99u.com/workbook/20482/how-elon-musk-thinks-the-first-principles-method" target="_blank">First Principles approach of thinking</a>. That’s where you think about: what is always going to be true about the people that you’re trying to serve? How does your product serve them today and how can your product do that in new and better ways? You can apply that not just to your entire product, but to a very small part of your product, as well. Or an experience in your product.</p>
<p>Product development typically goes, you make a bet and you get to a product-market fit, and then you just iterate and iterate and iterate to make things better and better and better. But then you get to a certain point where all those iterations stop paying off as much as they used to. You’re sort of plateauing in the effort you’re putting into it.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"We want to make sure that we’re not just building for the sake of building."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22We%20want%20to%20make%20sure%20that%20we%E2%80%99re%20not%20just%20building%20for%20the%20sake%20of%20building.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1844' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>And so that’s probably a good time to ask yourself: <strong>well, what are people actually trying to do?</strong> What problems are you actually solving? And try to get to that first principle of what people are trying to solve, and solve that again with the learning, the technology, the ability that you have today. That doesn’t mean redesign. <strong>It means rethink how you approach the problem.</strong></p>
<p><strong><big>How does the validation process differ from more traditional product development?</big></strong></p>
<p>It doesn’t differ too much. What you’re looking for is product-market fit. You’re looking for some kind of validation from users that you’ve solved a problem and tapped into a need for them. And you’re doing it in a market segment that is growing, so there’s a larger opportunity out there. The way that we go about validating a product is kind of like how you would do it in regular product development. It’s applying the same sort of experimental product development thinking, just in a different place.</p>
<p><strong><big>What does success look like for your team?</big></strong></p>
<p>Ultimately, our goal as an organization is to make sure that we’re continuing to innovate, we’re continuing to keep an eye out for those market opportunities and making the right investments in areas where makes sense. Right now it makes sense for us to do a lot of that exploration. Three years from now, will it mean that we will take a product that may have worked in emerging products and turn that into something bigger? I’m not sure.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1909 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/TS_divider-3.png" alt="Microscope - divider" width="128" height="128" /></p>
<p>But definitely I think that the spirit of constant observation of the world around us and constant reevaluation of where we need to make investments—to either explore or put more fuel on the fire—those are business decisions that we will make. Those become less about, “Hey, this is a framework that we should always follow.” It’s about, “We need to get to our vision. What is the best thing we need to do to get to our vision?&#8221;</p>
<p><strong><big>Can you share any ideas or new products you’ve been really excited about?</big></strong></p>
<p>There’s a couple of things we worked on last quarter. The first one was a new storytelling product for mobile that is very much in development. And we also explored things with the Alexa platform and using voice as a medium for enjoying stories—which is really fun.</p>
<p>We worked on some smaller projects, as well, based on an observation of how rich messaging experiences were getting, and how storytelling and messaging were starting to converge in an interesting way. We launched some iMessage apps for that.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"Speed and experimentation are the fundamental of everything we do."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22Speed%20and%20experimentation%20are%20the%20fundamental%20of%20everything%20we%20do.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1844' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>We look forward to more of those types of things, and probably also looking to things like AR and VR: looking at how machine learning and artificial intelligence plays a role in the creative storytelling process. We’re looking at how ubiquitous and sort of frictionless interactions with our consumer technology has an effect on storytelling.</p>
<p><strong><big>What are 3 guiding principles any emerging products department should keep in mind?</big></strong></p>
<p>I think the <strong>first</strong> is, if you’re building out a new part of your business, you want to make sure that you build the right business case for it, so the reason for that team’s existence is very, very clear to both the team and the rest of the organization.</p>
<p>The <strong>second</strong> thing is, I would make it very clear what success actually looks like. Defining what success means for a team that is working on lab, skunkworks type of thing needs to be very, very clear.</p>
<p>And I think the <strong>third</strong> is defining a clear working model that allows for speed and experimentation. I think speed and experimentation are the fundamental of everything we do. If we don’t operate with speed, and if we don’t operate in an environment where we’re constantly experimenting with things, then it hinders that team’s ability to actually learn. Through speed and experimentation you learn, and that learning helps you understand and develop the right product.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1910 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/TS_divider-4.png" alt="Test tube - divider" width="128" height="128" /></p>
<p><strong><big>What have you learned about experimentation that you didn’t know before doing this particular role?</big></strong></p>
<p>We have a very, very strong culture of experimentation here at Wattpad. And we are highly evidence-driven. We want to make sure that the things that we build for 45 million users or 500 users have evidence of something. Whether that evidence comes through qualitative, latitudinal studies or through A/B testing, we put a lot of effort into building out our experimentation and data infrastructure that has given the product organization a massive amount of leverage, and it’s been a huge service to the rest of the organization.</p>
<p>When I think about product management in its nature, what you are doing is you are facilitating problem-solving. <strong>And you’re facilitating problem-solving through experimentation.</strong> And the scope of that experimentation can sometimes be: you’re making a big bet on the market. Or sometimes the scope of that experimentation can be red button, blue button.</p>
<p>But at the end of the day, it’s all an experiment. So, when I think about product management, it’s just facilitating an experimental problem-solving process. It should always be experimentation.</p>
<hr />
<p><em><strong>How Roadmunk can help: </strong>Whether you&#8217;re self-disrupting or getting ahead of a disruptive market, a roadmap can help you navigate through the process. Try any of our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=tarunsachdeva" target="_blank">roadmap templates</a> to get in front of disruption.</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/tarun-sachdeva/">Self-disrupting with Wattpad&#8217;s head of emerging products</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How FreshBooks’ creative director bridges product &#038; brand</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/jeremy-bailey/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 14:59:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[freshbooks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jeremy bailey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[user experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ux]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1693</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>We talk to Jeremy Bailey, Creative Director for Product at FreshBooks, about stripping brands back to their studs, ditching your biases, and the Wild West. Like, the literal Wild West.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/jeremy-bailey/">How FreshBooks’ creative director bridges product &#038; brand</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Since its launch more than a decade ago, <a href="https://www.freshbooks.com/" target="_blank">FreshBooks</a> has achieved an unlikely end-goal: making DIY accounting feel painless, quick and even fun. Going cross-eyed over spreadsheets isn&#8217;t <em>usually</em> part of the self-employed dream—but it can easily become part of the reality.</p>
<p><a href="https://ca.linkedin.com/in/jeremy-bailey-0327052" target="_blank">Jeremy Bailey</a>, FreshBooks’ Creative Director for Product, played an instrumental role in establishing FreshBooks as the go-to cloud accounting software for small-business owners. Initially hired as a freelance art director, he joined the team full-time in 2010, delving deeply into users’ problems to connect a relatable marketing experience to a product that genuinely helps its customers. Marketing and product can often seem like their own realms, but Bailey has a foot firmly planted in both worlds. (He also works as a visual artist under his tongue-in-cheek alter-ego, <a href="http://jeremybailey.net/" target="_blank">Jeremy Bailey: Famous New Media Artist</a>.)</p>
<p>As part of our ongoing interview series with awesome product people, we chatted with Bailey about stripping brands back to their studs, ditching your biases, and the Wild West. Like, the literal Wild West.</p>
<p><big><strong>Your title is pretty unusual. How did you come to be Creative Director for Product?</strong></big></p>
<p>I was freelancing and FreshBooks was a client that came to me with a problem. I think a lot of startups probably have this problem: different people have come and gone really rapidly over the first few years. And different people have put their flag in the ground. So there were a lot of arbitrary and sometimes well-guided decisions, but altogether they don’t add up to a cohesive whole. That was definitely true for FreshBooks, not for any mal-intent, but just for the sheer speed at which they were operating.<br />
<img class="aligncenter wp-image-1699 size-medium" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-1-300x110.png" alt="Design elements - Divider" width="300" height="110" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-1-300x110.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-1.png 561w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><br />
They hired me to help bring that all together. And the first thing I did was wrong, too. I proposed a sweeping new look. And the humbling lesson that I learned is to figure out what their customer needs. So that became my job. And what I discovered by talking to the customers and spending time with the staff was that what they already had was wonderful. People already loved what they were doing. There were certain aspects of their brand, not visual, that people were over the moon for. Like their support, or the little things their product did to make them laugh. And the things the customers really loved could be applied more broadly across the whole product and platform. The whole image of the company.</p>
<p><big><strong>How did you calibrate design changes that went &#8220;too far” vs. changes that would have value?</strong></big></p>
<p>It was a very simple strategy that’s the same strategy every home renovator uses on a home decorating show. Which is to strip it all the way back down to the studs. And say, “What is the least we can have and still evoke these emotions?” So visually it would be removing all the drop shadows, the gradients, the additional flourishes, and saying, “Hey, we’re going to stick to a really simple color palette, and exercising some restraint will help us find out what’s essential. And when we hit a roadblock, we’ll add to that palette. And by pulling all the way back and then adding, we’ll understand how each decision was made.”</p>
<p>I was able to help arbitrary decision-making become more structured decision-making.</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><big><strong>How far back did you strip it, exactly?</strong></big></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We went back to blue and white and black. Which were the colors of the logo. And green for calls to action. And I got rid of all the non-heritage, non-long-lasting typefaces, because I knew they’d have to be replaced. And we just stuck with that.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"You don’t invent the brand, the customer invents it and then you just reflect it back to them."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22You%20don%E2%80%99t%20invent%20the%20brand%2C%20the%20customer%20invents%20it%20and%20then%20you%20just%20reflect%20it%20back%20to%20them.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1693' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We were using stock photos for our illustration, and I knew that wasn’t going to help us stand out. This was Web 2.0 era, and there were probably 30 competitors doing the exact same thing at the exact same point in their progress in the market. So there were 30 other brands people loved. My experience told me that if you want to stand out, you need to do something other people can’t do. And you don’t copy what others are doing. So constrain our palette, and then start to do things that others couldn’t copy.</span></p>
<p>It’s really basic. I kind of feel that anyone could apply that tomorrow and improve their brand. But then the more difficult thing in the longer term is: “How do we translate that same approach to the product?” At first we just did a visual scrub of the product, but for the last three years I’ve been really focused on bringing that same decision-making, consistency and restraint to the product.</p>
<p><big><strong>Do you have some advice around how to exercise effective constraint?</strong></big></p>
<p>One thing we did at FreshBooks was make it really hard for a single individual to make an arbitrary decision. As an example, we formed a little council that supervises every visual decision. We call it “art director’s circle.” When you want to change an element that’s core and that impacts different aspects of the brand, you come to that council and you make a case for it. It’s not like a tribunal in a negative way, but there’s a structure to the argument. And every time we’ve thought, “This is going to be an easy decision,” it ends up being a really hard decision. And I’m glad we make those decisions early on, and not after it’s out in the wild—when we’re like “oh shit.”</p>
<p><big><strong>What kinds of considerations go into that decision-making process?</strong></big><br />
There are different vectors. There’s some standard stuff. Is it accessible? Is it on-brand in terms of just the pure guidelines that we have?</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"I don’t think any customer wakes up wishing for their company to rebrand."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22I%20don%E2%80%99t%20think%20any%20customer%20wakes%20up%20wishing%20for%20their%20company%20to%20rebrand.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1693' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>The conversation goes something like, “Here’s the problem.” We show the problem, then we ask, “How are others solving this problem today?” So we might look at how other brands are solving that problem. Then we’ll stress test the solution. When you’re building those guidelines, you’re trying them out, not just on your marketing, but you’re also trying them out on the product. You’re also trying them out on your advertising or your corporate communication.</p>
<p>This whole exercise doesn’t take more than a week, but we do that for each major decision.</p>
<p><big><strong>It can be hard to correlate design changes directly to, say, a boost in conversions or revenue. How do you make a case that design changes add value? </strong></big></p>
<p>All these things add up to emotion, and if you feel like you’re coming out with a message and you’re not reinforcing that message, then of course you want to align them with that, because that’s going to help people understand with greater impact. You only have a few seconds of a person’s time when they first meet you, and if they’re wearing bedroom slippers outdoors in the snow, you’re going to be like, “What’s going on here?”</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1702 size-medium" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-2-300x111.png" alt="Pen and money - divider" width="300" height="111" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-2-300x111.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-2.png 561w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>I think it’s best to think about brands as people. And I always think of them as a reflection of the people we serve. Basically you’re trying to reflect back to that person, “Hey, I’m for you.” Not only am I for you—I look like you, I sound like you. It’s a trust thing. You don’t invent the brand, the customer invents it and then you just reflect it back to them.</p>
<p><big><strong>Why do you think it’s often a challenge to create consistency between product and brand?</strong></big></p>
<p>Most companies are organized in silos for product and marketing. And they do their thing. And in fact, they often become enemies. I don’t think that that’s always the intent. But, “Oh marketing did this” is a common refrain I’ve heard in my career. There’s exclusive language to both disciplines, and they’re sometimes in opposition.</p>
<p><big><strong>What mechanisms have you tried to break down silos?</strong></big></p>
<p>I’ll be very honest, I’ll say that’s my biggest challenge. But in the past, where I’ve seen the most success is when you have everyone on the same team.</p>
<p>So no more, there’s a marketing team or a product team. You have a team that delivers an experience. And a marketer is a part of that team. And a marketing designer is part of that team. And a product designer is part of that team. And everyone understands the goal, and they’re all pushing forward together toward that goal. I’ve never seen a team work better together and produce higher-quality work at as great a capacity without any friction or tension.</p>
<p><img class="size-medium wp-image-1716 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-3-300x110.png" alt="" width="300" height="110" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-3-300x110.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-3.png 561w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>The problem is when you create two different goals that aren’t aligned. On two different teams in two different sides of the building. Geography actually matters. Just like talking to a customer, the same thing is true internally. Sitting next to the person that you’re going to work with creates at least some sort of empathy for the other person’s predicament.</p>
<p><big><strong>How does it benefit a company to have more consistency between the branding and the product?</strong></big></p>
<p>When you have consistency you can put arguments to rest over taste. I don’t care that your husband or boyfriend or girlfriend or wife has an opinion on the color we should use. Let’s just establish this is what we’re going to do, this is performing well, and move forward because there are so many other challenges that are as important or more important. I don’t think any customer wakes up wishing for their company to rebrand. They’re more likely to switch brands, frankly, if you do that. One of the decisions I had to make was not to update our logo seven or eight years ago. Because that was the thing people recognized and loved and they weren’t complaining about it.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"The gut instinct you have in your corporate office is 9 times out of 10 absolutely not correct."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22The%20gut%20instinct%20you%20have%20in%20your%20corporate%20office%20is%209%20times%20out%20of%2010%20absolutely%20not%20correct.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1693' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>I always explain this cocktail party analogy. A logo is a lot like someone’s face. And if you meet someone and they’ve changed a little bit over time, you’re usually like, “Wow, it’s been so long, I haven’t seen you, you’ve changed so much.” But if you come back two weeks later and they’ve changed their face again, you’re like, “Something’s wrong.”</p>
<p>With consistency, you’re taking that objection off the table. This is a trustworthy company. That’s why brands existed in the first place, was to establish trust. Because there was a Wild West out there, literally, where companies were making all kinds of elixirs and stuff like that.</p>
<p><big><strong>How can product managers support design in creating symbiosis between product and brand?</strong></big></p>
<p>That’s really easy. For us, anyway, we always thought of the product manager as a designer. Or working alongside the designer as a perfect couple. If they’re working well, those two people are essentially two halves of a whole solution for building product. So the designer leans towards design, and the manager leans toward the practicality of development. But together they form a whole unit that can deliver outstanding results.</p>
<p><img class="size-medium wp-image-1717 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-4-300x110.png" alt="" width="300" height="110" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-4-300x110.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-4.png 561w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>At FreshBooks the research used to be entirely done by product managers. But now they share it evenly. Design decisions used to be entirely by the designer, but we have several meetings where we do critique, and the product managers and designers critique together. They also ideate together. So at all the key junctures, they’re considered the same person. They’re reporting together, they’re demoing together, they’re like a little pair.</p>
<p><big><strong>Can you tell us about your research process at FreshBooks?</strong></big></p>
<p>We’re either talking on the phone or inviting people in to look at products, or going to their offices to learn about the problems they have. So every designer talks to four people a week. That kind of customer intimacy is irreplaceable and it creates an intuition for what the right thing is, instead of going on your gut. The gut instinct you have in your corporate office is 9 times out of 10 absolutely not correct. It’s informed by privilege. And those privileged decisions are informed by an unintentional bias that unfortunately makes us make wrong decisions on behalf of our customers.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"The worst thing you can do is look at your competitor and copy that."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22The%20worst%20thing%20you%20can%20do%20is%20look%20at%20your%20competitor%20and%20copy%20that.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1693' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>Last year we spoke to over 1000 people, this year we’ll probably speak to twice that many. When you do it on a regular basis it becomes natural. Our natural instinct is to defend our position because we don’t want to admit we’re wrong. And we find data to back up our biases, and confirm our biases. And so I think it’s really important to get out and talk to the real people.</p>
<p><big><strong>What’s the worst mistake a company can do when trying to create consistent design that runs through product and marketing?</strong></big></p>
<p>I think the worst thing you can do is look at your competitor and copy that. It’s worth emphasizing, because it’s a natural instinct when you’re small to look at what the big guys are doing. But I can’t emphasize enough how backward that strategy is. The fact that you’re small is actually your biggest advantage.</p>
<p>A great company that came to my attention—probably too late, but who I’m in love with right now—is <a href="http://www.everlane.com" target="_blank">Everlane</a>. Their concept is radical transparency. And as a very small online retailer, they leverage the fact that they have no brick-and-mortar stores to offer a cheaper price and to be transparent about their markup, and to show you their factory. So all the things the big guys couldn’t do, they’re like, “This is our brand.”</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter" src="https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/564x/fd/9b/03/fd9b032bce5636e08fea8448e8888f06.jpg" alt="Diagram showing Transparent Pricing at Everlane" width="564" height="439" /></p>
<p><big><strong>How have you leveraged this idea at FreshBooks?</strong></big></p>
<p>With accounting software, they’d say it should look like business software. “This is too playful.” Right? But that’s precisely how we distinguish ourselves versus the most corporate giants in the world. If we went out and did exactly what Intuit or Quickbooks did, we’d look like a lesser version of them.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"For me, it’s the humility to understand that big problems require teams to solve."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22For%20me%2C%20it%E2%80%99s%20the%20humility%20to%20understand%20that%20big%20problems%20require%20teams%20to%20solve.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1693' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>But we come out and we do what they can’t do. They can’t use a playful tone, they can’t be transparent, they can’t pick up the phone. You can’t talk to the CEO. You have to play to your weaknesses as your strengths.</p>
<p><big><strong>Looking back at when you started at FreshBooks to now, what’s the most significant way you evolved as a designer?</strong></big></p>
<p>For me, it’s the humility to understand that big problems require teams to solve. You need to push down your problems to the team and collectively solve them, because ultimately they need to be implemented collectively.</p>
<p>That’s something I still work on today: how do we create organizations that emerge from the bottom? That aren’t driven from the top. Organizations where every day you come into work, and when there’s a problem you don’t just say, “Ugh, well I guess we have to deal with it because it’s the corporate way.” But where you’re like, “This problem could be solved if we work together.”</p>
<hr />
<p><em><strong>A Roadmunk sidenote: </strong>Whether you&#8217;re doing a complete rebrand or you just need to bridge that product-design gap, a roadmap can be your best friend. Use any of our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=jeremybailey" target="_blank">roadmap templates</a> to help build product-brand consistency.</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/jeremy-bailey/">How FreshBooks’ creative director bridges product &#038; brand</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>8 product managers share trends (and goals) for 2017</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/8-product-managers-share-trends-goals-2017/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 15:51:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tarif Rahman]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management goals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management trends]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product strategy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1516</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>In the spirit of fresh starts, we sat down with 8 very cool product managers to review the product management scene in 2016 and assess where the space is headed in 2017.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/8-product-managers-share-trends-goals-2017/">8 product managers share trends (and goals) for 2017</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Even if you’re not a resolution-setter, the new year is a moment for taking stock: reflecting on the last twelve months and projecting ambitions for the future.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the spirit of fresh starts, we sat down with </span><b>8 very cool product managers </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">to review the product management scene in 2016 and assess where the space is headed in the upcoming year. Will cyborgs rise up to replace us all and </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">doom humanity</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">?! Probably not. Predictions for 2017 range from the infiltration of data science, to fostering psychological safety, to the influx of AI (kiiiind of cyborg-ish, no?). </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These PMs’ insights will help you plan your product management strategies for the new year, no matter your company or industry. Here&#8217;s who we talked to:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="#suzie"><b>Suzie Prince</b></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Head of Product at <strong>ThoughtWorks </strong></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="#daniel"><b>Daniel Zacarias</b></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">,</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Product Management Consultant</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="#annamarie"><b>Anna Marie Clifton</b></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Product Manager at <strong>Yammer</strong></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="#ctodd"><b>C. Todd Lombardo</b></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Chief Design Strategist at <strong>Fresh Tilled Soil</strong></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="#vanessa"><b>Vanessa Ferranto</b></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Senior Manager of Product and Experience at <strong>Zipcar</strong></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="#matt"><b>Matt Bilotti</b></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Product Manager at <strong>Drift</strong></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="#rose"><b>Rose Grabowski</b></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Senior Product Manager at <strong>GrubHub</strong></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="#tim"><b>Tim Herbig</b></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Product Owner at <strong>ORBIT</strong></span></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h1 id="suzie">Suzie Prince</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-medium wp-image-1519 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Suzie-300x300.jpg" alt="Suzie Prince" width="300" height="300" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Suzie-300x300.jpg 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Suzie-150x150.jpg 150w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Suzie.jpg 400w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b>Head of Product<b><br />
Company:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">ThoughtWorks<br />
</span><b>Industry:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> IT<br />
</span><b>Tweet to her: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/pm_suzie" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@pm_suzie</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Finish this sentence: “2016 was the year of…”</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I wanted to say it was the year of </span><b>continuous deployment</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">, but actually I think it’s the year of </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">trying </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">to do that. I see a lot of aspiration, so maybe next year will be the year where people really grasp these processes.</span></p>
<p><b>Looking back on the past year, what did you learn about your space?</b></p>
<p>The saying “build it and they will come” is something people say, and not something I believe. This year it became really clear to me the holisticness that you need—marketing, messaging and sales —for one to get it right. You can’t just make this golden thing and hope that people will come use it.</p>
<p><b>You build products for software developers. What trends are emerging in your space for 2017?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the biggest trends we’re seeing is this idea of being “serverless.” Doing more and more work that is outside of your own hardware. The idea that next year you could pretty much build your entire startup on services that other people look after and support is becoming really clear to me. You don’t need to be some giant with all this massive infrastructure. </span></p>
<p><b>What is the #1 way you want to evolve as a PM in 2017?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think the biggest thing for all product managers is “don’t get stuck in the details.” You are not the person that needs to do every tiny little thing and be distracted by everything. It’s not a new thing, but it’s definitely something to be aware of. </span></p>
<p><b>Read more Suzie:</b></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/how-non-technical-product-managers-can-jump-the-skills-gap/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How “non-technical” product managers can jump the skills gap</span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="http://www.mindtheproduct.com/2016/02/what-the-hell-are-ci-cd-and-devops-a-cheatsheet-for-the-rest-of-us/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Product Managers’ Guide to Continuous Delivery and DevOps</span></a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h1 id="daniel">Daniel Zacarias</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-medium wp-image-1527 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Daniel-300x300.jpg" alt="Daniel Zacarias" width="300" height="300" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Daniel-300x300.jpg 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Daniel-150x150.jpg 150w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Daniel.jpg 401w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b><br />
Title:</b>Product Management Consultant<span style="font-weight: 400;"><br />
</span><b>Industry: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many!<br />
</span><b>Tweet to him: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/listentodaniel" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@listentodaniel</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Finish this phrase: &#8220;2016 was the year of….” </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">2016 was the year of realizing that </span><b>cross-functional teams are useful beyond software products.</b></p>
<p><b>Tell us more.</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I worked with a team in an industry that has nothing to do with software. They organized themselves by functional departments, each with “their responsibilities.&#8221; The problems I saw were all too familiar: information silos, conflicts between sales and engineering, low customer satisfaction… </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">That’s when it clicked. The real value that cross-functional teams bring to the table is not about lower risk, faster delivery, or even better outcomes for the company or product. It’s actually that it incentivizes having a common set of goals. That’s the #1 driver of a healthy team.</span></p>
<p><b>Looking back on this time last year, how did you see the software product space differently?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think we’ve made big strides in going towards a problems-first mindset. However, as an industry, we still suffer from shiny object syndrome and remain too technology-oriented. Too many conversations start with: “How can we use this tech to solve this problem?” Instead of: “How can these problems be addressed by technology?” </span></p>
<p><b>What product management trend (or strategy/idea/approach) are you excited to sink your teeth into in 2017? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I’m looking forward to setting up an internal communications process similar to </span><a href="https://postmarkapp.com/blog/from-roadmap-to-execution-effective-product-management-for-remote-teams" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">this one</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. It’s all too common that with so many moving parts we fail to keep everyone updated on what’s going on. </span></p>
<p><b>What’s the #1 way you would like to evolve personally as a PM in the next year? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I want to be better at summarizing my notes for other people to consume. Big fan of building shared understanding, but it’s sometimes hard to calibrate the right balance of information to share with other stakeholders. </span></p>
<p><b>Read more Daniel:</b></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-prioritization-techniques/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Product prioritization techniques: A map and guided tour</span></a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h1 id="annamarie">Anna Marie Clifton</h1>
<p><img class="size-medium wp-image-1539 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Anna_Marie-300x300.png" alt="Anna Marie Clifton" width="300" height="300" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Anna_Marie-300x300.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Anna_Marie-150x150.png 150w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Anna_Marie.png 401w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Title: </strong>Product Manager<strong><br />
</strong><b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Yammer<br />
</span><b>Industry: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Software<br />
</span><b>Tweet to her: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/TweetAnnaMarie" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@TweetAnnaMarie</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Complete the sentence: “2016 was the year of…”</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">2016 was the year of </span><b>psychological safety</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and bringing that concept into the workplace—specifically product managers doing so.</span></p>
<p><b>Can’t say I’ve heard that term before. What does that mean?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Google released a </span><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/02/28/magazine/what-google-learned-from-its-quest-to-build-the-perfect-team.html?_r=0" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">study</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> that found the unifying factor across high-performing teams is a concept they’ve defined as “psychological safety.” It’s the emotional experience team members have in being able to express opinions and faults without risk of retribution. </span></p>
<p><b>Very cool! Other than psychological safety, what have you learned about building software products in 2016?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Something I wrangle with as a PM in the software world is how to reduce ambiguity. I find the larger and more vague a project, the more debilitating it can be for team members to move forward. So I’ve learned how the role of the PM is to take that inertia and drive away as much ambiguity as possible. </span></p>
<p><b>And when you compare the software product space to this time last year, how did you see it differently?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">My career has been from many smaller, younger startups, so something that struck me when starting at Yammer is the systemization in place to address things like accessibility, localization and designing for user experiences incredibly unlike my own. I now consider and build out workflows to accommodate various accessibility and localization concerns that never occurred to me before.</span></p>
<p><b>What is the one thing you’d like to evolve personally as a PM in 2017?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The #1 thing I’m looking to strengthen is my ability to develop psychological safety on my team. I’m being conscious about getting more in tune with my team’s style and identifying how to provide a space for someone to say something when they may be afraid to. </span></p>
<p><b>Read more Anna Marie:</b></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://medium.com/@TweetAnnaMarie/so-how-did-you-get-into-product-management-7070a0449d2e#.vhiwcb9l5" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">So… how did you get into Product Management?</span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://medium.com/@TweetAnnaMarie/how-to-develop-your-product-intuition-9ba7dd2f07a3#.gpifa492b" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How to Develop Your Product Intuition</span></a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h1 id="ctodd">C. Todd Lombardo</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-medium wp-image-1544 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_C_Todd-300x300.jpg" alt="C. Todd Lombardo" width="300" height="300" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_C_Todd-300x300.jpg 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_C_Todd-150x150.jpg 150w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_C_Todd.jpg 401w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Title: </strong>Chief Design Strategist<br />
<b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fresh Tilled Soil<br />
</span><b>Industry: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">UX and Design Consultancy<br />
</span><b>Tweet to him: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/iamctodd" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@iamctodd</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Finish the statement: “2016 was the year of…”</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think 2016 was the year of <strong>data science infiltrating product</strong>. Dealing with various product teams, I saw a demand from clients to develop and design products that are heavily reliant on a data model. </span></p>
<p><b>As as mentor to product teams, what have you learned about product strategy this year?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The biggest thing I’ve learned is that product strategy comes in different levels. Companies have a stratification of strategy that’s dependent on their life stage, maturity, size and even industry.</span></p>
<p><b>Care to elaborate?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Take a company like Google: At the highest level, there’s a business strategy and underneath are business units with portfolio strategies for individual products. Compare that to Slack that has one product in market: </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Their business strategy is their product strategy</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<p><b>Looking back at this time last year, how did you see product strategy differently?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Growing up in the product world, I have this product-focused mind that didn’t always see this strategy stratification. In 2016, I found a framework for my brain that sees the connection between my product strategy and the overall business strategy which may include other products/services. </span></p>
<p><b>What are some emerging trends you see popping up in your particular product space?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I’m seeing more companies “validate qualitatively, verify quantitatively.” PMs are basing their initial product strategies on qualitative data and later backing their product choices with quantitative data to say, “Yep, it’s reinforcing our plan and we should continue with it.” </span></p>
<p><b>What’s the #1 way you would like to grow as a product person in 2017?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Given that technology changes so fast, as a product strategist I ask myself: How do I stay abreast of things while still offering the best advice to my clients, so they’re as successful as possible? Answering that is what I want to evolve most in 2017. </span></p>
<p><b>Read more C. Todd:</b></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920038573.do" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Design Sprint: A Practical Guidebook for Building Great Digital Products</span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="http://www.freshtilledsoil.com/category/product-hero/" target="_blank">Product Hero Series</a></span></li>
</ul>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<hr />
<h1 id="vanessa">Vanessa Ferranto</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-medium wp-image-1550 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Vanessa-300x300.jpg" alt="Vanessa Ferranto" width="300" height="300" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Vanessa-300x300.jpg 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Vanessa-150x150.jpg 150w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Vanessa.jpg 400w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Title: </strong>Senior Manager of Product and Experience<br />
<b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Zipcar<br />
</span><b>Industry: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sharing economy<br />
</span><b>Tweet to her: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/vgferranto" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@VGFerranto</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Complete the phrase: “2016 was the year of…”</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It was the year of <strong>process improvement for faster and more agile development. </strong></span></p>
<p><b>What made agile a special consideration in 2016?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our company transitioned towards a new platform and infrastructure. This shift meant aligning short- and long-term goals, and building communication across large product/engineering teams and global stakeholders. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We were already an agile organization, but a stronger emphasis on building iterative improvements in our process (including product management practices) has proven valuable in achieving our goals. </span></p>
<p><b>What have you learned about B2C software in 2016?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As product managers, we must advocate for realistic roadmaps and key metrics to measure against. Many PMs struggle with how to build a transparent and concise roadmap effective for any-sized organization. Having a clear vision is the first step to executing your way there. </span></p>
<p><b>What trends are emerging in your product space for 2017?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The industry is incredibly exciting with ride-sharing, car-sharing, peer-to-peer models and the emergence of autonomous vehicles. These trends focus around the collaborative consumption model and ways to integrate new technologies into fleets in fresh and interesting ways. </span></p>
<p><b>What’s the #1 way you would like to grow as a PM this upcoming year?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Being on the board of Boston Product Management Association—a co-founder of Boston Women in Product and co-creator of Agile Product Open—I want to leverage these communities (and more) to gain a greater knowledge of the agile and product management disciplines.</span></p>
<p><b>Read more Vanessa:</b></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://producthubbpma.org/2016/05/16/leading-as-a-product-manager/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Leading as a Product Manager </span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://producthubbpma.org/2015/09/30/six-steps-to-achieve-product-success/" target="_blank">6 Steps to Achieve Product Success</a></span></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h1 id="matt">Matt Bilotti</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-medium wp-image-1554 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Matt-300x300.jpg" alt="Matt Bilotti" width="300" height="300" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Matt-300x300.jpg 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Matt-150x150.jpg 150w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Matt.jpg 401w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b>Product Manager<b><br />
Company:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Drift<br />
</span><b>Industry: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">SaaS<br />
</span><b>Tweet to him: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/MattBilotti" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@MattBilotti</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Fill in the blank: “2016 was the year of…”</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Design becoming more important in the product cycle. This year <strong>design became more of a driving factor in the product development process</strong> in a way it wasn’t necessarily before. </span></p>
<p><b>You build a product for sales and customer success teams. How did you see your space differently this time last year?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It was still very focused on email. That’s where we were when we began building Drift. But then this concept of live chat and offline messaging with customers surfaced as really important. Companies started realizing:</span></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Offering these communication options helps connect better with customers, increases sales, keeps customers happy, etc. </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">This concept doesn’t require massive human-time investments (i.e. somebody sitting there all day answering questions).</span></li>
</ol>
<p><b>In 2016, what have you personally learned from your product space?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are so many tools for this space that it teaches you to ask: What are we building that will get customers to stay with us without handcuffing them? I feel the tools that win in this space don’t lock customers to their product, but work cohesively with the customer’s other systems.  </span></p>
<p><b>Looking ahead, what’s an emerging trend you see in this product space?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think AI and machine learning will be exponentially prevalent. It’s all about who’s got the algorithms that can help things scale better and people work smarter. </span></p>
<p><b>What’s the one way you’d like to grow as a PM in 2017?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Since we try to be inherently flexible at Drift, we build a lot of early “step ones” and know that “step ten” is somewhere ahead. I’m really good at creating the “step one”, but I want to get better at working out the ultimate thing we’re building towards earlier on—so we can draw more of a straight line towards it. </span></p>
<p><b>Read more Matt:</b></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://seekingwisdom.io/how-to-handle-bugs-backlog-prioritization-and-communication-with-the-burndown-framework-8ec8e559e85e#.nnq2itm2t" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How to Handle Bugs, Backlog, Prioritization and Communication with the Burndown Framework</span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://seekingwisdom.io/from-managing-pizza-to-managing-product-f6009ed628f4#.pa0ror6rv" target="_blank">What Pizza taught me about product</a></span></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h1 id="rose">Rose Grabowski</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-medium wp-image-1558 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Rose-300x300.png" alt="Rose Grabowski" width="300" height="300" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Rose-300x300.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Rose-150x150.png 150w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Rose.png 401w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Title: </b>Senior Product Manager<b><br />
Company:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">GrubHub<br />
</span><b>Industry: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Software<br />
</span><b>Tweet to her: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/rosegrabowski" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@rosegrabowski</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Complete the phrase: “2016 was the year of…”</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Listening.</strong> 2016 continued to show me the more I listen </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">(to customers, to stakeholders, to users), the more I understand their needs/wants and know the right things for us to work on. </span></p>
<p><b>What have you learned about building web and software products in the past year?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There seems to be this common misconception in the space around the origins of the MVP concept. The cliff-notes version of the concept centers around building the minimum product a customer can use. But creating a minimum product was originally intended to provide insights for what to build afterwards. By focusing on creating a cheaper product to start, you&#8217;re missing the unique potential of the concept.</span></p>
<p><b>Looking back on this time last year, how did you see your product space differently?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I used to think there was a &#8220;great&#8221; way to organize teams to build software, and it was probably agile—specifically scrum. I&#8217;m realizing many who claim to do agile/scrum awesomely actually experience the same significant challenges around the methodology. I&#8217;m now more skeptical that there&#8217;s a </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">right</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> team process, as opposed to, &#8220;Let’s just use this OK process, as long as it doesn&#8217;t get in our way.&#8221;</span></p>
<p><b>What product management trend are you excited to dive into in 2017?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Customer experience mapping. I&#8217;m currently working on a product with both software components and physical interaction aspects. I&#8217;m psyched to be thinking about the user experience more holistically, so I can affect more than just the software interaction.</span></p>
<p><b>What’s the one thing you’d like to evolve as a PM this year?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I want to not get bogged down in the day-to-day minutia. So much of that minutia is important, but I&#8217;m personally committed to ensuring that it doesn&#8217;t overwhelm my more strategic objectives. </span></p>
<p><b>Read more Rose:</b></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.freshtilledsoil.com/product-hero-rose-grabowski/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Product Hero: Rose Grabowski</span></a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h1 id="tim">Tim Herbig</h1>
<p><b><img class="size-medium wp-image-1562 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Tim-300x300.jpg" alt="Tim Herbig " width="300" height="300" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Tim-300x300.jpg 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Tim-150x150.jpg 150w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Trends_Tim.jpg 401w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Title: </strong>Product Owner<br />
<b>Company: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">ORBIT<br />
</span><b>Industry: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Software<br />
</span><b>Tweet to him: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/herbigt" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">@herbigt</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Finish this sentence: “2016 was the year of…”</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I have the impression that 2016 was the year of the <strong>design sprint</strong>. </span><a href="http://www.gv.com/sprint/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">This book came out</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and basically everybody in the corporate sector was like, “Hey, design thinking was yesterday now we need to do design sprints!” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For me personally, it’s not that much about the doing design by the book, but more like, “Okay, let’s really get to the essence of the design sprint.” Cross-functional teams working and focused for 3 days in a row and doing user testing at the end of it.</span></p>
<p><b>Looking back on this time last year, how did you view product management in a different light than you do now? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Last year I saw more value in the operational things, such as running and maintaining a backlog and keeping developers up to date. And now I&#8217;m more in the mindset of, “I really want to take care of the bigger questions” and &#8220;Which problems should I solve and for which user group?&#8221;</span></p>
<p><b>Looking ahead, what product management trend are you excited to take the reigns on?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">People are getting more used to the terminology of the product needing to fulfil the job. Also making the shift from user stories to job stories. The inventor of jobs to be done methodology, </span><a href="https://twitter.com/claychristensen" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Clayton Christensen</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, wrote a new book this year, </span><a href="http://www.competingagainstluck.com/" target="_blank"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Competing Against Luck</span></i></a><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></i></p>
<p><b>What about 2017—what&#8217;s the #1 way you personally want to evolve as a PM?</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I personally want to get back into public speaking more. I used to do a lot of talks back in 2012 or so. I see a huge personal gain in helping others, leveraging others and spreading knowledge. This is why I write and do a podcast and newsletter.</span></p>
<p><b>Read more Tim:</b></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://herbigt.com/product-business-job/" target="_blank">What&#8217;s your Product&#8217;s primary Business Job?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://herbigt.com/product-discovery/" target="_blank">How to succeed with your next Product Discovery</a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p><em>One way Roadmunk is evolving this year? By offering <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=trends" target="_blank">20+ customizable templates</a> that let you kickstart your roadmap.</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/8-product-managers-share-trends-goals-2017/">8 product managers share trends (and goals) for 2017</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
