<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title><![CDATA[Roadmapping Field Guide | Roadmunk]]></title><description><![CDATA[Get the how-tos and tools you need to lay the foundation for a crystal-clear, actionable roadmap.]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/</link><image><url>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/favicon.png</url><title>Roadmapping Field Guide | Roadmunk</title><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/</link></image><generator>Ghost 1.20</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 14:08:11 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Creating a sales roadmap for a growing sales team]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 7]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/sales-roadmap/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5b331b41f77e1a0001447b12</guid><category><![CDATA[Business]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[tarif]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 14:56:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch7.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch7.svg" alt="Creating a sales roadmap for a growing sales team"><p>What’s up? I’m Jalil, VP of Sales and Customer Success at Roadmunk.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As the head of our sales operations here for several years, I’ve evangelized the idea that sales roadmaps are a powerful tool that sales people need to fulfill at least one of three use-cases:</p>
<ol>
<li>Show your customers and prospects <strong>which direction your business and product are headed towards</strong>.</li>
<li>Outline <strong>the biggest deals in your sales pipeline</strong> and how long their sales cycles will be, so you can track key dates like when the customer signs or negotiations occur.</li>
<li>Plan and visualize <strong>a sales rep’s career trajectory</strong> and their contribution to revenue.</li>
</ol>
<p>But just like product roadmaps, <strong>sales roadmaps evolve with your growing business</strong>. (After all, a sales roadmap is also <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/what-is-a-product-roadmap/"><strong>a statement of intent</strong></a>, not a set-in-stone plan). And while a sales roadmap might fulfill a certain use case at one point in time of your business, it may not necessarily be valuable for that same purpose after your business has matured.</p>
<p>As the head of sales team that has matured from just me by lonesome to over a dozen of us, I’ve seen our sales roadmap evolve each step of the way. So, I thought I’d walk you through how you can expect <strong>your sales roadmap to evolve as your business grows from a startup to an SME to an enterprise</strong>.</p>
<p>Ready? Let’s do this.</p>
<h6 id="ifyourproductteamisjustasagileasyoursalesteamcheckoutourguidetoagileroadmaps">If your product team is just as &quot;agile&quot; as your sales team, check out our <strong><a href="http://go.roadmunk.com/agile-roadmap-ebook?utm_campaign=Agile%20Roadmap%20Ebook&amp;utm_source=AgileRoadmapChapter2">guide to agile roadmaps</a></strong>.</h6>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch7-1.svg" alt="Creating a sales roadmap for a growing sales team"></p>
<h2 id="thesalesroadmapforastartup">The sales roadmap for a startup</h2>
<p>As a startup, you don't necessarily need a sales roadmap to trace what deals you're trying to close. You’ve got minimal customers and are still hacking away at product-market fit. You can map your sales goals and targets, but what you need more at this point is <strong>a sales tool</strong> that gets you to “yes” quickly.</p>
<p>When Roadmunk was at this stage, our sales roadmap didn’t differentiate much from our product roadmap. It focused on <strong>upcoming product features</strong> and <strong>sales goals</strong> we wanted to hit. We’d pull it up to prospects to say, “This is what we’re building.” Presenting our product strategy <strong>managed customer expectations</strong> and <strong>boosted our credibility as a business</strong>. We weren’t just delivering a sales-y spiel of “Trust me, this product is what you need and it’ll only get better.”</p>
<h3 id="whoownstheroadmapatthisstage">Who owns the roadmap at this stage?</h3>
<p>When you’re a startup, literally <em><strong>everyone</strong></em> should have access to your sales roadmap. Your headcount should be small enough that you can feasibly have everyone collaborate on this living document, since product and business knowledge should be consistent across the entire business at this stage.</p>
<h3 id="whattoincludeonthisroadmap">What to include on this roadmap?</h3>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-7-1-1.svg" alt="Creating a sales roadmap for a growing sales team"></p>
<p>Essentially the way I think of the sales roadmap for a startup is that it’s <strong>a market-ready product roadmap</strong>. What you want to include on this roadmap is all your <strong>product-centric items</strong> for the next few months, quarters or years that you want to share with your customers. Remember, you’re treating your sales roadmap as a sales tool to push prospective customers down the funnel. <strong>Reframe your sales roadmap as a companion piece to your product roadmap.</strong> Not only should the sales roadmap somewhat mimic your product roadmap, it should capture customer requests and ideas.</p>
<p>In Roadmunk’s “infancy” stage, we’d take inputs we heard on calls in the sales process and consolidate them into our sales roadmap, categorize them and <strong>tag them against specific customers</strong>. That way when something got released, I could go into our roadmap and filter based on that feature to pull up every tagged customer. This made prospecting and revisiting old sales leads far, far easier. It also showed our customers that we’re good listeners, pushing them closer to “hell yeah.”</p>
<p>But the important thing to keep in mind about the sales roadmap at this stage is to make it <strong>market-friendly</strong>. No complex product jargon! Use terminology customers will understand. Also, include as many details in your items as possible like mocks, links to videos, or any appropriate collateral you can pull up during a roadmap presentation, that way you can really speak to your product’s (and business’) next steps.</p>
<p><mark>Build a market-friendly sales roadmap by customizing our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/sales-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter7">sales roadmap template</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch7-2.svg" alt="Creating a sales roadmap for a growing sales team"></p>
<h2 id="thesalesroadmapforansme">The sales roadmap for an SME</h2>
<p>This is the stage where we shift away from a product roadmap “replica” and more towards a roadmap charting <strong>your <em>largest</em> sales deals</strong> (not every single deal, just the highest-impact ones). SMEs consider sales roadmaps less of a tool for closing deals and more of <strong>an internal-facing tool</strong> to align everyone on how the sales mission is advancing.</p>
<p>Alternatively, this roadmap also <strong>highlights major clogs in the sales strategy</strong>. For example, we included a “Stage” field that when we filtered by, would show every customer’s current stage, such as prospecting, demos or negotiations. If I saw 70% of our prospects were stuck in negotiations and two or three sales reps were responsible for these deals, I knew there was a big risk there and I needed to pay serious attention to this bottleneck.</p>
<p>For salespeople thinking that CRMs can track things like sales stage, I say yes they can BUT as your business model develops and your lead/customer volume increase, <strong>a visualization achieves quicker alignment</strong>. You can literally point to a roadmap that’s filtered on owner and stage and ask, “Hey, what’s going on with these deals? What’s the bottleneck and how can I help?”</p>
<h3 id="whoownstheroadmapatthisstage">Who owns the roadmap at this stage?</h3>
<p>At the intermediate stage of a business, the sales roadmap should be almost entirely controlled by your <strong>sales manager</strong>, in conjunction with your <strong>product team</strong>. The reason I say product is because they’ll be the ones to validate what you can offer to customers when trying to seal the deal; they’re essentially a secondary function of your sales roadmap.</p>
<h3 id="whattoincludeonthisroadmap">What to include on this roadmap?</h3>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-7-2-1.svg" alt="Creating a sales roadmap for a growing sales team"></p>
<p>I mentioned above, this is when you map <strong>your largest deals and priority customers</strong>. But you’ll want to organize your roadmap based on fields like <strong>the stage of the deal</strong>, <strong>win/loss analysis</strong> or <strong>anticipated revenue</strong>. But you want to keep it straightforward because at an SME, not everyone will comprehend the sales roadmap as intuitively as they did when you were a startup and there was shared knowledge of each part of the business. Being at an SME means siloed teams, so using the roadmap for alignment on the sales strategy is even more vital.</p>
<p>When we reached this stage at Roadmunk, we also built in <strong>an HR component into our sales roadmap</strong>. We visualized our sales reps’ trajectories and growth by including <strong>owners</strong> on the roadmap and grouping deals based on who was responsible for them. This helped modify the sales roadmap from just a sales tool to also an accountability mechanism.</p>
<p><mark>Keep an eye on those major deals by creating a sales roadmap like above. <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/sales-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter7">Click here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch7-3.svg" alt="Creating a sales roadmap for a growing sales team"></p>
<h2 id="thesalesroadmapforanenterprise">The sales roadmap for an enterprise</h2>
<p>While we haven’t quite reached enterprise status here at Roadmunk, the reality is your sales roadmap at an enterprise has A LOT of ground to cover. With endless deals and prospects, you need to really prioritize the hefty deals, as well as the strategic initiatives your team will execute to secure more moula. One major evolution for a sales roadmap at this stage is <strong>assigning revenue to your major deals</strong>.</p>
<p>We started to do this at Roadmunk last year with the addition of our <strong>numeric fields</strong>. This field really helps us as a sales team when we’re bombarded with feature requests and feedback. We can go to our product team or higher-ups and point out that we’ve got six customers who want this integration. And as you can see on the roadmap, all of these fall under deal sizes that are $100,000 plus. <strong>Attaching numbers to your sales roadmap goes a long way in starting substantial dialogue with our product team and C-level execs.</strong></p>
<h3 id="whoownstheroadmapatthisstage">Who owns the roadmap at this stage?</h3>
<p>It’s almost exclusively your <strong>VP of Sales</strong> or <strong>CRO</strong> owning the roadmap at this stage. And honestly, they’re concerned with their <strong>biggest transactions</strong>. Since we’re talking enterprises, your executive team of course has a stake in this roadmap too. And don’t forget about product. They’ll also have a semi “veto” on the roadmap—as your biggest transactions will be influenced by your product strategy.</p>
<h3 id="whattoincludeonthisroadmap">What to include on this roadmap?</h3>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-7-3.svg" alt="Creating a sales roadmap for a growing sales team"></p>
<p>Again, at the enterprise-level, your stakeholders are most concerned with your <strong>top-tier deals and customers</strong>, so you can expect to see your bigger customers laid out on your sales roadmap and the strategic sales initiatives your team will perform to get their $$, retain them and/or prevent them from churning. You’ll want to pivot the data on your sales roadmap using either <strong>revenue</strong> and/or the same fields as you would with an SME-based sales roadmap like <strong>owner</strong>, <strong>stage</strong> and <strong>win/loss analysis</strong>.</p>
<p>But at this business level, sales teams can get tricky. What if you have different product lines? Or an inside sales team vs. an external sales team? While there may be an overarching sales strategy, each team has different ways of selling their specific strategies. So, another way to approach your sales roadmap at an enterprise is to develop <strong>different views for each team and then roll them up into one consolidated view</strong> for you to present to your exec team (we call this a Master roadmap here at Roadmunk). This way each team still has individual control over their own sales strategy, but the VP of Sales or your CRO can get one overall view that captures the most important details of each individual strategy.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-7-4.svg" alt="Creating a sales roadmap for a growing sales team"></p>
<p>And what about when your sales team is scattered around the globe? Short answer: <strong>the sales roadmap becomes more critical</strong>. While every team may be delivering the same product, what I’ve seen work really well is the sales team in each region–whether it’s Europe, Central America or Australia–creates their own sales roadmap that’s tied to product delivery. Then you can roll them all into one Master sales roadmap like the one above. <strong>This can serve as a check and balance to see which region is performing stronger than another</strong>.</p>
<p><mark>Need a sales roadmap for your corporate environment? We've got a template for that <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/sales-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter7">here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch7-4.svg" alt="Creating a sales roadmap for a growing sales team"></p>
<h2 id="evolveyoursalesroadmapwithyourgrowingbusiness">Evolve your sales roadmap with your growing business</h2>
<p>Frankly, I think a lot of sales people view a roadmap as a sales tool, much like we did originally, and less as a tool for accountability and outcomes. But as your business “blooms” and reaches certain stages, you’ll begin to see that dynamic shift.</p>
<p><strong>The sales roadmap cannot fulfill the exact same function at every business stage.</strong> Just like we stress that product roadmaps are statements of intent, a sales roadmap also embodies that philosophy. As your sales needs change with business growth, <strong>your sales roadmap has to change too</strong> to reflect those changes. Otherwise, say peace out to all that $$$ you were hoping to rake in.</p>
<p><mark>No matter what your sales roadmap looks like, build it with Roadmunk's <em>free 14 day trial</em>. <strong><a href="https://app.roadmunk.com/signup">Sign up here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Building an HR roadmap from scratch]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 6]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/hr-roadmap/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5b3319f8f77e1a0001447b10</guid><category><![CDATA[Business]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[tarif]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 14:55:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch6.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch6.svg" alt="Building an HR roadmap from scratch"><p>Hey there! I’m Rebekah and I lead the HR department here at Roadmunk.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ll be honest, if you asked me before starting here what tools are essential for HR teams, I wouldn’t have said roadmaps. Instead I would’ve said an HRIS, payroll, or learning and development platforms.</p>
<p>But after joining a company that builds a roadmapping tool that can be used by any type of team, I’ve started to see the real value of a roadmap within my workflow. (And not just because they pay me.)</p>
<p>HR departments build an HR roadmap to <strong>strategize and prioritize company culture and people-focused initiatives</strong>, as well as <strong>build and manage hiring plans</strong>. And while this HR roadmap definition sounds great on paper, it feels like an added process to learn and manage in an already overstacked workflow.</p>
<p>But for me, an HR roadmap has been vital in <strong>syncing with the rest of the business on our team’s objectives and priorities</strong>. Plus, it helps me ensure that overall plans to add new Roadmunkers are timely and focused in the right business areas. (And truthfully, it wasn’t hard at all to pick up!)</p>
<p>As a former non-roadmapper who was hesitant about learning this new skillset, I wanted to share <strong>how I approached building my HR roadmap from scratch</strong>. So here’s how I built it at Roadmunk.</p>
<h6 id="wedidtheresearchonleadingroadmappingtoolssoyoudonthavetocheckitouthere">We did the research on leading roadmapping tools, so you don't have to. <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/product-roadmap-tools-comparison?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter6">Check it out here.</a></strong></h6>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch6-1.svg" alt="Building an HR roadmap from scratch"></p>
<h2 id="step1figureoutwhyyouneedanhrroadmap">Step 1: Figure out why you need an HR roadmap</h2>
<p>Okay, so I’m in HR, and I’ve had minimal exposure to roadmapping (I usually just whiteboard my plans). What the heck do I do?! First thing’s first, establish why you need this specific document. I personally identify four major purposes for an HR roadmap.</p>
<p><strong>1. Priority mapping:</strong> When I approached our HR roadmap at Roadmunk, I had all these strong aspirations I wanted our team to achieve immediately. But I had to step back and figure out what was important for the business, what was doable AND if I had given myself enough ramp up time to reach these goals. So for me, <strong>roadmapping is an ideal exercise for visualizing which HR goals are manageable</strong> and thus, picking out the top objectives to bring to the front of the line.</p>
<p><strong>2. Resourcing:</strong> HR supports various departments, through one-on-one leadership training, compensation analysis, policy reviews, and curating exceptional everyday experiences for our employees. With so many balls in the air, <strong>HR leaders need to ensure they’re not over-committing when rolling out these initiatives</strong>. Burnout is real, people!</p>
<p><strong>3. Hiring plans:</strong> If recruitment is a top priority for your HR team, this roadmap can illustrate your recruitment efforts across the business. <strong>How and when will new resources be added to the business?</strong> And how do we as HR best support the induction and onboarding of these new hires?</p>
<p><strong>4. Identify efficiencies:</strong> Finally, one of our core missions is to figure out <strong>how we as a business can scale in the most resourceful and effective way</strong>. An HR team (I’m about to get deep here) <em>technically</em> doesn’t bring in revenue; dare I say, some may even consider us a cost (!). So it’s our job to identify opportunities in which the business can be more efficient and effective. <strong>An HR roadmap highlights efficiency-improving opportunities</strong> we want to target such as automating administrative efforts and streamlining onboarding.</p>
<p>So these were <em>my</em> motivations for building an HR roadmap. Yours may differ (or maybe we’re eerily similar in motivations...), but once you’ve determined what’s spurring you to create this roadmap, it’s time for the next step: getting chatty with your stakeholders.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch6-2.svg" alt="Building an HR roadmap from scratch"></p>
<h2 id="step2talktoyourstakeholders">Step 2: Talk to your stakeholders</h2>
<p>So, this step definitely varies business to business. At a smaller company like Roadmunk, I automatically linked with the founders and every single leader to see what their challenges or sore spots were. (These meetings might be harder to secure at a more enterprise level.) This step helped—and still helps—<strong>inform my prioritization</strong>, determine teams experiencing <strong>talent gaps</strong> and identify business areas that would benefit from <strong>efficiency-improving efforts</strong>.</p>
<p>If your business is small enough, I highly encourage you to have one-on-one’s with every employee. Your frontline employees are the one’s with the most impactful insights into how you can effectively improve the employee experience.<strong>Casting a wider net = more research = better prioritization</strong>.</p>
<p>For instance, if your people leaders are saying, “We need one-on-one leadership coaching,” but your frontline workers actually feel like the leaders are genuinely strong, that tells me we can de-prioritize leadership development initiatives. Instead of rushing and going “all in” on this one effort, we can inform our leaders of the feedback and refocus on higher-priority concerns.</p>
<h3 id="bonusquestionsforyourchats">Bonus: Questions for your chats</h3>
<p>In order to get the most out of these chats with employees, you should treat them as candidate interviews. To help, I suggest going into each of these convos with a few core questions. I always like to do a <strong>start, stop and continue</strong>. This means asking:</p>
<ul>
<li>What should we as a business start doing?</li>
<li>What should we stop doing?</li>
<li>And what do we continue doing?</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s one of the most basic HR concepts, but it extracts the most relevant info every time.</p>
<p>Other questions I would suggest asking in stakeholder chats are:</p>
<ul>
<li>If our business had infinite time and money, what would you like to see done differently?</li>
<li>Who or what business do you really admire? How are they really killing it when it comes to company culture?</li>
</ul>
<p>I find people start to say, “Well, I’ve seen such and such company do this. Maybe we can implement something similar?”</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch6-3.svg" alt="Building an HR roadmap from scratch"></p>
<h2 id="step3identifywhattoincludeonyourroadmap">Step 3: Identify what to include on your roadmap</h2>
<p>Step two was weighing ALL the options of what to include on the roadmap, and now it’s time to make the official call on which items to include.</p>
<p>In my case, I decided to prioritize items related to improving the efficiency of existing processes. For instance, onboarding initiatives for new hires can take <em>looong</em>, so I made it a point to create and prioritize an initiative to automate and streamline it.</p>
<p>You can also include items related to wider company events—like town halls or ops retrospectives. In some cases, internal events fall under HR’s purview (despite us trying to shake off the party planner stereotype) so that can also be a focus on your roadmap. Or maybe you want to stick only to massive action items, such as implementing an HRIS or rolling out new employer benefits.</p>
<p>Something I personally include is <strong>budget</strong>. Budgets and costs impact every aspect of what we do in HR. Can we afford to roll out BambooHR? Can we invest in external training? <strong>Working budget in with each of your items can add valuable detail that will help with decision-making</strong>. (Roadmunk’s numerical fields are my saviour when it comes to this!)</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch6-4.svg" alt="Building an HR roadmap from scratch"></p>
<h2 id="step4chooseaviewandbuildtheroadmap">Step 4: Choose a view and build the roadmap</h2>
<p>Alright, with all your foundations in place, the next step is to actually build the damn thing. Luckily, Roadmunk offers two different views that play to different HR roadmap use cases.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-6-1.svg" alt="Building an HR roadmap from scratch"></p>
<p><mark>Heads up, this roadmap was built in Roadmunk! You can make your own version by going <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/hr-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter6">here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p>If you’re an HR team that wants a more detailed story of how your team will contribute to business growth, a <strong>Timeline View</strong> is for you. This view maps out your team’s milestones, targets and events for the upcoming year (or months or quarters).</p>
<p>It’s the view that helps you <strong>confirm if your goals are achievable and you have enough bandwidth</strong>—both in terms of time and people. Looking at the roadmap above, let's say I undershot for how much time I’d need to hire certain team members. Maybe I’ve realized I’ve only hired half the headcount I need and I’m a few weeks away from when that target should be hit. Having an overview of the year lets me see what's a lower priority that I can push to another quarter, or even next year, in order to achieve this goal.</p>
<p>Think of this view as your opportunity to walk stakeholders through your anticipated timelines and validate your targeted efforts and goals. (I welcome any debate with our leadership team!) <strong>It’s your chance at getting buy-in and obtaining any extra resources you may need</strong>.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-6-2.svg" alt="Building an HR roadmap from scratch"></p>
<p><mark>And if a Swimlane HR roadmap is more your speed, customize our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/hr-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter6">HR roadmap template here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p>I chose to go with our <strong>Swimlane View</strong> though, because I feel it’s tailored specifically for rapidly growing businesses (i.e. a company like ours!). This view doesn’t get rid of time altogether, but gives you an overview of the whole year by grouping things into <strong>loose time buckets like months or quarters</strong>. It’s a flexible, holistic overview of what’s going on with us over at HR.</p>
<p>And keeping things loosey-goosey is perfect for a growing business because our HR plan is always evolving. As new resources are brought in, priorities change and new tasks pop up that need to be addressed sooner rather than later. This means I need to be on my toes when planning. Using a flexible view that doesn’t latch onto specific timelines, helps me stay nimble (and calm) when I have to adjust plans accordingly.</p>
<p>I believe our Swimlane View is best suited for tracking <strong>who you’re hiring, what teams they’re joining and their respective onboarding initiatives</strong>. By pivoting the data on departments, you can quickly reference this view and see if you’re hiring for the right objectives, or whether any talent gaps exist. This also tells you which departments will need HR’s support in terms of onboarding, training or any other resources they need.</p>
<p>An additional benefit to this view is that it doesn’t just speak for HR; <strong>this view speaks on behalf of all departments</strong>. I can use this view to translate to the exec team that this is how each department lead wants to grow out their team—and ultimately the business. It acts as a consolidated view of all the hiring plans, so everyone in the business gets an in-your-face transparent picture of how the team headcount will grow.</p>
<p><mark>Go on, give Roadmunk a try with a <em>free 14 day trial</em> by <strong><a href="https://app.roadmunk.com/login/?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter6#/signup">signing up here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p>So, there you have it! As someone who had never built a roadmap in her life, this process helped me build an HR roadmap from scratch that I’m now using daily within my workflow. If you’re interested in trying it out for yourself, <a href="https://app.roadmunk.com/signup"><strong>sign up</strong></a> to kickstart your own HR roadmap. (If I can do it, you definitely can!)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[4 real-world marketing roadmap examples]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 5]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/marketing-roadmap-examples/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5b331466f77e1a0001447b0e</guid><category><![CDATA[Business]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[tarif]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 14:54:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch5.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch5.svg" alt="4 real-world marketing roadmap examples"><p>Any half-decent marketing is essentially storytelling.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As a marketer, everything you create needs to tell the story of your product and the value it offers your users. That’s why roadmaps are such a natural fit for marketing teams. A marketing roadmap <em><strong>tells the story</strong></em> of your marketing strategy.</p>
<p>As leader of the marketing team here at Roadmunk, I leverage a few iterations of my roadmap to communicate our team’s initiatives across our entire company. We obviously use a ton of tactical software, but I go back to my marketing roadmap every week to regroup on the big picture. More concretely, I use it in a few different contexts:</p>
<ul>
<li>I present our roadmap at our <strong>monthly town hall meetings</strong>, where our whole company can align on what our marketing team has in the pipe.</li>
<li>I show different pivots during <strong>strat alignment sessions</strong> to get buy-in from our executive team.</li>
<li>I use project-specific roadmaps to plan <strong>feature releases</strong> or <strong>big initiative launches</strong>.</li>
<li>I also use our roadmapping tool for <strong>lightweight resource planning</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>I thought it would be cool to give a window into my process and how I use different versions of my roadmap. For this exercise, I’m using our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/marketing-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter5">marketing roadmap template</a></strong>, which is accessible within Roadmunk. (And as a side note for non-marketers, we also have a wide selection of <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter5">roadmap templates</a></strong> that you can check out in-app or on our website.)</p>
<p>K, let’s go. 💨🚲</p>
<h6 id="ifyourewonderingwhattoolyoushouldusetocreateyourroadmapwevegotaguideforthathere">If you're wondering what tool you should use to create your roadmap, we've got a guide for that <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/product-roadmap-tools-comparison?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter5">here.</a></strong></h6>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch5-1.svg" alt="4 real-world marketing roadmap examples"></p>
<h2 id="thethemebasedmarketingroadmap">The theme-based marketing roadmap</h2>
<p>This is how I actually structure the roadmap I show in our town hall meetings. After trying a few variations, I decided that organizing quarterly by theme was clearest. Here’s why:</p>
<ul>
<li>Organizing by category was <strong>dead simple</strong> for everyone to understand. Even if you’re not a marketer, everyone knows who does digital marketing, who does content, who does design. It’s a crystal-clear way to orient the whole company to the activities of different members of our marketing team.</li>
<li>I tried a monthly roadmap, but it was just too constricting (and unrealistic) for our growing team at a growing company. Going quarterly gave us leeway for bigger projects, while offering some structure around time.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-5-1.svg" alt="4 real-world marketing roadmap examples"></p>
<p><mark>Build your own version of a theme-based marketing roadmap <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/marketing-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter5">here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch5-2.svg" alt="4 real-world marketing roadmap examples"></p>
<h2 id="thegoalbasedmarketingroadmap">The goal-based marketing roadmap</h2>
<p>When I’m doing strategy alignment with other leaders in our organization, I usually start by showing my category roadmap and explaining, “<strong>This is what we’re going to do.</strong>” Then I switch over to my goal-oriented roadmap and show, “<strong>This will be the impact of each of those projects.</strong>”</p>
<p>Our team evaluates success across a few different metrics, including <strong>generating qualified leads</strong>, <strong>building awareness</strong> for our company, and supporting sales to <strong>convert free trial users to customers</strong>. The goal-oriented marketing roadmap shows how you’re going to distribute resources to accomplish different types of goals.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-5-2.svg" alt="4 real-world marketing roadmap examples"></p>
<p>Using Roadmunk, it’s really easy to maintain two views that you can switch between in meetings. This is a screenshot of my actual '<a href="http://support.roadmunk.com/creating-and-working-with-views">Views</a>' drop-down for my marketing roadmap inside Roadmunk. Each view pulls from the same data set. It’s the same data, just structured differently—so maintaining each view is not finicky. During meetings, I’ll often pivot between different views to give the full picture of our marketing activities.</p>
<p><mark>Get goals-y by creating your own goals-based marketing roadmap <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/marketing-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter5">here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch5-3.svg" alt="4 real-world marketing roadmap examples"></p>
<h2 id="thewegotdeadlinesmarketingroadmap">The “we got deadlines” marketing roadmap</h2>
<p>Timeline is not my go-to marketing roadmap, but I do find it helpful (slash, sanity-saving??) when we’re rallying to a deadline with a particular date stamp. When we released the <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/new-roadmunk">new Roadmunk</a></strong>, I plotted every single element of the launch plan on a timeline roadmap, so we could make sure we’d resource correctly to complete each step before launch.</p>
<p>The marketing roadmap example below is probably more typical for <strong>process-driven teams that work on timelines</strong>. It shows a variety of marketing initiatives evolving over time, with projects assigned to particular team members. This is especially useful for <strong>teams that work with long (but strict) lead times</strong>.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-5-3.svg" alt="4 real-world marketing roadmap examples"></p>
<p><mark>Process-oriented marketing teams, this marketing roadmap template is available <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/marketing-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter5">here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch5-4.svg" alt="4 real-world marketing roadmap examples"></p>
<h2 id="thewhosdoingwhatmarketingroadmap">The “who’s doing what” marketing roadmap</h2>
<p>You may have noticed the “by person” view in the screenshot of my views tab above. When I’m doing quarterly planning, I’ll usually create a person-by-person breakdown of my roadmap. This <strong>ensures we have the resources to execute on our projects</strong>—and make sure no one is going to be wayyy over-burdened. This is also how I <strong>validate new hires</strong>: determining which projects will make the biggest impact towards hitting our goals, then visualizing what resources we need to get there.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-5-4.svg" alt="4 real-world marketing roadmap examples"></p>
<p>In a case like this, I can quickly see that Jamie doesn’t have much in her pipe. Meanwhile, Carly might be maxed out. Resourcing isn’t my primary purpose for building a roadmap, but it’s an easy way to get a snapshot of what’s happening.</p>
<p><mark>Construct your own interpretation of the above marketing roadmap by going <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/marketing-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter5">here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p>These examples show the four key ways I currently build my marketing roadmap. If you’re curious to try it for yourself, check out our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter5">roadmap template</a></strong> library to get started. Happy roadmapping! 😀</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why you need a roadmap for project management]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 4]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/project-roadmap/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5b3311fbf77e1a0001447b0c</guid><category><![CDATA[Business]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[tarif]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 14:53:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch4.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch4.svg" alt="Why you need a roadmap for project management"><p>As a project manager, you have a clear-cut mission: lead your team and project to 100% completion, by communicating and aligning everyone on the project in question. A project roadmap helps you precisely do that.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As an underutilized (and underestimated) tool within project management, a project roadmap is a tool we strongly believe should be implemented in a project manager's workflow—even if there's a project plan in place. Here’s our case for why you need a roadmap for project management.</p>
<h6 id="btwwealsowrotearealworldguidetocreatinganystyleofagileroadmapdownloadithere">Btw, we also wrote a real-world guide to creating any style of agile roadmap. <strong><a href="https://go.roadmunk.com/agile-roadmap-ebook?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter4">Download it here.</a></strong></h6>
<h2 id="whatisaprojectroadmap">What is a project roadmap?</h2>
<p>To define <em>what</em> a project roadmap is, we need to explain the <em>why</em> behind project roadmaps.</p>
<p>A project roadmap offers a project manager—and their relevant stakeholders—with <strong>a high-level overview of the project’s goals, initiatives and deliverables</strong>. And we’re not just talking project managers spearheading technical projects. It could be project leads for sales, marketing, HR, or otherwise; this roadmap applies to all your business departments.</p>
<p>A project roadmap is <strong>a bird’s eye view of a project</strong>, so that a project manager can get all their stakeholders on the same page regarding the major components of the project like milestones and overall objectives.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch4-1.svg" alt="Why you need a roadmap for project management"></p>
<h2 id="butwhatsthedifferencebetweenaprojectroadmapandaprojectplan">But what’s the difference between a project roadmap and a project plan?</h2>
<p>Well, the key difference between the two is that a project roadmap is what we stressed above: a <strong>high-level</strong> view of your project.</p>
<p>An effective project plan gets very in the weeds about what must happen for the project to be a success. Your project plan should provide granular answers to questions like:</p>
<ul>
<li>What is the value proposition?</li>
<li>How is the project scope being managed?</li>
<li>How much budget is allocated to this project?</li>
<li>What are the biggest risks? And what the contingency plans in place?</li>
</ul>
<p>It also addresses all the minute details of your project like client names, specific training requirements and staffing schedules. It’s your project’s behind-the-scenes context that shows every aspect of the project has been thoroughly considered and planned.</p>
<p>Your project roadmap is the big picture. <strong>It takes all the details in the project plan and surfaces the most crucial factors relevant to all stakeholders</strong>. In a really simple analogy, if your project roadmap is a photograph, your project plan is the same photograph under a microscope—so you can see every pixel.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch4-2.svg" alt="Why you need a roadmap for project management"></p>
<h2 id="sowhydoyouneedaprojectroadmap">So, why do you need a project roadmap?</h2>
<p>Yes, a meticulous project plan provides all the context you need for key stakeholders with very specific questions, but not every project member wants to go through pages and pages of documentation. For example, your CEO doesn’t need to sift through every technical and non-technical requirement you need for your project. They want a summary of when they can expect deliverables.</p>
<p>More often than not, <strong>stakeholders just need a quick check-in on when a deliverable is due or what the status of X task is</strong>. A project roadmap speeds up this process by providing a streamlined and focused version of the project plan. A project roadmap is what you want to present in your recurring project syncs so you can quickly get everyone aligned on timelines and milestones, without getting caught up on details. (And for team members who do need more details, the project plan is readily available for reference.)</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch4-3.svg" alt="Why you need a roadmap for project management"></p>
<h2 id="howshouldaprojectroadmaplook">How should a project roadmap look?</h2>
<p>With a project roadmap’s intended purpose in mind, you need to ensure you’re building a project roadmap that fulfills the why. Our template library offers two specific views for a project roadmap that can be adapted for any type of project you may be leading.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-4-1.svg" alt="Why you need a roadmap for project management"></p>
<p>The first view we offer is a <strong>Timeline View</strong> meant for deadline-oriented project managers and teams. For project managers whose biggest challenge might be managing expectations on timelines and deliverables, this view provides a snapshot of how the project’s key initiatives should unfold. Milestones can be used to explicitly point out to the team, “Hey, this is when this is due.”</p>
<p><mark>Create your own Timeline project roadmap <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/project-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter4">here</a></strong> and make our template your own.</mark></p>
<p>Similar to a Gantt chart, this view provides team members with a visual representation of not only the anticipated length of tasks, but how resourcing will evolve across the project. What really differentiates this view from your traditional Gantt chart though is the fact that you can pivot and filter the data based on various fields such as theme, status, owner or whatever else you see fit.</p>
<p>You can even double-up on data pivoting and have multiple fields represented on the roadmap. For example, in the above project roadmap you can clearly see who owns what task, whether the item falls under alignment, deliverables or research, and you can identify the status—all in one viewing. With a project roadmap you’re not forced to represent your project in a waterfall fashion; based on how you pivot the data you can represent your project timelines concurrently.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-4-2.svg" alt="Why you need a roadmap for project management"></p>
<p>For project managers and teams more concerned with the status of imminent tasks over the deadlines, our <strong>Swimlane View</strong> is more up your alley. This project roadmap provides a high-level visualization of which project tasks are complete, in progress or waiting in backlog.</p>
<p>This view summarizes the need-to-knows of each project task. Think of this as an ideal view for quick status updates or spontaneous syncs with stakeholders in agile/flexible environments that are known for shifting dates. Or even for longer-term projects that don’t have looming deadlines that <em>must be hit</em>.</p>
<p>You can also pivot the data so it’s categorized by theme or owner. By doing so, project managers can then share a more granular story about the status their project, allowing team members to hold themselves and others more accountable for their work.</p>
<p><mark>FYI: The Swimlane roadmap above is available to use and customize <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/project-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter4">here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch4-4.svg" alt="Why you need a roadmap for project management"></p>
<h2 id="rememberaprojectroadmapisthebigpicturenotadetailedbreakdown">Remember: A project roadmap is the big picture, not a detailed breakdown</h2>
<p>The main thing to remember is that your project roadmap is your project’s big picture—not its detailed breakdown. <strong>It’s NOT there to replace your project plan</strong>. It’s there as a companion piece for your project plan when you need to quickly present and coordinate everyone on critical project details.</p>
<p>Ultimately, you’ll be hard-pressed to find anyone willing to navigate through a heavily-detailed project plan everytime they have a small inquiry or need a speedy sync on your project. Visualizing the important components of the project plan, a project roadmap helps you push your team and project closer to the finish line.</p>
<p><mark>Create + share beautiful roadmaps: test drive Roadmunk with a <em>free 14 day trial</em> by <strong><a href="https://app.roadmunk.com/signup">signing up here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 3]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/business-roadmap-templates-for-non-product-teams/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5b330f23f77e1a0001447b0a</guid><category><![CDATA[Business]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[tarif]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 14:52:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch3.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch3.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"><p>When it comes to roadmaps, the common assumption is that they’re tools for a business’ technical teams, you know, like product or engineering. But your other business teams like marketing, sales and HR, shouldn’t be shafted. <strong>Roadmapping is a bigger necessity for them than expected</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Roadmaps are communication tools for <em>any</em> type of team to share and align their entire business on their goals and strategy. Non-product teams need to track their growth just as much as their technical counterparts, so that they too can play a hand in achieving overall business goals.</p>
<p>Below, we’ve outlined 7 business roadmap templates to help your non-product teams plan and contribute to business growth. (Just so you know, you can access all these roadmaps in our template library!)</p>
<ul>
<li>Marketing roadmap</li>
<li>Content marketing roadmap</li>
<li>Digital marketing roadmap</li>
<li>HR roadmap</li>
<li>Sales roadmap</li>
<li>Design roadmap</li>
<li>Ecommerce roadmap</li>
</ul>
<h6 id="technicalteamswegotyoutooheresaguideof10powerfultechnologyroadmaptemplates">Technical teams, we got you too. <strong><a href="https://go.roadmunk.com/10-technology-roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter3">Here's a guide of 10 powerful technology roadmap templates</a></strong>.</h6>
<h2 id="marketingroadmap">Marketing roadmap</h2>
<p>As a heavily deadline-oriented team, marketing tends to be in a constant state of balancing many projects and deliverables. As a result, your digital marketer needs your content marketer’s copywriting help, who needs your designer’s expertise, who needs to finish some work for the events manager and so on. Things are a little chaotic.</p>
<p>A marketing roadmap tidies up the chaos, by visualizing major marketing initiatives across the different verticals on the team (content, digital marketing, events, design, ABM, etc.), so that every team member gets what their fellow marketer is undertaking. By surfacing the team’s priorities and goals, every marketer can make better decisions regarding resourcing and planning.</p>
<p>While this roadmap is owned by and made for marketers, a marketing roadmap also serves as a communication line to the rest of the organization on what the heck is going on with marketing.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-1.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>Our marketing roadmap template offers two specific views. Our <strong>Timeline View</strong> allows you to map out when individual projects and initiatives will roll out over a specified timeframe. You can get very detail-oriented by pivoting the data on team verticals and owners so that everyone is aware of who is working on what and when.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-2.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>Our <strong>Swimlane View</strong> categorizes your marketing deliverables and projects into their respective verticals and easily-digestible timeframes like quarters, so the team (and business) can know what’s happening with each specific marketing function in each timeframe.</p>
<p><strong>P.S.</strong> If you want to get more in-depth into how you can visualize your marketing roadmap, our very own Marketing Director, Eleni, put together <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/marketing-roadmap-examples/">a list of four real-world ways</a></strong> she approaches our marketing team’s roadmap.</p>
<p><mark>Organize your marketing team and initiatives with our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/marketing-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter3">marketing roadmap template</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<h2 id="contentmarketingroadmap">Content marketing roadmap</h2>
<p>While a marketing roadmap covers all verticals of your marketing team, sometimes those specific verticals need a roadmap for themselves. One such team is content marketing.</p>
<p>When building a content marketing roadmap the key is to remember: it visualizes a high-level strategy, not the nitty-gritty. This roadmap isn’t where you list every single piece of content you’re publishing. Instead, you’re showcasing a zoomed-out version of your content strategy that highlights major milestones like a new ebook, or a podcast season, or a snazzy video series.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-3.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>Our <strong>Timeline View</strong> of a content marketing roadmap is meant for deadline-driven teams needing to sort through all the content projects they’re pushing. Mapping important content initiatives across months, quarters or a year, the projects can be grouped by marketing stage funnel. This grouping lets content teams communicate to the rest of marketing—and the organization—the business value of each project. Plus, they’ll be able to identify parts of the funnel they may be neglecting or over-exerting.</p>
<p>Furthermore, you can pivot the data based on owners, so that the content team can clarify priorities and ownership among themselves and to any curious stakeholders.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-4.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>For content teams that place more emphasis on progress over dates, the <strong>Swimlane View</strong> is a better companion. Scrapping the funnel stages, a swimlane content marketing roadmap groups major content projects by status such as Ideation, Writing and Published. By also pivoting the data on owners, content teams can keep track of everyone’s big content pieces—and how close they are to being published.</p>
<p><mark>Use our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/content-marketing-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter3">content marketing roadmap template</a></strong> to effectively outline your own content strategy.</mark></p>
<h2 id="digitalmarketingroadmap">Digital marketing roadmap</h2>
<p>Another marketing vertical that often requires its own roadmap is digital marketing. As a big lead generator for marketing—and thus a key contributor to business growth—digital marketing teams balance a slew of complex channels at once. A digital marketing roadmap visualizes how this team uses these different channels to promote their business and product, whether that’s through SEO &amp; SEM, display/banner advertisements, email or Google Adwords (to name a few).</p>
<p>Rather than outlining every action taken on these channels, digital marketing roadmaps highlight the most important channels and strategies enlisted by digital marketers. Digital marketers and marketing leads can use this roadmap to get buy-in from the rest of the organization regarding digital plans to funnel more leads to the business.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-5.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>Use our <strong>Timeline View</strong> to orient your digital marketers (and organization) around critical deadlines for your digital marketing projects. Get in-depth by pivoting on owners so that team members can hold themselves—and others—accountable for the projects they’re managing. This allows marketing leads to determine issues with resourcing, as well as ensure everyone is working towards the next major deliverable.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-6.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>The thing about digital marketing, it’s very experimental; meaning digital marketing teams need to be flexible. In these cases where strict(er) timelines don’t match your digital marketing plan, a <strong>Swimlane View</strong> is more relevant. By organizing work based on channels (SEO, paid search, social media, etc.) and charting it across easy-to-understand timeframes like quarters, the swimlane digital marketing roadmap offers a flexible visualization of your digital marketing plan.</p>
<p><mark>Customize our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/digital-marketing-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter3">digital marketing roadmap template</a></strong> to reflect your plan for digital lead generation.</mark></p>
<h2 id="hrroadmap">HR roadmap</h2>
<p>You can’t capture A+ talent without a plan. An HR roadmap is a tool precisely for that. A human resources department and/or recruiters use an HR roadmap to communicate their plan to grow out each team via new talent.</p>
<p>But business growth isn’t just influenced by hiring plans; company culture has a part to play in growing a business too. HR roadmaps are also an opportunity for HR teams to demonstrate company culture initiatives they plan on rolling out across the business to ensure healthy and happy employees.</p>
<p>While this document is an asset for HR and recruiters, this roadmap is beneficial to department leads as well. An HR roadmap communicate to C-level execs how a team will grow over time. Higher-ups can use the roadmap to determine if resourcing is being equally distributed or if certain talent gaps exist in the business.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-7.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>If keeping an up-to-date schedule for business growth is more your speed, consider using a <strong>Timeline View</strong> for your HR roadmap. Outlining when new roles will be added to each team across the next few months, quarters, or year, gets everyone on the same page for how each department (and the business) is evolving.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-8.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>Since hiring can sometimes take longer (or way less time) than expected, a timeline may not be the most appropriate view. Instead try a <strong>Swimlane View</strong>. Organizing hiring plans and HR initiatives across loose time buckets like quarters, instills flexibility into your HR plan.</p>
<p><strong>Sidenote</strong>: Our head of HR—and former non-roadmapper—Rebekah, shares her <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/hr-roadmap/"><strong>step-by-step process of building her first HR roadmap</strong></a> here at Roadmunk. (In case, you're apprehensive about using a roadmap.)</p>
<p><mark>Top-notch talent comes with a top-notch plan. Use our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/hr-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter3">HR roadmap template</a></strong> to chart an A+ HR plan.</mark></p>
<h2 id="salesroadmap">Sales roadmap</h2>
<p>A sales roadmap is an overview of the sales strategies put in place to hit targets like a specific MRR, ARR, or number of deals closed. But much like many of the roadmaps on this list, the main thing to remember is that it’s high-level; it’s not the place for every sales rep to visualize every lead they’re nurturing.</p>
<p>Sales leaders can apply this roadmap to align the entire sales team on how their work plays into the business’ wider vision. Plus, they this roadmap can communicate the team’s major goals and priorities to teams like marketing, product and operations, so that the rest of the business can get a better understanding of sales’ operations.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-9.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>Our <strong>Timeline View</strong> of a sales roadmap is extremely valuable for sales leaders who are sticklers for dates. This view aligns the sales team on major priorities and projects over the next few months, quarters or year, whether it’s related to strategy, lead generation or fighting retention and churn. And by surfacing key milestones like quarterly revenue goals, the timeline sales roadmap explicitly visualizes the goals that sales reps should rally around.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-10.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>Our <strong>Swimlane View</strong> of a sales roadmap is best suited for a global sales teams. A swimlane sales roadmap categorizes initiatives based on a team’s geographic location, providing a snapshot of how sales will grow region-by-region. For example, your US sales team might be cold calling your lead lists, while the Europe team is understandably working on securing leads from the European launch of your product.</p>
<p><strong>Another note</strong>: For growing sales teams, our VP of Sales and Customer Success, Jalil, breaks down <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/sales-roadmap/"><strong>how your sales roadmap will evolve from a startup to an SME to an enterprise</strong></a>.</p>
<p><mark>Build your own <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/sales-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter3">sales roadmap</a></strong> to visualize how you'll rake in big $$.</mark></p>
<h2 id="designroadmap">Design roadmap</h2>
<p>Streamlining a design team’s creative process into important phases like research, creative approach, delivery and implementation, a design roadmap concretely lays out the work each designer is responsible for. Design teams can use this roadmap to essentially check themselves on how long it’s taking them to complete certain creative projects.</p>
<p>At the same time, design teams can use the roadmap to communicate to the rest of the business how essential design projects are progressing. This helps design teams manage expectations for any not-design-savvy stakeholders demanding you whip up a design in a short timeframe.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-11.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>We offer two views for our design roadmap template; the first being the <strong>Timeline View</strong>. Simply outlining each designer’s task for your preferred timeframe, this view indicates expected timeframes for each step of the creative process. It also pulls out essential milestones like client presentations and submission deadlines, allowing designers to plan and execute their work match up with these dates.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-12.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>The second view is our <strong>Swimlane View</strong> which focuses less on communicating deliverables and more on communicating progress. The swimlane design roadmap makes it dead-simple to view the status of each designer’s projects—whether it’s being defined, planned or implemented.</p>
<p><mark>Streamline your design process with our flexible <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/design-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter3">design roadmap template</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<h2 id="ecommerceroadmap">Ecommerce roadmap</h2>
<p>Organizing and visualizing the work behind growing an ecommerce platform, an ecommerce roadmap brings transparency to this multi-layered process involving multiple teams. Businesses running an ecommerce platform can use this roadmap to communicate to the entire organization the specific work done by teams like marketing, design and development over the next <em>insert specific chunk of time</em>.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-13.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>Seeing as ecommerce platforms are influenced by various external time periods like back to school or seasonal changes, a <strong>Timeline View</strong> is very helpful. Emphasizing milestones and crucial dates, a timeline ecommerce roadmap helps these teams strategically plan their work around these dates. Showcasing each team’s projects across the next few months, quarters or year, allows each team and the business overall to see what exactly teams are doing to contribute to platform growth. And if you want to get even more granular, you can group work by owners so that you can tell an even more detailed story of your ecommerce growth plan.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-3-14.svg" alt="Business roadmap templates to grow your non-product teams"></p>
<p>For ecommerce platforms that aren’t as time-sensitive, you can apply the <strong>Swimlane View</strong> for your ecommerce roadmap. Charting each team’s deliverables and major projects across time buckets like quarters, this view serves a bird’s-eye view of how your business plans on growing out their ecommerce platform.</p>
<p><mark>Move towards owning your digital marketplace with the help of our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/ecommerce-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter3">ecommerce roadmap template</a></strong>.</mark></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 2]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/business-roadmap-examples/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5b32940cf77e1a0001447b05</guid><category><![CDATA[Business]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[tarif]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 14:51:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch2.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch2.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"><p>In our last chapter we specified that business roadmaps are effective vehicles for visualizing and communicating business growth.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>While we broke down the most common roadmap use case for visualizing business growth, it’s definitely not <em>the</em> only way to spin your business roadmap; a business roadmap can take on countless forms.</p>
<p>To help narrow the scope for any business planning their own growth, we’ve outlined eight business roadmap examples below that are aimed at organizations looking to scale. (<a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter2"><strong>Btw, all of these roadmaps are available in our template library which you can check out here!</strong></a>)</p>
<ul>
<li>Strategic roadmap</li>
<li>Change roadmap</li>
<li>Capability roadmap</li>
<li>Business development roadmap</li>
<li>Business intelligence roadmap</li>
<li>Data strategy roadmap</li>
<li>Startup roadmap</li>
<li>Enterprise architecture roadmap</li>
</ul>
<h6 id="searchingfortherighttoolforyourroadmappingneedsletourroadmaptoolguidehelpyou">Searching for the right tool for your roadmapping needs? Let our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/product-roadmap-tools-comparison?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter2"><strong>roadmap tool guide</strong></a> help you.</h6>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch2-1.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<h2 id="strategicroadmap">Strategic roadmap</h2>
<p>Simply put, a strategic roadmap communicates your business’ vision. Outlining the steps to achieve your mission, this business roadmap example hinges on long-term objectives and deadlines. Keyword: long-term. That means ixnay on including product features and short-term wins; this roadmap is reserved for overarching goals like fundraising rounds and MRR targets.</p>
<p>Generally owned by senior-level stakeholders, this roadmap should be accessible to every employee (not to edit per se, but to view). By granting this access, you align your entire organization on your plans to grow the business and you encourage teams to develop projects that contribute directly to said growth.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-1.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>For organizations planning their business growth strategy over the next few months, quarters or years, use a <strong>Timeline View</strong>. Businesses can use this view to track key initiatives and milestones that each of your departments will undertake to contribute to the overall mission.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-2.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>A <strong>Swimlane View</strong> is for businesses that are less strict about the “when” of their strategic planning. This roadmap assigns each team an individual swimlane, and organizes their respective strategic initiatives by status. This way, any stakeholder can quickly glance and know what strategic project is upcoming, in progress or completed.</p>
<p><mark>Plan to achieve your big vision with our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/strategic-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter2">ready-to-use strategic roadmap template</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch2-2.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<h2 id="changeroadmap">Change roadmap</h2>
<p>Business growth requires many, <em>many</em> changes that a business needs to communicate across the board—especially for heavyweight, complex organizations. A change roadmap visualizes and expresses how a business plans to evolve in order to achieve scaling.</p>
<p>Similar to a strategic roadmap, your change roadmap gets employees bought-into your business’ long-term plan. In this case, we’re talking a long-term plan of change initiatives, like team restructures, current system overhauls or introductions of new infrastructures. This roadmap is particularly useful for team leads responsible for implementing change processes within their teams.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-3.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>For businesses that want to explicitly see how changes will unfold in the future, a <strong>Timeline View</strong> best serves you. Breaking down change processes team-by-team, this view aligns the entire business on how each team will progress with the business. What makes this view even handier is the fact that you can surface major milestones, so every team has deadlines to work towards.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-4.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>Since change is unpredictable, assigning a schedule to it isn’t exactly easy. Hence, why we offer a <strong>Swimlane View</strong>. Not focused on dates, a swimlane change roadmap offers a more flexible alternative for evolving businesses. Still breaking down change by team, this roadmap view groups change initiatives based on their status such as research, planning and review.</p>
<p><mark>Get ahead of the effects of business growth with our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/change-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter2">change roadmap template</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch2-3.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<h2 id="capabilityroadmap">Capability roadmap</h2>
<p>You know those big projects you’ve always envisioned, but they’re so grand they take years to implement? Yeah, a capability roadmap helps you plan how to execute these projects.</p>
<p>Plotting the large-scale capabilities a business wants to tackle in the next few quarters or years, a capability roadmap revolves around potential rather than your present projects. It plans the super-ambitious, game-changing goals beyond features and releases. Think launching 5 product lines in three years, or opening up a global office in Europe, or owning 25% of the market share in two years.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-5.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>Seeing as this roadmap is meant for planning years into the future, a <strong>Timeline View</strong> of your capability roadmap just makes sense. Showcasing each team’s planned capabilities for the next few years, the timeline capability roadmap paints the big picture of where your business is going and when they plan on getting there.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-6.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>If a timeline is too detailed for your capability plans, a <strong>Swimlane View</strong> might be more up your alley. Organizing your plans into loose and/or fuzzy time buckets like years or “Future,” this roadmap view offers a digestible snapshot of how and when each team plans on tackling capability initiatives.</p>
<p><mark>Turn your big, audacious ideas into a reality with our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/capability-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter2">capability roadmap template</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch2-4.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<h2 id="businessdevelopmentroadmap">Business development roadmap</h2>
<p>For super-speedy businesses barreling towards major growth by the end of the year, a business development roadmap is an ideal asset for your toolkit. This roadmap highlights the essential tasks that contribute to rapid revenue and market-share growth, often in a one-year timeframe.</p>
<p>Sales, marketing and product champion this roadmap as they use this tool to plan and communicate their business development projects that play a hand in aggressive business growth. For example, sales can use this roadmap to visualize their “land and expand” strategies, while product can outline initiatives like a referral program or live chat that will capture more customers—and ultimately rake in $$.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-7.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>The <strong>Timeline View</strong> of a business development roadmap says to the entire organization, “Hey, here’s how each team will contribute to business development over the next year.” Any team at your business can sneak a peek at this roadmap to understand how the rest of the organization will participate in “biz dev” and thus, plan their initiatives accordingly.</p>
<p>Milestones can clearly highlight the KPIs the business wants to hit during this growth period, thereby giving your teams specific goals (and deadlines) to strive towards. On top of that, you can also explicitly communicate external factors, like changes to privacy laws or updates to a certain OS, that could muddy the “biz dev” waters.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-8.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>For the less deadline-oriented businesses, a <strong>Swimlane View</strong> lets you bucket your business development tasks into loose buckets such as quarters. It’s a sweet and simple way to manage all the teams’ expectations on when certain things must get done.</p>
<p><mark>Reach your biz dev goals (even) faster with our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/business-development-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter2">business development roadmap template</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch2-5.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<h2 id="businessintelligenceroadmap">Business intelligence roadmap</h2>
<p>For business intelligence (BI) teams wanting to maximize their effect on organizational decisions and growth, enlist in a business intelligence roadmap. Owned and operated by BI managers and their teams, this type of roadmap visualizes and communicates all aspects of BI including data mining and analysis to querying and reporting.</p>
<p>BI managers can use this roadmap to plan how their team can optimize internal business processes to be more efficient, which leads to better informed decisions by the business, which culminates in scaling. An added benefit of this roadmap is that it helps BI managers inform the rest of the organization and C-level executives about what BI is doing and how they plan on being a part of the business’ bigger picture.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-9.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>In our template library we offer two views for your BI roadmap. The Timeline View allows BI teams to portray how their activities and initiatives will occur over the next months, quarters or years. With a focus on KPIs and major dates, this view allows BI teams to plan their initiatives to knock down these targets.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-10.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>The <strong>Swimlane View</strong> of the BI roadmap hones in on the BI team’s higher-level goals versus the dates that they’re hitting. Assigning BI tasks to different business verticals like data governance, process improvement or architecture &amp; infrastructure, this roadmap then organizes tasks based on BI goals like strategy, growth and efficiency.</p>
<p><mark>Build your own business intelligence roadmap with our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/business-intelligence-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter2">ready-to-use template</a></strong> (just like above ☝️).</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch2-6.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<h2 id="datastrategyroadmap">Data strategy roadmap</h2>
<p>A data strategy roadmap tells the rest of your organization how you’ll improve your business’ data operations—such as data collection, storage, management, and application. Well-planned and properly stored data = better business decisions = better organizational growth.</p>
<p>This roadmap tends to fall into the hands of your CIOs, CTOs and data teams. These data-leaning individuals use this roadmap to ensure their business’ data strategy fits nicely with not only their business processes, but security and information management best practices.</p>
<p>Think of this roadmap as a way to answer any pressing questions—internally and externally—regarding how your business handles data. Are you legally (and ethically) collecting the right data from your users when they visit your website? Are you storing any “unclean” data that should be expunged from your records? What security protocols are in place in case of a data breach?</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-11.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>With our <strong>Timeline View</strong> showcase the data initiatives planned for the future. Splitting the roadmap into three different phases—planning, process and review—the timeline roadmap streamlines your data strategy so that the rest of the organization can easily digest the data plan.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-12.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>For more flexibility with your data strategy, apply a <strong>Swimlane View</strong>. Rather than mapping data initiatives across an extensive timeline, the team’s activities and tasks are sorted into smaller time frames like months or quarters. This way, the team (and organization) can see which types of data security initiatives are getting priority and when.</p>
<p><mark>Get your data strategy in order with our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/data-strategy-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter2">data strategy roadmap template</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch2-7.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<h2 id="startuproadmap">Startup roadmap</h2>
<p>While a business roadmap can be adapted for any-sized organization, the reality is if you don’t have many teams or resources, the common business roadmap template <em>might</em> not be as applicable. That’s why we suggest a startup roadmap for businesses still finding their footing.</p>
<p>A startup roadmap helps smaller businesses plan how they’ll get off the ground running and then scale to a much larger size. Because starting your own business is very much a roller coaster of an experience, a startup roadmap helps bring some clarity to the messy and experimental process.</p>
<p>As a fresh-out-the-gate business, startups tend not to be heavily process-oriented. As a result, startup roadmaps lean more on the high-level and flexible side (as should all roadmaps!), so as to adapt quickly with the often-chaotic startup environment. The roadmap is a small business’ way of zooming in on their end goal (hint: business growth) and mapping out a feasible plan to achieve said goal.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-13.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>With the <strong>Timeline View</strong>, a startup roadmap can clearly and effectively lay out all the future tasks that need to be completed to get your business standing. Pivot your data based on teams, owners, or theme depending on how early you are in the startup game. And also highlight any crucial milestones you’re aiming for, so that you can bring some razor-sharp focus to the up-and-down startup process.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-14.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>The truth is, as a startup, you’re probably not too strict about timelines, nor are you actually sticking to everyone. So, that’s where a <strong>Swimlane View</strong> is most useful. For startups that just aren’t as confident (or trusting) of their timelines, apply a swimlane view for your business where the focus is on what the status of each project is, not when it’s getting pushed out.</p>
<p><mark>Startups, we got you. Chart your growth with our customizable <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/startup-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter2">startup roadmap template</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch2-8.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<h2 id="enterprisearchitectureroadmap">Enterprise architecture roadmap</h2>
<p>On the other end of the spectrum, you’ve got enterprises that also need a roadmap to bring clarity to the chaos as well. Designed for your big corporations and complex, towering businesses, an enterprise architecture roadmap presents how an enterprise will evolve its own infrastructure in the coming years.</p>
<p>Focusing on organizational agility, efficiency and stability, this business roadmap illustrates the steps that will be taken to evolve the enterprise’s architecture from status quo to end goal. Mapping and planning this evolution communicates to the rest of the organization how the enterprise will stay competitive and brace itself for changes in the market.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-15.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>For those businesses wanting to explicitly see how the enterprise infrastructure will evolve over (insert here) timeframe, a <strong>Timeline View</strong> is your best bet. Not only does this roadmap chart an enterprise’s evolution across different business verticals like product, applications and strategy, but it also puts heavy emphasis on goals and KPIs that the enterprise is concerned with.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-2-16.svg" alt="8 business roadmap examples for scaling your organization"></p>
<p>For enterprises that want to provide a quick summary of their business growth, a <strong>Swimlane View</strong> may be more your speed. Charting enterprise architecture projects across flexible timeframes like months or quarters, this roadmap provides an overtly-transparent depiction of which project will be completed when.</p>
<p><mark>Bigwig businesses, we've got an <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/enterprise-architecture-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter2">enterprise architecture template</a></strong> you can make your own.</mark></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[What is a business roadmap?]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 1]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/what-is-a-business-roadmap/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5b3289daf77e1a0001447b00</guid><category><![CDATA[Business]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[tarif]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 14:50:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch1.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-ch1.svg" alt="What is a business roadmap?"><p>As an entrepreneur, you’ve got business goals to hit and a plan in mind to get there. While a business plan seems like the obvious choice for jotting down this plan, it’s not always the most relevant artifact for planning growth.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Business plans can get <em>super</em> granular and balloon to the size of a novel. And truth be told, it’s a ton for stakeholders to digest.</p>
<p>When planning organizational growth, you want <strong>a flexible document that captures and succinctly presents key goals, dates and plans of action relevant to all your stakeholders</strong>. Not an endless document you have to sift through with a fine tooth comb. Enter a business roadmap.</p>
<h6 id="findtherightroadmappingtoolforyouandyourbusinessdownloadourfreeguidehere">Find the right roadmapping tool for you and your business. <strong><a href="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/what-is-a-business-roadmap/">Download our free guide here.</a></strong></h6>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch1-1.svg" alt="What is a business roadmap?"></p>
<h2 id="thebusinessroadmapdefinition">The business roadmap definition</h2>
<p>What is a business roadmap? Much like a business plan, <strong>it’s a long view of where your organization is going and how you’re getting there</strong>. But what differentiates it from your typical business plan is that it’s a <strong>higher-level</strong> visualization of your business’ big picture.</p>
<p>A business roadmap illustrates your company’s major objectives and strategies for achieving growth. For businesses comprising of multiple departments, a business roadmap prevents individual teams from being siloed off by clearly outlining the business’ future and each department’s role in upcoming growth.</p>
<p>Now, business growth can be illustrated in various types of roadmaps like a strategic roadmap, a startup roadmap or even something as specific as a marketing or HR roadmap. But the most common use case for mapping business growth is a roadmap that visualizes <strong>key business growth projects and deadlines across all of a company’s departments</strong>. So let’s take a look at this business roadmap example.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/07/Bus-ch1-2.svg" alt="What is a business roadmap?"></p>
<h2 id="howtovisualizeyourbusinessroadmap">How to visualize your business roadmap</h2>
<p>Let’s assume we’re dealing with a business beyond the two-people-in-a-garage phase. (Not that this roadmap can’t work for small businesses, but it’ll be much simpler than what we’re presenting.) <strong>You’ve got different teams and departments with several balls in the air.</strong> Product is planning a rollout to mobile. Marketing needs to ensure the go-to marketing plan for this launch is ready. Plus, they’re planning their next event. Sales is following up on a crapload of leads brought in from the last event. And HR, well, they’re on a hiring roll for all departments.</p>
<p>With so many moving parts, there’s a lot for anyone in a business to wrap their head around. Your C-level execs need clarity on whether your departments are headed in the right direction. Your department heads need to know that their projects are contributing to the overall growth of the business—and not being stalled by other departments. And if you’re a business vying for investors or partners, these external stakeholders sure as heck want to know your future plans for expansion.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-1-1.svg" alt="What is a business roadmap?"></p>
<p><mark>All set to build your own Timeline business roadmap? <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/business-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter1">Check out our ready-to-use template.</a></strong></mark></p>
<p>A <strong>Timeline View</strong> of your business roadmap provides a straight-to-the-point overview of major projects and deadlines team-by-team. Plotting each department’s growth strategy across  months, quarters or a year (the timeframe’s completely up to you!), businesses can accurately assess each team’s <strong>time/resource allocation</strong> and <strong>contribution to growth-related initiatives</strong>. As well, this view lets teams see how they’re working in conjunction with the rest of the org to grow the business, squashing (or identifying) any feelings of being siloed off.</p>
<p>A timeline also lets a business pull out important dates via <strong>Milestones</strong>. By laying out expected deadlines, the entire organization can be on the same page about when to expect certain initiatives or goals to be complete, making it easier for teams to plan their work accordingly.</p>
<p>For businesses that crave details, this view can be pivoted many different ways to tell a more detail-oriented story of your business’ plan. For instance, you can pivot the roadmap by owner (like in the roadmap above), which allows higher-ups to determine if too much strain is being put on certain resources. The end result: <strong>better decisions about work distribution</strong>.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/bus-1-2.svg" alt="What is a business roadmap?"></p>
<p><mark>Maybe the Swimlane business roadmap like ☝️ is more your speed. <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/business-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BusinessRoadmapChapter1">Get a template here.</a></strong></mark></p>
<p>For businesses that don’t really dig the idea of allocating specific timeframes to every <em>single</em> item, you can organize your business roadmap in a <strong>Swimlane View</strong>. Still showing each department’s individual projects and strategies, you can have swimlanes dedicated to each team and then organize items by any timeframe. Think of this view as <strong>a snapshot of each team’s primary objectives for certain periods of time</strong>. Someone should be able to look at this business roadmap and quickly understand what each team is trying to achieve in each timeframe.</p>
<p>But maybe you’re a more status-focused entrepreneur. In that case, you can pivot this view to highlight which projects per team are <strong>in progress vs. scheduled vs. proposed</strong>. This is another way to provide a transparent snapshot to anyone who wants an update on how the business is developing.</p>
<p>As your business evolves though, your business goals will change and your roadmap will have to reflect that. In the above examples, we’re still dealing with a lot of high-level business initiatives like operations determining onboarding practice, or sales cold calling their lead lists, or marketing rolling out conversion tracking. The more you grow, the more precise your goals get.</p>
<p>Maybe you want to map out <strong>specific revenue targets</strong> or <strong>fundraising goals</strong>. Or maybe you pivot to only showcase each department’s <strong>business development initiatives aimed at very-rapid revenue growth</strong>. Or if you’ve reached enterprise status, maybe you only map <strong>LARGE, ambitious business capabilities</strong> like releasing new product lines or owning certain percentage of market share. Your business roadmap has to mature in order to reflect the more developed and thorough goals that come with business growth.</p>
<p>So go ahead, try one of our business roadmap templates. <strong>No matter your business size, you’ll always need a plan to achieve growth</strong>. Don’t solely depend on a business plan to strategize growth; implement a business roadmap to align your entire organization on every team’s efforts to grow the business.</p>
<p><mark>If you want to build more roadmaps, give Roadmunk a try with a <em>free, 14-day trial.</em> <strong><a href="https://app.roadmunk.com/signup">Sign up here.</a></strong></mark></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 4]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/roadmap-templates/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5b352f6cf77e1a0001447b1c</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[tarif]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 14:42:09 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/basics-ch4.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/basics-ch4.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"><p>Roadmapping isn’t an exercise reserved solely for product teams—or rather, it shouldn’t be.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/what-is-a-product-roadmap/">Roadmaps are communication tools</a></strong> and are perfect vehicles for teams of all kinds to <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/get-product-roadmap-buy-in/">share their priorities and goals with the rest of the organization</a></strong>.</p>
<p>To help you out, we created <strong>seven templates</strong> that can be used across your organization to boost visibility into high-level business strategy and more tactical team-based goals.</p>
<h2 id="1theproductroadmap">1. The product roadmap</h2>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-1a.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>Let’s start with the bread and butter of roadmaps: <strong>product</strong>.</p>
<p>For product-driven companies—be it B2B SaaS shops or consumer-facing apps—a product roadmap is essential to organizational alignment. A product roadmap illustrates <strong>high-level product strategy and demonstrates how a product will evolve over time</strong>. It includes upcoming features and the nitty gritty of product development—like technical considerations and resourcing.</p>
<p>A product roadmap is a powerful communication tool that product managers use to align different departments on one vision. <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/how-to-use-your-product-roadmap-for-sales-purposes/">It empowers the sales team to lead informed product conversations with prospects</a>, the marketing team to plan campaigns that align with feature releases and HR to determine who to hire and when.</p>
<p>Our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/product-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">product roadmap template</a></strong> was built knowing that <strong>there isn’t just one way to create a product roadmap</strong>. Some product teams love key dates, while others prefer an agile approach.</p>
<p>For deadline-sticklers, our template’s timeline view charts how your product will grow and evolve over time. You can organize your team’s tasks into pre-set buckets—including new features, infrastructure and stickiness. You can also highlight important events, like a feature release, with milestones.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/Home-4-1b.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>The swimlane view (above) sorts your tasks according to progress, not time.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/product-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">Give our product roadmap template a whirl.</a></strong></p>
<p>P.S. For organizations with multiple product lines, our portfolio roadmap template makes it possible to illustrate and communicate a high-level overview of how each different products will evolve and how they relate to each other. <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/portfolio-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">Try the portfolio roadmap template.</a></strong></p>
<h6 id="ifyoureanagileproductteamcheckoutourguidetocreatinganystyleofagileroadmapping">If you're an agile product team, check out our <strong><a href="https://go.roadmunk.com/agile-roadmap-ebook?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">guide to creating any style of agile roadmapping</a></strong>.</h6>
<h2 id="2thestrategicroadmap">2. The strategic roadmap</h2>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-2a.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>A strategic roadmap is used to <strong>communicate an organization’s vision and mission</strong>, illustrating the key steps required to bring these two things to fruition. This roadmap is accessible to every employee, and it helps ensure that every department is ideating and working on initiatives that serve the organization’s bigger strategic aims.</p>
<p>This particular roadmap is created and championed by <strong>senior-level stakeholders</strong>. Business objectives are generally mapped out across the long-term.</p>
<p>Unlike a product roadmap that outlines what plans need to be executed in the short-term, <strong>a strategic roadmap is all about the long game</strong>. An organization’s vision and mission are often hefty, audacious goals that can be broken down into smaller, bite-size initiatives across many years.</p>
<p>Our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/strategic-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">strategic roadmap template</a></strong> includes a timeline view. Use this view to track your key strategic initiatives and milestones over upcoming months, quarters and years.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-2b.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>Alternately, if you wish to be less strict with dates, our swimlane view visualizes your strategic initiatives based on progress.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/strategic-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">Lay out your vision and mission-critical business objectives with our strategic roadmaps.</a></strong></p>
<h2 id="3theinnovationroadmap">3. The innovation roadmap</h2>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-3a.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>An innovation roadmap is a great companion to the strategic roadmap. A roadmap can and should be used to <strong>map new areas for growth opportunities, testing new ideas, tracking competitors and keeping up with advancing technologies</strong>. Organizations only remain competitive within their markets when they continuously look forward to discover new business models and ways to bolster their products with value-added improvements.</p>
<p>An innovation roadmap is generally built and managed by an organization’s product managers and its executives to align all departments on strategic initiatives. They help companies <strong>achieve disruption and avoid getting disrupted themselves</strong>.</p>
<p>Track innovative achievements, like shipped features, against the work that your team is doing to keep sharp—like competitive benchmarking and breaking down barriers preventing new and exciting things from shipping.</p>
<p>Our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/innovation-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">innovation roadmap template</a></strong> includes a timeline view to plan and track what your organization is doing in upcoming quarters and years, while also accessing and preparing for risks.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-3b.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>The swimlane view provides a flexible way to keep track of your game-changing ideas by visualizing progress across key verticals like product and efficiency gains.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/innovation-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">Document your disruption tactics with our innovation roadmap template.</a></strong></p>
<h6 id="needhelpfindingtherightroadmappingtoolforyouwehaveaguidetohelpwiththat">Need help finding the right roadmapping tool for you? <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/product-roadmap-tools-comparison?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">We have a guide to help with that</a></strong>.</h6>
<h2 id="4themarketingroadmap">4. The marketing roadmap</h2>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-4a.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>Marketing teams are generally project-oriented, and it’s very common for marketing teams to be slammed with multiple deliverables and initiatives at once. It gets hectic and unmanageable if not documented. Enter the marketing roadmap.</p>
<p>A marketing roadmap highlights <strong>key projects and priorities across all marketing channels and functions</strong>, creating clarity in the chaos. It charts all priorities and initiatives across all channels that marketing is responsible for—such as content, digital advertising and events. Creating an in-depth marketing roadmap surfaces a team’s highest priorities and keeps all of its marketers on track.</p>
<p>As an added bonus, a marketing roadmap also serves as a key communication tool for marketing teams to share their plans across their whole organization.</p>
<p>Our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/marketing-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">marketing roadmap template</a></strong> comes with two types of views baked in. The timeline view allows you to meticulously plan when key initiatives will unfold across each of your marketing channels.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-4b.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>Our swimlane view groups your marketing initiatives into channels and manageable, easy-to-understand timeframes, like quarters.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/marketing-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">Organize your marketing team and initiatives with our marketing roadmap template.</a></strong></p>
<h2 id="5thehrroadmap">5. The HR roadmap</h2>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-5a.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>An HR roadmap is owned by an organization’s recruiters and human resources team to <strong>build and manage hiring plans and chart HR initiatives</strong>. It visualizes how each department within an organization will evolve and provides a snapshot of the roles being added and when.</p>
<p>This type of roadmap is extremely helpful for <strong>catching gaps in talent, ensuring that your organization is adequately resourced</strong> and that <strong>growth is properly balanced across departments</strong>. Each department leader can also use this roadmap to flag what resources they need and identify when their team will burst.</p>
<p>This roadmap also provides insight into what HR is working on to make employees happier in their day-to-day like changes to benefits plan, new referral bonuses, etc.</p>
<p>Our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/hr-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">HR roadmap template</a></strong> includes a timeline view so that your organization can see which new hires will be added to the team in upcoming months, quarters or years.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-5b.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>Predicting exact hiring dates isn’t always possible given that some roles are more difficult to fill than others. Our swimlane view brings flexibility to your HR plan.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/hr-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">Start mapping your hiring and HR initiatives with our HR roadmap template.</a></strong></p>
<h2 id="6thetechnologyroadmap">6. The technology roadmap</h2>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-6a.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>A technology roadmap outlines <strong>how an organization plans to use technology to achieve their goals</strong>. It can be used in a couple of different ways.</p>
<p>Some organizations employ a technology roadmap to <strong>monitor technology considerations and resources</strong> within their product’s research and development strategy. Other organizations use a technology roadmap to <strong>visualize the administration of internal processes and systems</strong>, like information security audits and tracking employee hardware.</p>
<p>In both cases, a technology roadmap communicates complex initiatives within an easy-to-follow, actionable plan.</p>
<p>Our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/technology-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">technology roadmap template</a></strong>’s timeline view enables you to simply visualize timing for all technology initiatives coming up in your pipeline.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-6b.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>Our swimlane view provides a high-level snapshot of your technical priorities, and it tracks the progress of initiatives that are in progress, completed or within the backlog.</p>
<p><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/technology-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4"><strong>Turn your complex technology initiatives into an easy-to-read roadmap with our template.</strong></a></p>
<h6 id="wecover10morewaystobuildapowerfultechnologyroadmapinourfreedownloadableguide">We cover 10 more ways to build a powerful technology roadmap in our <strong><a href="https://go.roadmunk.com/10-technology-roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">free downloadable guide.</a></strong>.</h6>
<h2 id="7theprojectroadmap">7. The project roadmap</h2>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-7a.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>A project roadmap can be used by <strong>various departments across your organization</strong>—sales, customer success, admin, etc.</p>
<p>It’s a roadmap that can be applied to a wide range of projects that involve multiple stakeholders and moving parts. It provides <strong>a high-level overview of a project’s objectives, initiatives and deliverables</strong>.</p>
<p>A project roadmap is different from a project plan. While a project plan tracks each and every tactical detail, a project roadmap instead provides an overview of the most important components and milestones (i.e. the big picture). It aligns teams on key milestones and keeps everyone on the right path.</p>
<p>Use the timeline view of our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/project-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">project roadmap template</a></strong> to see key tasks and deadlines, and how your resources will be allocated over time.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/06/home-4-7b.svg" alt="7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment & communication"></p>
<p>Our swimlane view makes it easy to quickly visualize which tasks are complete, in progress or waiting in the backlog.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/project-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=BasicsChapter4">Align your project team with our template.</a></strong></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[7 customizable product roadmap templates]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 6]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/7-product-roadmap-templates/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a9daccdf77e1a0001447a61</guid><category><![CDATA[Product]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Jillean]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2018 20:27:49 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/product-ch6.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/product-ch6.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"><p>There isn't just <em>one</em> type of product roadmap. Product teams have a lot on the go — from managing a product or two (or three or four), coordinating feature launches and managing development / design resources. With this in mind, we created seven different product roadmap templates to help product teams stay on track.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Check ‘em out — you’ll definitely find one or two (or three or four) that will work for you and your team.</p>
<h2 id="1productroadmaptemplate">1. Product roadmap template</h2>
<p>Let's start with the basics. This bread-and-butter <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/product-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">product roadmap template</a></strong> illustrates a team's high-level product strategy. It includes upcoming features and technical considerations — while also demonstrating how a product will evolve over time.</p>
<p>Product teams can use this holistic iteration of a product roadmap to align executives and other departments on their long-term product vision.</p>
<p><strong>Timeline:</strong> Use the Timeline view of the product roadmap template to chart how your product will grow over time. You can organize your tasks within key buckets — including new features, infrastructure and stickiness.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/product-tl.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p><strong>Swimlane:</strong> If you require more flexibility, use Swimlane to sort tasks based on progress, not time.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/product-sw-1.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p>Try the <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/product-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">product roadmap template</a></strong> and make it your own.</p>
<h2 id="2portfolioroadmaptemplate">2. Portfolio roadmap template</h2>
<p>For organizations that have more than one product on the market, the <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/portfolio-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">portfolio roadmap template</a></strong> is 👌. It provides a high-level overview of what's going on with the entire product line. Product managers can use this to show stakeholders how each individual product will evolve and how they all relate to each other.</p>
<p><strong>Timeline:</strong> Use the Timeline view of the portfolio roadmap template to illustrate how how your family of products will hit the market and grow.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/portfolio-tl.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p><strong>Swimlane:</strong> Swimlane provides a quick snapshot of how each part of your product line is progressing.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/portfolio-sw.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p>Try the <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/portfolio-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">portfolio roadmap template</a></strong> to illustrate how your product family will grow.</p>
<h2 id="3productdevelopmentroadmap">3. Product development roadmap</h2>
<p>The <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/product-development-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">product development roadmap template</a></strong> provides product teams with a tool that cleary communicates where a product is going — and it helps PMs align all stakeholders on the chosen direction.</p>
<p>This roamdap shows how a product will enter the market and compete in it — while ensuring cohesion and support across all stages of the product development process.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/product-development-tl.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p><strong>Timeline:</strong> The Timelane view turns your release plans, technical stories, design projects and marketing initiatives into a crystal-clear plan with set deadlines and deliverables.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/product-development-sw.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p><strong>Swimlane:</strong> Perfect for agile teams, the Swimlane view tracks the progress of your product development strategy.</p>
<p>Try the <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/product-development-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">product development roadmap template</a></strong> to build out a solid strategy.</p>
<h2 id="4productlaunchroadmap">4. Product launch roadmap</h2>
<p>The <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/product-launch-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">product launch roadmap template</a></strong> illustrates your entire go-to-market strategy — all the way from pre- to post-launch.</p>
<p>This is a roadmap that crosses departmental lines to include all of the stakeholders involved in a product launch — including product, development, marketing and sales. It clearly outlines all of the tasks required to make sure that pre-launch, launch and post-launch tactics are successfully executed.</p>
<p><strong>Timeline:</strong> Timeline view can be used to document how your go-to-market strategy will progress over a set time frame. You can organize tasks by department and other buckets important to your planning.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/product-launch-tl-3.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p><strong>Swimlane:</strong> With Swimlane, you can sort your go-to-market tasks into categories like pre-launch, launch and post-launch.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/product-launch-sw.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p>Try the <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/product-launch-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">product launch roadmap template</a></strong> to plan your next go-to-market strategy.</p>
<h2 id="5featureroadmap">5. Feature roadmap</h2>
<p>The <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/feature-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">feature roadmap template</a></strong> is a great tool for PMs to track the development and releases of their product’s key features. This roadmap also communicates the direction of a product's feature development to internal and external stakeholders.</p>
<p>This roadmap hones in on feature development without going into detail on other areas within the organization — keeping the focus on initiatives that add value to users.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/feature-tl.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p><strong>Timeline:</strong> Use Timeline to visualize the future of your product and illustrate when new features will be coming through your pipeline.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/feature-sw.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p><strong>Swimlane:</strong> Alternately, Swimlane buckets your features into buckets that are not tied to deadlines.</p>
<p>Try the <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/feature-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">feature roadmap</a></strong> to align your team on what features are coming and when.</p>
<h2 id="6softwareroadmap">6. Software roadmap</h2>
<p>The <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/software-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">software roadmap template</a></strong> is used by product and engineering teams to keep track of software development processes at a high level. This template visualizes both short- and long-term initiatives that an organization needs to launch new features and stay ahead of the market.</p>
<p>A software roadmap often includes tasks that cross different technical teams — like development, product and design — to plan out how they'll work together to hit their collective goals.</p>
<p><strong>Timeline:</strong> This view can be used to see how each team’s projects will be delivered over time.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/software-tl.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p><strong>Swimlane:</strong> For teams that don't adhere to strict deadlines, use Swimlane to track progress.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/software-sw.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p>Try the <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/software-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">software roadmap</a></strong> to align your technical teams on upcoming projects.</p>
<h2 id="7agileroadmap">7. Agile roadmap</h2>
<p>For the most flexible of product teams, the <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/agile-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">agile roadmap template</a></strong> illustrates how your product strategy will evolve without a heavy focus on dates. The agile roadmap is more concerned with themes or progress.</p>
<p>The agile roadmap template includes four different iterations.</p>
<p><strong>Theme:</strong> This version of the agile roadamp group initiatives into high-level themes.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/agile-theme-based.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p><strong>Fuzzy time:</strong> Build a Swimlane that organizes tasks into loose buckets of time.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/agile-fuzzy-time.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p><strong>Sprint:</strong> Plan out your realeases for both the short- and long-term.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/agile-sprint.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p><strong>Agile-ish:</strong> For when you need to know when tasks will happen but can't quite assign deadlines.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/agile-agile-ish-1.svg" alt="7 customizable product roadmap templates"></p>
<p>Try the <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/agile-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">agile roadmap template</a></strong> — no matter your agile style.</p>
<p><mark>Check out our libray of <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=ProductRoadmapChapter6">35+ roadmap templates</a></strong>. Access them for free by signing up for a Roadmuk trial.</mark></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[5 challenges of a technology roadmap presentation]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 4]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/5-challenges-of-a-technology-roadmap-presentation/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5aa67398f77e1a0001447a81</guid><category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Jillean]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2018 13:39:29 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/tech-ch4.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/tech-ch4.svg" alt="5 challenges of a technology roadmap presentation"><p>As we’ve described in the past, a roadmap presentation is more than just words on a page or screen or whiteboard. It’s an alignment exercise meant to affirm your stakeholders’ motivations and receive nods of approval before moving forward with your plans.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Acing a roadmap presentation requires a whole lot of planning and preparation, because pushback is plentiful and getting people to reach a consensus on a single plan is challenging (<strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/how-to-ace-your-roadmap-presentation/">it’s why we wrote an entire guide to help</a></strong>). But presenting a technology roadmap in particular has its own unique subset of problems that aren’t common when presenting other types of roadmaps. After all, it is the document that encompasses ALL the technical and infrastructure-related efforts that impact the functioning of an organization.</p>
<p>Here are a few common challenges you’ll experience during a technology roadmap presentation, as well as methods for mitigating these obstacles.</p>
<h6 id="letourfreeguidehelpyoubuildtherighttechnologyroadmapforyourteamdownloadithere">Let our free guide help you build the right technology roadmap for your team. <strong><a href="http://go.roadmunk.com/10-technology-roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Technology%20Roadmap%20Ebook&amp;utm_source=TechnologyRoadmapChapter4">Download it here.</a></strong></h6>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch4-1.svg" alt="5 challenges of a technology roadmap presentation"></p>
<h2 id="challenge1translatingtechnicallanguage">Challenge 1: Translating technical language</h2>
<p>Building a technology roadmap means your roadmap is going to have, well, technical stuff on it. And unfortunately, not all your stakeholders are the tech-savviest people around. Receiving questions around “that doo-dad” and “thingamajiggy” from non-technical individuals should be expected.</p>
<p>Not everyone will comprehend every technology initiative on the roadmap—or its effects—as deeply as you. This means during your technology roadmap presentation, you should be cognizant of the language being used.</p>
<p>Sure, if you’re speaking to super technical stakeholders, put that tech talk on full blast!</p>
<p>But if not, reel in the technical talk before you lose your audience and feel like any adult talking in the Charlie Brown world. If you’ve lost your audience, you can say good riddance to any stakeholder-wide approval.</p>
<p><mark>Ready to start roadmapping? Get started with our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/technology-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter4">tech roadmap template</a></strong> and make it your own.</mark></p>
<p><strong>Solution:</strong></p>
<p>The solution to this is not to ‘dumb things down’ per se. The solution is to communicate relevant value and end-goals to your audience; ensure your presentation speaks to the things that your non-technical audiences want to hear.</p>
<p>Each type of stakeholder wants to see something different. Your customer success team wants to know what the customer gets out of upgrading the deployment infrastructure. Sales is concerned with how this upgrade will impact the timeline of delivering a specific feature.</p>
<p>So rather than presenting your technology roadmap’s super-technical view that you show to developers and DevOps (who are interested in the nitty-gritty), present a technology roadmap that has higher-level descriptions and lumps the more technical stuff into more digestible chunks. This way you can say to non-technical stakeholders, “We’re improving infrastructure phase 1,” and give an overview of how it impacts their work, versus saying, “We’re upgrading our JavaScript library from Knockout JS to React,” and (likely) being met with blank stares.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch4-2.svg" alt="5 challenges of a technology roadmap presentation"></p>
<h2 id="challenge2forgettingthebackgroundtasks">Challenge 2: Forgetting the ‘background’ tasks</h2>
<p>A technology roadmap documents both the obvious and not-so-obvious technology initiatives in an organization. So another common challenge that arises with your technology roadmap presentation is that a lot of the not-so-obvious, but equally important, initiatives get lower priority in favor of ‘flashier’ tech projects. That is to say, stakeholders are drawn to more prominent—and relevant to them—items on your technology roadmap versus the very, very essential tasks that are worked on in the background.</p>
<p>Take security for example. A crapload of work goes into maintaining security protocols and keeping data safe. You could allot a big chunk of your technology roadmap just to implementing new security tools. However, during your technology roadmap presentation, stakeholders may be more concerned with why implementing new servers is taking so much time, rather than security-related tasks that are just as vital, but not as in-your-face on the roadmap.</p>
<p>This leaves room for less discussion about these ‘background’ tech tasks and more opportunity for intense questioning when these background tasks do appear on stakeholders’ radars at later technology roadmap presentations.</p>
<p><strong>Solution:</strong></p>
<p>Dedicate time to presenting these ‘background’ tasks. Rather than waiting for your stakeholders to notice it and bring it up, you should call attention to the parts of the roadmap that you want addressed. As the keeper and researcher of your technology roadmap, you included those ‘background’ items on the roadmap for a reason and you want the sign-off. Carving out time to discuss these items during your technology roadmap presentation lets you proactively achieve affirmation from your stakeholders.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch4-3.svg" alt="5 challenges of a technology roadmap presentation"></p>
<h2 id="challenge3guesstimatingbasedonunknowns">Challenge 3: Guesstimating based on unknowns</h2>
<p>The unknowns when it comes to technology pile up quickly. Will this new technology integrate with our current system properly? Will it meet expectations and standards that the vendor promised us? How long will it take to get up and running? How many resources do we need to research and implement this new technology? And so on.</p>
<p>With so many questions you can only answer once you start working with the technology, creating a technology roadmap can sometimes feel like shooting in the dark. The lack of information results in making wild guesses about timelines and deadlines that you include on the technology roadmap. It’s a lot of trial and error.</p>
<p>As a result, this opens your technology roadmap presentations to a lot of scrutiny—especially if in the past you’ve been wrong about timelines. And the last thing you want is your stakeholders not confident in the timelines and plan you’re presenting.</p>
<p><strong>Solution:</strong></p>
<p>Maintain that your technology roadmap is a statement of intent. <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/what-is-a-product-roadmap/">We believe that all roadmaps should be considered—and presented—as statements of intent.</a></strong></p>
<p>A technology roadmap is a plan that can and 100% will change. If you stress this point and align everyone on this definition before and during your technology roadmap presentation, your stakeholders can’t hold you to every single detail being presented. This definition manages their expectations and eases any tension that may come with changing deadlines or wonky timelines. Your stakeholders will understand the roadmap is a plan and not the be all, end all.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch4-4.svg" alt="5 challenges of a technology roadmap presentation"></p>
<h2 id="challenge4technologyinitiativesareunpredictable">Challenge 4: Technology initiatives are unpredictable</h2>
<p>This challenge ties into the previous one. The reason why many individuals will find themselves making crazy guesses about how long the items on their technology roadmap will take is because truthfully, introducing and integrating new technologies is unpredictable. It’s not as simple as downloading and installing an app on to your desktop. It’s a matter of shifting an entire infrastructure and making sure it doesn’t crash your servers. And the bigger the org is, the more complex the procedure gets.</p>
<p>This means the length of some projects on your technology roadmap are hard to gauge—and might just take way longer than anticipated. That also means a lot of stakeholders asking: “Why is this taking so long?” “Why can’t we get it done by x date?” “What’s stopping us from completing this quicker?” These may be familiar questions when presenting any roadmap, but with a technology roadmap it’s especially challenging feedback because you can’t compromise the quality of big tech projects to meet arbitrary deadlines and expectations.</p>
<p><strong>Solution:</strong></p>
<p>If the challenge is that you can’t predict how long the task will take, then just break it up. Literally split tasks into phases and put them on your roadmap as such. That way during your technology roadmap presentation you can present bigger tasks in smaller blocks and be more confident in the amount of time you’ve allotted to each block.</p>
<p>It’s like reading a post and seeing a giant wall of text. It’s overwhelming and makes you think I don’t know how long this is going to take me. Breaking the text up makes it seem more manageable to conquer—even though it’s the same word count. Apply that same idea to your roadmap and you—and your stakeholders—can feel more confident about the timelines you’re presenting, since it’s much easier to manage shorter bursts of time, rather than a seemingly drawn-out project.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch4-5.svg" alt="5 challenges of a technology roadmap presentation"></p>
<h2 id="challenge5peopledontlikechange">Challenge 5: People don’t like change</h2>
<p>Okay, this is a universal challenge that extends beyond tech, but it’s particularly significant for technology roadmaps. Users hate when their favorite tech or app suddenly is turned on its head. (Remember all the Facebook re-designs?) And you can expect the same behavior during a technology roadmap presentation.</p>
<p>When change doesn’t sit well with a stakeholder, you might hear something along the lines of, “Things aren’t broken! Why the change?” And frankly, it’s a legitimate fear. There’s always risk when introducing new technology, especially as we’ve previously pointed out that technology comes with plenty of unknowns. So while discomfort to change can be founded, it unfortunately makes it harder to get your technology roadmap approved.</p>
<p><strong>Solution:</strong></p>
<p>Honestly, we’re going to repeat ourselves here—with a twist. Break your key technology initiatives up, but also over-communicate why you’re introducing this new initiative AND why you’re breaking it up. Explain that you want to mitigate the project’s risks and by splitting it into major phases, you can then better monitor and tackle any emerging issues. This approach offers a compromise to any change-resisting stakeholders and assures them that you’re considering the potential liabilities at hand.</p>
<p><mark>Create + share beautiful roadmaps: test drive Roadmunk with a <em>free 14 day trial</em> by <strong><a href="https://app.roadmunk.com/signup">signing up here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[3 technology roadmap examples]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 3]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/3-technology-roadmap-examples/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5aa66f12f77e1a0001447a7f</guid><category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Jillean]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2018 13:39:10 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/tech-ch3.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/tech-ch3.svg" alt="3 technology roadmap examples"><p>The term ‘technology roadmap’ is broad in its application, so we created three distinct examples to showcase its versatility.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>While one of the common applications of a technology roadmap is to plan out the administration and evolution of an organization’s technology stack, the technology roadmap can go beyond your common “<strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/it-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter3">IT systems roadmap</a></strong>.”</p>
<p>Some organizations use a technology roadmap to strategize how their technology initiatives will help them achieve their own research and development goals. Others may use this roadmap to visualize and streamline internal tech processes and systems—like information security audits and organizing employee hardware. Or maybe you’re just drowning in a crapload of tools and tech and a roadmap can get you sorted.</p>
<p>No matter your use case, a technology roadmap is a flexible enough document (at least it should be!) that can be pivoted to apply to your specific scenario. Below we introduce three technology roadmap examples that demonstrate the adaptability of this roadmap type and that will help you kickstart your own technology roadmap. (P.S. All these roadmaps are available in our template library that you can access <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter3">right here</a></strong>.)</p>
<h6 id="needmoreexampleswevegot7moreinourfreeguidetotechnologyroadmapsdownloadithere">Need more examples? We've got 7 more in our free guide to technology roadmaps. <strong><a href="http://go.roadmunk.com/10-technology-roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Technology%20Roadmap%20Ebook&amp;utm_source=TechnologyRoadmapChapter3">Download it here.</a></strong></h6>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch3-1.svg" alt="3 technology roadmap examples"></p>
<h2 id="itroadmap">IT roadmap</h2>
<p>We’d say this technology roadmap example is pretty similar to an internal IT systems roadmap. Both an IT and internal IT systems roadmap explicitly lay out how a business plans on building and maintaining internal technology solutions. But with an <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/it-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter3">IT roadmap</a></strong>, expect more <strong>emphasis on how the IT initiatives will support the company-wide vision</strong>. It’s less, “Who’s owning what IT project?” and more, “What’s the business value of this IT initiative?”</p>
<p>Think of it as a melding of your business and IT strategies; relaying to the rest of the organization how your IT strategy aligns with your business goals. For example, a SaaS company that wants to convert 30% of their free customer base to paid this year might require a marketing automation system so that marketing can nurture and upsell free users. On top of that, sales and CS might need a new, more powerful CRM system to keep up with the influx of new customers and keep them happy. An IT roadmap can align all these teams on all that “mumbo-jumbo” and, well, make it not “mumbo-jumbo” but rather clear.</p>
<p><strong>An IT roadmap answers questions like:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>What types of IT initiatives will you be rolling out in such and such timeframe?</li>
<li>What business goal will this IT initiative help achieve?</li>
<li>How will this IT initiative (whether it’s an app, new technology, internal process, etc.) help us ultimately grow as an organization?</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Who should use this type of roadmap?</strong><br>
You can expect your org’s technology leaders to implement and apply this roadmap. Your CTOs, CIOs, IT managers. Not only does this roadmap help tech leaders attain company-wide alignment on their strategy, but it lets these leaders be steps ahead of technological shifts at the organization. With this roadmap, planning ahead and prioritization of IT projects becomes more feasible and scrambling to put out IT-incited fires becomes less of a reality.</p>
<p><strong>What does an IT roadmap look like?</strong><br>
Since it’s meant to be an organization-wide doc, your IT roadmap will probably have a lot of eyes on it. A lot of eyes = a lot of questions. One of the main questions: “What’s the status on x?” A Swimlane View of our IT roadmap answers that question quickly by organizing the big IT projects into Backlog, In Design, In Progress and Completed. This way if you or any other departments need a refresher on the status of certain initiatives, they have a consistent reference point.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-3-1.svg" alt="3 technology roadmap examples"></p>
<p>If the questions and pushback you receive revolve around the question of “when,” flipping your IT roadmap over to a Timeline View can provide simple answers. This view communicates how everything will roll out across upcoming months, quarters or years.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-3-2.svg" alt="3 technology roadmap examples"></p>
<p><mark>This IT roadmap is available as a template in our library. <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/it-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter3">Get it now.</a></strong> And make it your own.</mark></p>
<p>Or get even more granular by pivoting by theme and discover where most of your IT efforts are allocated. And from there, call the shots in terms of redistribution or resourcing. For example, in the above roadmap you can see integrations seems to be a hefty organizational goal this year, whereas improvement-related projects don’t appear to be as prominent.</p>
<p>Based on this roadmap, you might allocate more resources from your improvement projects to support upcoming integrations because you know the team’s putting more emphasis on rolling out integrations than tech improvements. Again, unlike your internal IT systems roadmap, an IT roadmap is not about listing who’s owning what IT project; it’s about communicating how these IT initiatives fulfill your business goals.</p>
<p>Major IT milestones can also be thrown on to the roadmap to demonstrate when goals are expected to be met. Not only will this show progress, but it’ll get all stakeholders working towards the same timeline.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch3-2.svg" alt="3 technology roadmap examples"></p>
<h2 id="applicationroadmap">Application roadmap</h2>
<p>With an app for almost every part of a business workflow, it can get overwhelming to remember what to sign into, when and why (remembering all your passwords is already hard enough). An <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/application-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter3">application roadmap</a></strong> is a technology roadmap example designed for visualizing the abundance of apps that an organization integrates within their workflow, so that smarter decisions and prioritization can be made regarding the applications portfolio.</p>
<p>As businesses evolve, implementing the right tools becomes increasingly important towards maximizing business growth. An application roadmap removes any uncertainty around which apps should be implemented, which team is using what and which business areas are impacted by what. Bringing clarity to complex application infrastructures, an application roadmap is ideal for getting the best value from each application within your workflow. Plus, it helps teams prioritize which app implementation will happen when.</p>
<p><strong>Who should use this type of roadmap?</strong><br>
As a tech administrator, the application roadmap falls under your umbrella. Whether you’re an operations manager or an IT team member, you’re the best individual to oversee an applications roadmap since you have the deepest insight into your application portfolio. As with any technology roadmap (or roadmap, in general), getting input from each stakeholder team ensures you get the application stack in order.</p>
<p><strong>What does an application roadmap look like?</strong><br>
If you’re balancing a whole slew of applications and need to get nitty-gritty about the “when” and “why,” a Timeline View of your application roadmap is most effective. Mapping out how your application portfolio will be upgraded and maintained over time, this view of an application roadmap is a simple way to update stakeholders on when (and where) new tools or upgrades are required.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-3-3.svg" alt="3 technology roadmap examples"></p>
<p>If you’re more process-oriented (and time is less of a pressing concern) then the Swimlane View may be more your speed.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-3-4.svg" alt="3 technology roadmap examples"></p>
<p><mark>Create your own application roadmap now with our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/application-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter3">ready-to-use application roadmap template</a></strong>.</mark></p>
<p>Progress is the primary component of this technology roadmap example, as applications are organized into their respective stages of evaluation, implementation and maintenance.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch3-3.svg" alt="3 technology roadmap examples"></p>
<h2 id="developmentroadmap">Development roadmap</h2>
<p>The <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/development-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter3"><strong>development roadmap</strong></a> is probably the most in-the-weeds technology roadmap example, as this is the roadmap based only on your dev team’s work. Highlighting the technology initiatives, epics and features all set up in the engineering pipeline, the development roadmap communicates a dev team’s primary goals.</p>
<p>So, while a development roadmap gets more in-depth than other technology roadmap examples on this list, it still is a high-level approach. That means this isn’t the place to track your issues or projects; it’s the place for dev teams to share what the heck their team is actually working towards.</p>
<p><strong>Who should use this type of roadmap?</strong><br>
This one’s for all the engineering leaders; whoever is overseeing the development team(s) and communicating with the rest of the organization regarding the dev pipeline. Those are the people who should have their hands on this roadmap, as they can speak best to what’s upcoming in the workflow, and any tradeoffs that must be considered when changes are requested.</p>
<p><strong>What does a development roadmap look like?</strong><br>
Since the development roadmap is all about the dev workflow (and agile is the status quo at tech companies), you can organize your development roadmap by sprints. By categorizing your features and projects based on which sprint they’ll be developed in, you can portray a clearer picture to the rest of your organization about when they can expect what.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-3-5.svg" alt="3 technology roadmap examples"></p>
<p>But that’s not the only way you can represent your development roadmap in a Swimlane View. Structuring your roadmap so it showcases which projects and features are ready for dev, makes it superrr clear to anyone asking questions about the status of certain initiatives. (This one’s for anyone who doesn’t want to get incessantly pinged when something is in development).</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-3-6.svg" alt="3 technology roadmap examples"></p>
<p>Granted, the bigger your organization gets, the more likely time will have to be incorporated in your roadmap. Presenting your development roadmap in a Timeline View lets you showcase the “when” to the rest of your organization and manage their expectations of the dev workflow. But just remember if you are using a Timeline, reiterate that it’s a statement of intent and therefore can (and probably will) change.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-3-7.svg" alt="3 technology roadmap examples"></p>
<p><mark>Psstt... this roadmap ☝️ was created in Roadmunk. <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/development-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter3">Get the ready-to-use development template free</a></strong>.</mark></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to create a technology roadmap]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 2]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/how-to-create-a-technology-roadmap/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5aa66a8bf77e1a0001447a7d</guid><category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Jillean]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2018 13:38:42 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/tech-ch2.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/tech-ch2.svg" alt="How to create a technology roadmap"><p>Here’s a step-by-step process to create a technology roadmap—no matter which way you visualize it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We offered a couple of ways to approach a technology roadmap in <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/what-is-a-technology-roadmap/">the previous chapter</a></strong>, but here we do a deeper-dive into how to get to those final products. Whether you end up with a Swimlane or Timeline View of your technology roadmap (which are both available in our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/technology-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter2">template library</a></strong> btw), you’ll encounter similar questions and points of consideration when creating a technology roadmap.</p>
<h6 id="getourguideoftenpowerfulpracticalwaystobuildyourtechnologyroadmapdownloadithere">Get our guide of ten powerful (&amp; practical) ways to build your technology roadmap. <strong><a href="http://go.roadmunk.com/10-technology-roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Technology%20Roadmap%20Ebook&amp;utm_source=TechnologyRoadmapChapter2">Download it here.</a></strong></h6>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch2-1-1.svg" alt="How to create a technology roadmap"></p>
<h2 id="1establishthewhy">1. Establish the why</h2>
<p>Knowing the why = having a purpose to your roadmap. With the “why” top of mind you’ll know what to include on your technology roadmap and create a doc with an end-goal—rather than an aimless document that your CEO is asking for. So, first ask yourself: <strong>Why do I need this technology roadmap?</strong></p>
<p>While <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/how-to-create-a-product-roadmap/">a product roadmap is all about tracking your product features, improvements and strategy</a></strong>, a technology roadmap is all about strategizing the work that supports your product and organization. Technology roadmaps organize the infrastructure-related technologies and tools that need to be put in place to make sure product-related shit actually happens. Yes, that means there can be overlap between your product and technology roadmaps (after all, technology is almost always going to be essential to your product strategy), but that doesn’t mean every single one of your tech-related projects belongs on the product roadmap and vice-versa.</p>
<p>Basically, if you’re finding there are a bunch of infrastructure-related projects you want to put on your product roadmap that don’t fit anywhere, it’s usually time to implement a technology roadmap. It should be a plan that demonstrates how your technology initiatives support your product initiatives.</p>
<p>But that’s only one way to look at your technology roadmap. Your technology roadmap can take on so many different forms. There’s the <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/what-is-a-technology-roadmap/">IT systems roadmap</a></strong> we introduced in our last chapter, or there are technology roadmaps meant for aligning your org on <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/it-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter2">how your IT strategy ties into your business strategy</a></strong>. Or you can even split up your IT initiatives and only focus on what your development team is working on, and then have a separate roadmap for your internal tools and processes related to non-product related teams like marketing, sales, CS and operations.</p>
<p>The concept of a technology roadmap is broad, that’s why there are so many incarnations. But it’s also why figuring out why the hell you need the doc beforehand is so crucial. Once you have the purpose down pat, you can effectively move forward with the next steps of creating a technology roadmap.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch2-2.svg" alt="How to create a technology roadmap"></p>
<h2 id="2identifyandinterrogateyourstakeholders">2. Identify—and interrogate—your stakeholders</h2>
<p>With the basic motivation behind your technology roadmap understood, the next question to answer is: <strong>who’s seeing your technology roadmap?</strong> Knowing which pairs of eyes will ultimately analyze, push back and question the roadmap, offers you an audience to tailor to and a clearer idea of what needs to be on the doc. However, the follow-up question to this is: <strong>who gets input into your technology roadmap?</strong></p>
<p>The answer to this question isn’t exactly mutually exclusive to who’s seeing your roadmap, but there is some differentiation. Chances are people who are invested in the ‘final’ roadmap will want a say in it. For instance, if upgrading your servers will impact product development speeds, your product managers and dev team will probably have a few concerns about when that should happen.</p>
<p>But in cases where your technology roadmap is expected to reach your C-level executives, you’re most likely not knocking on the doors of your CTO, CIO, C-<em>insert abbreviation</em> asking for help putting together the roadmap you’ll be presenting to them. They’re too engrossed in high-level strategy to know (or care about) the minutiae of your IT infrastructure.</p>
<p>**Side note: **Of course, this also all depends on how your organization is structured. If you’re a smaller company or startup, your CTO or CIO might actually be the ones managing your roadmap.</p>
<p>Your next key step is defining which stakeholders will just see the roadmap and those who should be involved in the technology roadmapping process.</p>
<p>Once you know who you need to go to for input, start speaking to them. Seriously, just grill them and find out what you should be including on the roadmap, what makes sense to them in terms of formatting and so on. Just like you talk to your customers to understand what they want out of a product, you want to talk to your front-line people that work with the technology everyday –– the ones most impacted by infrastructure changes and updates. This includes talking to your product team, DevOps and your developers to understand such things as where technology can be brought in to release some pressure, costs and resourcing, areas of improvement, etc.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch2-3.svg" alt="How to create a technology roadmap"></p>
<h2 id="3prioritizeextinguishyourbiggestfires">3. Prioritize: Extinguish your biggest fires</h2>
<p>Once you’ve gathered all required information from your stakeholders, it’s time to start building the technology roadmap. How do you sift through all your gathered info and map it out so your stakeholders can align on one unified technology strategy?</p>
<p>There are many ways you can go about prioritizing what you put on your technology roadmap. After all, you (and your stakeholders) know your organization’s infrastructure needs best. But when it comes to your technology roadmap, we suggest prioritizing based off your biggest fires. What are your most pressing weaknesses in your technology stack? What, from a technology standpoint, is holding up your organization from achieving its business goals or preventing your product strategy from reaching the finish line?</p>
<p>Maybe the production system needs reconfiguring and it’s hindering your devs and causing them to lose their hair. Or your database system is out-of-date and needs to be updated to 21st century standards. Whatever the case, identifying holes in your infrastructure can highlight what needs to be addressed first. From there you can figure out how you can bring in technologies to alleviate these issues, which in turn will shape what you put on the roadmap first and second and third and so on.</p>
<p>Essentially, creating your technology roadmap is a twofold exercise: an audit of your tech infrastructure AND a planning exercise in optimizing the same infrastructure. When you first approach your technology roadmap, keep these two exercises in mind, as that will be what helps you prioritize what goes on your roadmap and determine your long-term, high-level technology strategy.</p>
<h3 id="anotherwaytoprioritize">Another way to prioritize: $$$</h3>
<p>While we strongly recommend determining prioritization for your technology roadmap based on biggest fires, another popular approach is to base your roadmap off of costs. Maintaining an org’s tech infrastructure ain’t a cheap operation, and sometimes the technologies and processes in place aren’t cost-efficient.</p>
<p>If you’re an organization highly-concerned with costs, or you’re finding your technology processes draining your bank, identifying the most costly tech initiatives might be a more appropriate prioritization technique. Minimizing costs of pricey tech projects could be considered a ‘big fire’ for your team.</p>
<p>Balancing your technology strategy between cost-reduction initiatives and projects tackling your org’s most-pressing tech concerns is another clear-cut way to organize your technology roadmap and get everyone on the same page for how you’re approaching your technology strategy.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch2-4.svg" alt="How to create a technology roadmap"></p>
<h2 id="4selectyourstructure">4. Select your structure</h2>
<p>The final step in the technology roadmapping process is choosing how to visualize and organize all the research you’ve gathered. We offer two visualizations of a <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/technology-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter2">technology roadmap in our template library</a></strong>: the Swimlane View and Timeline View. Your visualization comes down to you and what you see best fits your organization.</p>
<p>We find that the newer and smaller the org, the better suited the Swimlane View is for your technology roadmap. A Swimlane is meant for those companies who aren’t setting hard deadlines and dates for their tech initiatives. Instead progress &gt; time.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-2-1.svg" alt="How to create a technology roadmap"></p>
<p>With the Swimlane view you get a quick snapshot of what’s going on with your technology infrastructure and can easily mark progress on each individual project. This structure is ideal for when you may not have the confidence yet to attach dates to each item on the roadmap.</p>
<p><mark>Create your own Swimlane technology roadmap <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/technology-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter2">here</a></strong> and make our template your own.</mark></p>
<p>For more ‘mature’ companies that have been established for some time and don’t have the privilege of ignoring dates, the Timeline View is a better option for your technology roadmap.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-2-2.svg" alt="How to create a technology roadmap"></p>
<p>The more resources you have and the more complex your org gets, the harder it gets to ignore time. Stakeholders become concerned with ‘the when’ and how long they should be waiting, so a Timeline View provides clarity when it comes to your technology projects. Not only can all your stakeholders rally around common dates, but with a Timeline View you can also easily align on resourcing.</p>
<p><mark>Create + share beautiful roadmaps: test drive Roadmunk with a <em>free 14 day trial</em> by <strong><a href="https://app.roadmunk.com/signup">signing up here</a></strong>.</mark></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[What is a technology roadmap, really?]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 1]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/what-is-a-technology-roadmap/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5aa2e1c9f77e1a0001447a6b</guid><category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Jillean]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2018 13:37:47 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/tech-ch1.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/tech-ch1.svg" alt="What is a technology roadmap, really?"><p>One of the most popular roadmaps in our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter1"><strong>template library</strong></a> is the technology roadmap. And its popularity is a result of its broad application.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>“Technology roadmap” is an umbrella term that encompasses several different roadmap sub-types and iterations. A few examples include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Development roadmap</li>
<li>Application roadmap</li>
<li>Internal IT systems roadmap</li>
</ul>
<p>One of the broadest—and most universal—applications of this type of roadmap, however, is defining and documenting the administration of an organization’s internal IT system. So, as an example, let’s walk through what this type of roadmap looks like.</p>
<p>Since most organizations use a hefty collection of tools, maintaining this stack is often complex and taxing on resources. An internal IT systems roadmap helps teams implement a clear plan of action and make smarter decisions about technology.</p>
<h6 id="wecreatedafreeguidetohelpyouidentifybuildtherighttechnologyroadmapdownloadithere">We created a free guide to help you identify &amp; build the right technology roadmap. <strong><a href="http://go.roadmunk.com/10-technology-roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Technology%20Roadmap%20Ebook&amp;utm_source=TechnologyRoadmapChapter1">Download it here.</a></strong></h6>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch1-1.svg" alt="What is a technology roadmap, really?"></p>
<h2 id="somuchtechtoolittletime">So much tech, too little time</h2>
<p>The amount of technology that organizations use in day-to-day operations is a little bananas. Think of all the business apps and tools that make it possible for you and your co-workers to get shit done—customer relationship management, marketing automation, content management systems, accounting platforms, HR portals, video conferencing, and on and on.</p>
<p>The technology roadmap can be used to plan when/how new apps and tools will be implemented—as well as who will be involved in the process. It can also be used to outline when upgrades and improvements to an existing stack will take place and when parts of it will be moonlit.</p>
<p>For example, retiring a CRM system to onboard a new one is an arduous project that involves multiple stakeholders and a lot of finicky tasks like data migration. A technology roadmap can break this process into bite size pieces over a quarter. It sets expectations for all impacted team members, keeps everyone on track, and aligns everyone to the goal of pushing the new system live.</p>
<p>Charting IT initiatives helps organizations determine which apps and tools to prioritize based on their impact on achieving bigger short-term and long-term goals. Maybe the new CRM system will boost the productivity of the sales team by “X” amount and therefore help them close “Y” amount of deals to get annual recurring revenue to “Z” amount. So, maybe onboarding the marketing team’s new analytics platform gets pushed out to next quarter because its impact on the organization’s bigger goal of getting that $$$ is slightly less significant.</p>
<p>Ultimately, the IT systems roadmap exists to align the organization on the when and why of what’s happening to IT. This type of roadmap is most effective when managed by the administrators of tech—be it a dedicated IT team or an operations manager. However, just as important is the input from each stakeholder team to enable the keepers of IT to clearly understand the needs and objectives that each function requires from their technology stack.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-ch1-2-1.svg" alt="What is a technology roadmap, really?"></p>
<h2 id="whatanitsystemsroadmaplookslike">What an IT systems roadmap looks like</h2>
<p>There are a couple ways to approach this type of roadmap. The swimlane view of our technology roadmap template is particularly helpful for getting a high-level understanding of what’s going on in IT for each department. Marketing will be able to understand, at a glance, the status of the latest tech to be added or upgraded.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-1-1-1.svg" alt="What is a technology roadmap, really?"></p>
<p>For teams that want to get really granular with the administration of their IT system, I recommend the timeline view.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/03/Tech-1-2-1.svg" alt="What is a technology roadmap, really?"></p>
<p>The timeline view makes it easy to visualize the timing and resourcing for the technology resources in your pipeline.</p>
<p>You can pivot your roadmap to tell a very detailed story of how IT administration will roll out over a specific time period. For example, you can showcase which employee is spearheading each initiative and when it will be completed, like in the example above.</p>
<p>The timeline view also lets you add milestones to your roadmap. Milestones are the key achievements of your IT administration strategy—like releasing upgrades. Milestones showcase progress and rally the team around deadline-oriented goals, keeping everyone on course.</p>
<p>So, give our technology roadmap a whirl to organize your IT systems administration and build a solid plan of action.</p>
<p><mark>Ready to build your own tech roadmap? <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=TechRoadmapChapter1">Check out our ready-to-use templates.</a></strong></mark></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[5 best practices for your agile product roadmap]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 4]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/5-best-practices-for-your-agile-product-roadmap/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a313ad5f9ac71000121ea27</guid><category><![CDATA[Agile]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Jillean]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2017 19:16:42 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/agile-ch4.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/agile-ch4.svg" alt="5 best practices for your agile product roadmap"><p>No matter how you choose to represent your agile product roadmap, there are certain standards you just gotta follow.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/Agile-ch4-1.svg" alt="5 best practices for your agile product roadmap"></p>
<h2 id="1treatanagileproductroadmapasastatementofintent">1. Treat an agile product roadmap as a statement of intent</h2>
<p>First thing’s first: <strong>approach your agile product roadmap as a statement of intent.</strong> (<strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/are-agile-product-roadmaps-counterintuitive/">We’ve covered this already</a></strong>.) Treat your agile product roadmap as a living document that can (and 100% will) change.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“From just a mechanic standpoint, making sure you have a roadmap that can actually be updated is really important,” says Ahsan Nanji, Director of Product Management at Electronic Arts. “I’ve seen PMs struggle with creating a plan that doesn’t build any flexibility into it. So you want to — with either the software or whatever process you’re using — be very adaptable to change.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you’re too hung up on dates or milestones, you restrict your product roadmap and ultimately set yourself up for failure. Give yourself breathing room, so that way you can sync your product roadmap nicely with the  flexibility and changes you’ll experience in an agile environment.</p>
<h6 id="downloadourebooktoseesomerealworldexamplesofagileproductroadmaps"><strong><a href="http://go.roadmunk.com/agile-roadmap-ebook?utm_campaign=Agile%20Roadmap%20Ebook&amp;utm_source=AgileRoadmapChapter4">Download our ebook</a></strong> to see some real-world examples of agile product roadmaps.</h6>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/Agile-ch4-2.svg" alt="5 best practices for your agile product roadmap"></p>
<h2 id="2determineiftimeisrightforyou">2. Determine if time is right for you</h2>
<p>When we asked Casey McKinnon, VP of Product at ecobee, about his agile product roadmap best practices, the very first thing he brought up was evaluating the role of time for your roadmap.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Well, first of all I would consider if time’s a factor,” he says. “If the idea is that you need to hit a specific date, you need to compare that to something where you can put your product out into the world and there are no consequences for when it’s launched.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Determine how time plays a role (if at all) in your day-to-day function. If it doesn’t play a role: awesome, your product roadmap won’t incorporate time.</p>
<p>Maybe a timeline is for you. Maybe you’re not that concerned with dates, so you want to employ fuzzy time buckets. Or maybe you have a million sprints you need to show on your roadmap. Whichever way you approach time, knowing whether it applies and its particular role in your environment will lead to a more effective agile roadmap.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/Agile-ch4-3.svg" alt="5 best practices for your agile product roadmap"></p>
<h2 id="3rememberwhosseeingyouragileproductroadmapandtailortothem">3. Remember who’s seeing your agile product roadmap and tailor to them</h2>
<p>Creating a product roadmap without an audience in mind is pretty useless. The whole point of a roadmap is to communicate and align with your stakeholders. One of the very first questions you should be asking is: who’s going to see this?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“You want to understand your audience first, because they want to see different things,” says Latif Nanji (our CEO here at Roadmunk). “If you’re building this agile roadmap for engineers you can get a lot more granular about information, whereas sales and marketing are more concerned about the ‘what’ and ‘when.’”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Knowing your audiences means knowing what expectations to set; you know who you’re catering to. Imagine a mystery novelist showing up to a romance novel convention, expecting to sell out. It’s not going to happen. Romance novel fanatics are looking for very specific things (i.e. scandalous cover art and tales of unrequited love) that a mystery novelist (most likely) won’t offer.</p>
<p>The same goes for your roadmap. If you’re expecting to get buy-in from C-level executives, but you’ve created an agile roadmap specifically for developers, don’t expect a very productive meeting.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“One of the worst things you can do is have everyone see the same roadmap,” says Latif.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you know each stakeholder has individual goals and concerns, you can’t show up to each meeting with the same exact plan. Offer something relevant to them. The result: expectations are managed and stakeholders can feel assured that their needs are being addressed.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/Agile-ch4-4.svg" alt="5 best practices for your agile product roadmap"></p>
<h2 id="4knowyourproductmarketlikereallyknowit">4. Know your product market. Like really know it.</h2>
<p>This seems obvious. Of course a PM should know their product market! But we’re talking really knowing what upcoming features users want, beforehand. In agile this will change — and quickly. But a strong market knowledge makes your product roadmap much more adaptable to inevitable changes.</p>
<p>Sarah Pyo, Product Manager at Expedia, puts it this way:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Understanding how your product works technically will help with prioritization, because you’ll know different levers to pull to drive your product. What new, futuristic features can we push out there and what is the demand?”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Recommending a user-centric method to collect market knowledge for your agile product roadmap, Rahul Kulkarni, Product Manager at Shopify, says:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Validate low-fidelity mockups with customers as often as possible. Get real feedback and parse out what’s relevant.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Chances are your market will be disrupted (many times), and as a result, so will your product roadmap. Keeping tabs on users’ wants and needs will prepare you to be just as agile; allowing you to update your roadmap swiftly to reflect any market shifts.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/Agile-ch4-5.svg" alt="5 best practices for your agile product roadmap"></p>
<h2 id="5checkinwithyouragileproductroadmapasateam">5. Check-in with your agile product roadmap (as a team)</h2>
<p>This should be the easiest guideline to remember because it’s a natural outcome of agile. Working in short cycles, you’re immersed in a constant feedback loop. You’re regularly forced to stop and ask yourself, “So what worked and didn’t work this last cycle?”</p>
<p>This introspective (and zen) behavior pushes you to check in with your roadmap often. Your document should always be up-to-date with your product strategy and if you’ve created (and you should have) a living document that can change, it’ll be easy to update to reflect recent changes.</p>
<p>Casey McKinnon agrees with this practice, but emphasizes incorporating the whole team:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“You should continue to revisit your roadmap with your whole team. Don’t let it be an artifact of product, but an artifact of the whole company. This way we all agree, we all bought in, and everyone’s really excited about the roadmap.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As a PM it’s your responsibility to ensure you’re sitting with your roadmap consistently, but also making sure you’re roping in your team. This way alignment is not only easier, but way more consistent.</p>
<p><mark>Once your plan is planned, use our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/agile-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=AgileRoadmapChapter4">agile roadmap template</a></strong> to hit the ground runnng.</mark></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A 5-step guide to agile product roadmap planning]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chapter 3]]></description><link>http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/a-5-step-guide-to-agile-product-roadmap-planning/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a31378bf9ac71000121ea25</guid><category><![CDATA[Agile]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Jillean]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2017 19:05:42 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/agile-ch3.svg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><blockquote>
<img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/agile-ch3.svg" alt="A 5-step guide to agile product roadmap planning"><p>Behind every effective agile product roadmap is a well-thought out plan. As true (and cheesy) as that statement is, it’s also a bit of a weird statement since a product roadmap is meant to be a (flexible and transparent) plan that aligns stakeholders across your organization.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So what we’re saying is you need to plan for your plan. A truly effective agile product roadmap (i.e. plan) is one that people will have confidence executing. And without proper thought put into that plan, you’ll be hard-pressed to find individuals willing to stake their time, money and energy on your product roadmap.</p>
<p>You might be asking: what’s the point in planning for an agile product roadmap when it will ultimately change? You’re not wrong — your agile product roadmap should be a statement of intent that you update frequently. But you should be updating your product roadmap to reflect changes brought on by your agile environment, organization and market — NOT because you poorly planned your roadmap. <strong>Prep work for your agile product roadmap can prevent unnecessary changes and even complete overhauls of your plan.</strong></p>
<p>For all the PMs we’ve spoken to, roadmap planning is a key step in their workflow — particularly in agile. So before you open up your roadmapping tool (or app or whiteboard or spreadsheet... <em>shudder</em>) to create your agile roadmap, here are five steps you should take for effective agile product roadmap planning.</p>
<h6 id="realworldwaystobuildagileroadmapsgetthehelpfulnonboringguidedownloadithere">Real-world ways to build agile roadmaps. Get the helpful, non-boring guide. <strong><a href="http://go.roadmunk.com/agile-roadmap-ebook?utm_campaign=Agile%20Roadmap%20Ebook&amp;utm_source=AgileRoadmapChapter3">Download it here.</a></strong></h6>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/Agile-ch3-1.svg" alt="A 5-step guide to agile product roadmap planning"></p>
<h2 id="step1setyourgoals">Step 1: Set your goals</h2>
<p>Your agile roadmap <strong>communicates with and aligns stakeholders</strong>, but what are you addressing? Even if you have a list of impressive features to release, the big picture must be considered. Your objective might be achieving product-market fit, or launching “sticky” features. Whatever the goal, your roadmap should convey the plan for achieving your high-level strategy.</p>
<p>Without established objectives, expect stakeholders to walk away from your roadmap with different priorities (the TOTAL opposite of what you want). <strong>Your roadmap should always tie directly back to your primary goals</strong> so that stakeholders are clear about your product strategy.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Ask yourself if the document speaks to your company and product vision</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Bonus question</strong>: If you want to get reallyyy specific, also ask yourself what key performance indicators you want to focus on. Planning your main KPIs will allow you to create a roadmap that explains how you’ll hit those targets.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/Agile-ch3-2.svg" alt="A 5-step guide to agile product roadmap planning"></p>
<h2 id="step2evaluateyourresources">Step 2: Evaluate your resources</h2>
<p>If you have ten developers, but two are on vacation and one is shared by marketing, how much can you ship in your next sprint? The answer: probably not as much as you could with a fully available team of ten developers. Planning for your agile roadmap should address your <strong>available resources and their constraints</strong>.</p>
<p>Another thing to plan against: the speed at which resources operate. You’re going to get pushback on how fast (or slow) your team is delivering on your plan—even in agile. Plan a cycle length that works best for your team — especially if you’re representing time on your roadmap.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Determining your team’s speed will let you develop a plan grounded in reality.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/Agile-ch3-3.svg" alt="A 5-step guide to agile product roadmap planning"></p>
<h2 id="step3checkinwithyourusers">Step 3: Check-in with your users</h2>
<p>It boggles our minds when organizations build roadmaps based solely on quantitative market data. User needs go much deeper than statistical research. <strong>Speaking first-hand to customers during your planning</strong> provides insights into disregarded investments. Before committing to anything on your roadmap, it makes sense to understand if your users, you know, actually want these things.</p>
<p>Additionally, user research makes a really, really strong case when getting buy-in.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>User research shows stakeholders that your agile roadmap isn’t just a random, aimless plan you pulled out of thin air, but one developed from <strong>authentic user needs</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s pretty hard to refute real user needs.</p>
<p><mark>No matter your agile style, check out our free <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/agile-roadmap?utm_campaign=Roadmapping%20Field%20Guide&amp;utm_source=AgileRoadmapChapter3">agile roadmap template</a></strong> and make it your own.</mark></p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/Agile-ch3-4.svg" alt="A 5-step guide to agile product roadmap planning"></p>
<h2 id="step4determineyourbuildingblocks">Step 4: Determine your building blocks</h2>
<p>Next up: establish your <strong>major themes</strong>, and the <strong>features</strong> that fall under each of them. Then break it down into <strong>epic</strong>s and <strong>user stories</strong>. From there develop high-confidence estimates on your features, epics and stories, and identify any <strong>dependencies</strong> that could hold you back.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Hack away until you have all the building blocks you need before assembling your roadmap.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If this seems like a lot of work before creating an agile roadmap, we say: planning for these elements will prepare you to address (and defend) your choices when changes do pop up. And if changes are needed, you can speak to impacts and trade-offs that must be made.</p>
<p><img src="http://roadmunk.com/roadmapping/content/images/2018/02/Agile-ch3-5.svg" alt="A 5-step guide to agile product roadmap planning"></p>
<h2 id="step5holdplanningsessions">Step 5: Hold planning sessions</h2>
<p>This step isn’t so much isolated, but more ongoing and works in conjunction with the previous steps. <strong>Make agile roadmap planning a team effort</strong> by putting your whole product team in one room. This is your opportunity to really understand together your use cases, discovery work and objectives before making any roadmap investments.</p>
<p>Think of it as a way to get buy-in for the plan for your plan (again—strange, we know).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Early buy-in during your planning stage will be beneficial when getting official buy-in and public affirmations from your stakeholders.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Want to see real-world examples of well thought-out agile product roadmaps? Check out our ebook (and also get a handy checklist to add structure to your planning process).</p>
<h6 id="wevegotevenmoreagilecontentforyougettherealworldguidetoagileroadmapshere">We've got even more agile content for you. <strong><a href="http://go.roadmunk.com/agile-roadmap-ebook?utm_campaign=Agile%20Roadmap%20Ebook&amp;utm_source=AgileRoadmapChapter3">Get the real-world guide to agile roadmaps here.</a></strong></h6>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>