<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Jillean Kearney &#8211; Roadmunk Blog</title>
	<atom:link href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/author/jillean/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog</link>
	<description>Product Management and Product Roadmaps</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 19:44:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.7.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/favicon.png</url>
	<title>Jillean Kearney &#8211; Roadmunk Blog</title>
	<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Product to Product: Square&#8217;s Aman Manik on product management culture</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/aman-manik/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2017 14:16:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jillean Kearney]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3723</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Aman Manik, Product Manager at Square, noticed his product team all had very different definitions of product management. So he created a PM culture guide for his product team.  </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/aman-manik/">Product to Product: Square&#8217;s Aman Manik on product management culture</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Welcome to the latest episode of <a href="https://roadmunk.com/product-to-product-podcast" target="_blank"><strong>Product to Product</strong></a>, a podcast for / by product people.</span></p>
<p>Listen to the episode below:</p>
<p><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/ca/podcast/product-to-product/id1293415837?mt=2" target="_blank"><img class="size-full wp-image-4037 alignnone" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/link-apple.png" alt="" width="289" height="67" /></a><a href="https://play.google.com/music/listen?u=0#/ps/Is7ibqzwhkqszuin6l2li7f3in4" target="_blank"><img class="wp-image-4036 size-full alignnone" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/link-google.png" alt="" width="289" height="67" /></a></p>
<p><iframe style="border: none;" src="//html5-player.libsyn.com/embed/episode/id/5974537/height/90/theme/custom/autoplay/no/autonext/no/thumbnail/yes/preload/no/no_addthis/no/direction/backward/render-playlist/no/custom-color/32c7c0/" width="100%" height="90" scrolling="no" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This episode features <strong><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/amanik" target="_blank">Aman Manik</a></strong>, a product manager at <strong><a href="https://squareup.com/" target="_blank">Square</a></strong>. He’s been a part of Square’s product team since 2015 when Fastbite, the company he co-founded, was acquired. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As Aman was getting ramped up at Square, he noticed that the PMs he was working with all came from different backgrounds and had varying perspectives on what the role of a PM should be within an organization. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">So, he decided to get them all together to come up with a singular definition of what it means to be part of<em> their</em> product team. And they created what Aman calls a <strong>PM culture guide</strong>. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Aman spoke to <strong><a href="https://linkedin.com/in/nick-gray-51ab1267" target="_blank">Nick</a></strong>, our own product manager at Roadmunk, about the guide (the process of making it, how it’s used, the feedback it received, and how other teams can benefit from the same exercise.)</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The episode can be listened to above, and we’ve also included a transcript below. You can subscribe to Product to Product on iTunes (</span><strong><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/podcast/product-to-product/id1293415837?mt=2https://itunes.apple.com/ca/podcast/product-to-product/id1293415837?mt=2">here</a></strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">) and Google Play (</span><strong><a href="https://play.google.com/music/listen?u=0#/ps/Is7ibqzwhkqszuin6l2li7f3in4">here</a></strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">), or get the latest episodes delivered to your inbox by subscribing </span><strong><a href="https://hubs.ly/H09g5Yv0" target="_blank">here</a></strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3561" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/pp-icon-1.png" alt="" width="2273" height="150" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/pp-icon-1.png 2273w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/pp-icon-1-300x20.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/pp-icon-1-768x51.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/pp-icon-1-1024x68.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2273px) 100vw, 2273px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Nick: Thank you so much, Aman, for joining us today. I&#8217;m really excited to have you on Product to Product. Before we get into this really cool idea around creating this product management culture guide, maybe you can describe to us what you define as product management culture.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> I think culture is really interesting. The way I got introduced to a product management culture was at Box—where I felt like everybody I worked with was a friend. We were able to share the same values. We had the same passions. We were really about driving the business forward. There wasn&#8217;t a lot of hidden agendas or ulterior motives or politics that can be seen when you get to bigger companies.</p>
<p>But really, I think a great culture is one where—especially for product managers—you&#8217;re really sharing best practices with each other, you&#8217;re connecting around making each other better, and you&#8217;re ebbing and flowing around a common set of principles.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"I don’t think there’s a recipe to create a PM culture."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22I%20don%E2%80%99t%20think%20there%E2%80%99s%20a%20recipe%20to%20create%20a%20PM%20culture.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3723' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>At Square, we all came from different backgrounds. We were product managers but we were all working on our own products. We were doing great in our own right, but there was an opportunity for us to connect a little bit deeper beyond being coworkers and friends, and really share what our expectations of product managers were.</p>
<p>Even you Nick, you came from a different background, so your idea of a product manager and how it fits at Roadmunk is probably very different than how a product manager fits in for me. So a really good culture is one where you can join on a common set of values and really build from there. I don’t think there’s a recipe to create a PM culture.</p>
<p><strong>Nick: Yeah, I agree with you on so many levels. A great foundation when you&#8217;re in any organization, is trying to start out with camaraderie and friendship—getting to know people on a more personal level and seeing how those attractions lead into a more professional culture and environment. But as we go deeper into product management culture, how do you feel that lives independently from the company culture?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> So, what I like about Square—and I think what keeps me there—is our passion for the small business owner. I feel like everything we do is about growing their business. And that’s macro and everyone has a common language and understanding. But when you get into product management, it’s separate because that’s more of a functional role. That’s getting one level deeper, about how do we actually get our products better, so we can serve our customers better.</p>
<p>Other roles like sales and customer support are there to help customers get started and solve issues—and it’s pretty standard across different companies. But when you talk about a product manager, in my experience, PMs all have their own general understanding of what a product manager does. It&#8217;s not a bad thing. It just means that everybody has their own shape and view of what a product manager does. And this is probably the reason why there are unlimited resources online for what a product manager does and how they can be successful, because there are very different ways a product manager can fit into a company.</p>
<p>The way I think about product management culture for us at Square, is that it&#8217;s really a union for us to share best practices and codify what a product manager is, in terms of their roles and responsibilities and day-to-day. Whereas, the culture for Square is more macro.</p>
<p><strong>Nick: I can definitely see the similarities when I interact with other PMs myself. Everyone does have a unique definition within their own organization. And it is a very fluid understanding of what a PM does. Was there a certain incident that sparked this interest to create a PM culture guide? Or were you inspired by another team that was doing something similar?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> So when I joined Square—I probably do this naturally as a human being—I tried to find places of familiarity. You know when you go into a building that’s dark, you’re always looking for the light switch; it’s something familiar. I came in and wondered are there other PMs at the company. How are their roles compared to mine?</p>
<p>What was really awesome at Square, we already had this product management ‘all hands,’ where all PMs would get together every month to talk about interesting topics and customer journeys. And I kept talking to PMs at the company, grabbing coffees, and having one-on-ones about the company. I found out that other PMs had very different understandings or views of how their role fits into the company.</p>
<p>The instance that was interesting to me was when I was getting ramped up at Square and I started getting my stride with one of my engineering managers. We were working really well. People were like, &#8220;Wow, you guys are really moving fast. You guys are beating milestones. What has been working really well for you?&#8221; And it’s funny, I took some advice from an older friend who’s happily married, about setting expectations in your relationship. So I thought to myself, fundamentally, the relationship cascades across everything, in my work as well.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"I came in and wondered are there other PMs at the company. How are their roles compared to mine?"</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22I%20came%20in%20and%20wondered%20are%20there%20other%20PMs%20at%20the%20company.%20How%20are%20their%20roles%20compared%20to%20mine%3F%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3723' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>So one thing I did differently with my engineering manager was go for a coffee when we first met and started working on a brand new project together. I asked him, “Let’s take the product management title out of the way. Let’s take the engineering manager title out of the way. We’re both partners here in trying to meet these goals. What are your expectations of me? Based on what we know about the project, where can I really excel and make our team’s lives easier, and make your life easier?&#8221; And he started doing the same thing back to me.</p>
<p>That exchange was really awesome. He pointed out that he really wanted me to shield the team from scope creep. He really wanted me to be the domain expert in what our customers wanted and help us prioritize. But even getting down to this is how we want to work together, this is how often we want to meet and this is the transparency we want to have when we speak.</p>
<p>So I shared that with a fellow PM and she thought that would be a really fun exercise for us all to do; to share our expectations of each other and our team. Because sometimes you feel like you&#8217;re doing exactly what a PM is supposed to do, but sometimes, I feel like I’m doing a lot of other things outside of that. It moves around; you wear multiple hats. So honestly, we made this process up and we pitched it to our head of product, and he said, “That sounds like a great idea!” So the other PM and I brainstormed how to do it and we ended up putting together a guide that we disseminated to the rest of the team to say this is what we think we should be doing. Here are some areas where we could improve.</p>
<p><strong>Nick: So before you even introduced this idea to your head of product, what were the steps you took to bring this guide to life?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> In engineering, you have paired programming. So I asked a fellow colleague, &#8220;Hey, do you wanna pair on this?&#8221; We would then just sit down and brainstorm the best way to structure this.</p>
<p>We started to throw ideas around and so I thought, why don’t we get everyone to write down their ideas on Post-It notes. We didn’t want to bias anybody in the room; we wanted everyone to write down freely what they thought about their role. What are some important themes? Aspects of their role that they thought we should be doing or we shouldn&#8217;t be doing.</p>
<p>We put all these notes on a whiteboard. And then we started adding some structure to all these ideas. Once we got everything structured, we asked, &#8220;How do we turn this into something that’s readable and approachable? Our north star we can point to.&#8221;</p>
<p>I got together with my colleagues to share it with the head of product. He suggested the best thing we should do is rate ourselves on how well we’re doing in each of these categories. And that could be used to find areas of improvement for us as individuals and as a team. We coalesced our original idea with the head of product’s idea and began using the guide as an exercise in improvement.</p>
<p><strong>Nick: When you were going through that sticky note phase of gathering feedback to build your culture guide was it limited to only product managers? Or was that open to other departments or members of the executive team?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> We made an explicit choice not to involve anybody else. And I think that was good idea, now looking back at the feedback we got. I think it was a fun exercise for us a group to do together, because everything we’ve done as PMs is always involving other parties. We’re always involving stakeholders in our meetings and thinking about the customers. So it was the first time where we wanted just PMs to figure things out internally. We also weren’t sure what was going to come out of this process. So we kept it to just us.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"How do we turn this into something readable &amp; approachable? Our north star we can point to."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22How%20do%20we%20turn%20this%20into%20something%20readable%20%26%20approachable%3F%20Our%20north%20star%20we%20can%20point%20to.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3723' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>We actually started extending our weekly product meeting by an hour to actually go through this exercise and add more Post-Its to the whiteboard. The intention was to eventually share this as an editable Google Doc to everyone else in the company. But we at least got the foundation out there, and then let the document evolve.</p>
<p><strong>Nick: When you did share this with the wider company, what kind of feedback did you get from these other departments?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> The thing that people loved the most was the empathy and insights aspect of the guide. One of the things that we all talked about was having better domain knowledge of our stakeholders, the customers, the customers’ “jobs to be done.” We thought, &#8220;Are we doing a good thing of gathering those &#8216;jobs&#8217; from our customers?&#8221; All of us felt we could always do more.</p>
<p>So when we put that as a big area in the guide of where we could improve—gather more empathy and insights from our customers whether it be our diners, couriers and restaurants—other departments wanted to piggyback on customer visits with us and jump on support calls as well. That was awesome, because it showed that people were interested in this, but no one had broken the seal, so to speak, of actually putting a concerted effort of doing it. Some of us already did that implicitly anyways, it was just now that we put it into a doc and formalized it.</p>
<p><strong>Nick: Let&#8217;s say that you had gone a different route during the sticky note phase and gathered outside feedback earlier. Do you feel like that would have had a negative effect on the PM guide?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> No, I think what that we could have created something together, but it would have been a lot more feedback for us to sift through. I think the exercise would have taken a lot longer. Imagine if we had added 10, 20 or 30 more people! I think it would have taken more of a village to organize and go through all the feedback.</p>
<p>It was really impactful to stay small and test it out because it&#8217;s a brand new process. Just like product management you don&#8217;t want to just say, &#8220;Alright here&#8217;s what we&#8217;re gonna do.&#8221; And do whatever you want. You start small. It&#8217;s one of our cornerstone values at Square, as well.</p>
<p>And starting small was great because I think we can revisit this again next year, because the role evolves over time, especially as we mature and grow as a company. Maybe next time we could even invite somebody from design over. Maybe we could invite one of our representatives from marketing—and not make it super large—but add a few more flavors. Or maybe even have an independent discussion with the marketing team and conduct it for them in relation to product development.</p>
<p><strong>Nick: Did you notice that even after you had released this culture guide that it was received well? Was there any friction? Did you have to address anything immediately or maybe you completely missed something?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> It’s funny, I was hoping for some bad reception just because naturally everybody&#8217;s like, &#8220;Whoa, you guys created this yourselves. Did you put in my input?&#8221; But actually everybody was very supportive of it. I think it was a surprising delight. No one knew we were doing this. At one of our company “all hands,” one of our engineering managers said, &#8220;I&#8217;m very impressed and excited with our product management team. I feel like our team has a lot more structure now. I have a better understanding of where they&#8217;re coming from and what they want to do.”</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"You want to make sure that you control your time, not let your time control you."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22You%20want%20to%20make%20sure%20that%20you%20control%20your%20time%2C%20not%20let%20your%20time%20control%20you.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3723' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>I think everything was well received. I think people are anxious to see the progress. One thing that we&#8217;re going to do at the end of the year, or quarter, is we&#8217;re going to grade ourselves on how we did on our OKR&#8217;s and use that as a feedback loop to the guide. So that we can ask, “How was this guide helpful?” “Did it miss anything that we should be improving as a team?” “Are there other expectations we can include?” I’m really excited about that exercise coming up.</p>
<p><strong>Nick: And has this guide been able to help onboard new product hires at Square?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> Absolutely! It has. We just hired two more designers and we hired a bunch more engineers—and it&#8217;s great. When we hire someone new, as part of their onboarding each person meets everybody on the product floor, every engineer, design. I used to just talk about what we do on product, sort of high level, based on my understanding and experience. But it&#8217;s so great that we put this guide together, because I actually have a structure I can go down.</p>
<p>Here’s how we want to drive the business forward. Here’s an example of how we did that, how we’re doing that and how we’re continuing to do that. Here&#8217;s how we do empathy and insights each month, and this is how we conduct that. It also lets me ask, whether it’s a designer or engineer, what are some of your expectations before I share what we do as PMs.</p>
<p><strong>Nick: As I&#8217;ve gone into the product management community and spoken to other PMs, I&#8217;ve noticed there is one similarity that&#8217;s been flagged by people—and it’s that they feel the PM culture in many organizations is defined as the “shit umbrella” of the organization. I want to know your thoughts on that definition of a PM.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> So I think this kind of applies generally for a lot of work, and especially for me. One thing that was kind of interesting was when looking back at my time as Fastbite as a startup, and then even looking back on my time at Square, I noticed the times I was most successful was when I was the most proactive. I think that definition comes in when everyday is reactive—like all the time, because everybody is just pulling you in different directions.</p>
<p>It is really tough and I think there&#8217;s no real strong way to give you a general answer here that can apply to anyone, but what I can say is take a look at all the shit that&#8217;s coming in onto your umbrella and see if you can identify some themes. I know it sucks because maybe you&#8217;re really tired and you’ve spent a lot of time. But what I found when you don&#8217;t put any time to plan a structure, the chaos ends up just building and forming. It kind of takes a mind of it&#8217;s own, right?</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"It is really important to know what’s expected of you and what’s expected of others."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22It%20is%20really%20important%20to%20know%20what%E2%80%99s%20expected%20of%20you%20and%20what%E2%80%99s%20expected%20of%20others.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3723' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>You want to make sure that you control your time, not let your time control you. I think it’s a feeling; it’s a symptom; it’s an emotion that we’re all going to have. I think a big part of this is taking a look at what that shit is and trying to really organize it a little bit. Let me get more context on where this stuff is coming from. Just the way you speak to your customers, you start talking to your stakeholders and your colleagues, and ask them in the same way, “Tell me more about the job I’m serving for you and where do I fall short?”</p>
<p><strong>Nick: Love it dude, it’s time to move away from the shit umbrella. How would you help facilitate other organizations to take the same steps that you did to implement this PM culture?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> I think what I would first do is create a guide for other teams of here’s how you conduct your own PM culture. And what I would do is sit down with the team, help facilitate and make sure they’re doing the right thing. Because I think it’s really easy to have a discussion and not put stuff on paper and not grade yourself. (It’s an awkward thing to do sometimes.)</p>
<p>So I would go in and create a step-by-step guide. Definitely, get buy-in that the team wants to do this. Because if they don’t want to, it’s going to be hard to get anything done. Once the buy-in is there, set up a time. Maybe it’s in the office, maybe it’s done outside the office.</p>
<p><strong>Nick: Could you sum up why PMs in other organizations should do this?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> It is really important to know what&#8217;s expected of you and what&#8217;s expected of others. And taking time on that with your team can help you build a culture and common fabric that you can grow from. Just as you may want to reflect on your year and what you’re doing the following year, it’s a great sort of PM reflection. I can&#8217;t see why this would not help improve any type of experience for a PM, their company or their team.</p>
<p><strong>Nick: Love it. I know that I&#8217;ll start looking into this myself and start getting the feedback loop going with our own PM culture here. So, I appreciate the learnings. Thank you so much for your time!</strong></p>
<p><strong>Aman:</strong> Yep. Thank you!</p>
<hr />
<p><em>Subscribe to Product to Product on iTunes (<a href="https://itunes.apple.com/podcast/product-to-product/id1293415837?mt=2https://itunes.apple.com/ca/podcast/product-to-product/id1293415837?mt=2" target="_blank"><strong>here</strong></a>) and Google Play (<a href="https://play.google.com/music/listen?u=0#/ps/Is7ibqzwhkqszuin6l2li7f3in4" target="_blank"><strong>here</strong></a>), or get the latest episodes delivered to your inbox by subscribing <strong><a href="https://hubs.ly/H09g5Yv0" target="_blank">here</a>.</strong></em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/aman-manik/">Product to Product: Square&#8217;s Aman Manik on product management culture</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Product to Product: Squarespace&#8217;s Inga Chen on machine learning</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/inga-chen/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 13:09:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jillean Kearney]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inga chen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[machine learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product strategy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product to product]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[squarespace]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3540</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Introducing Product to Product, a podcast for / by product people. Our first episode features Inga Chen, a Product Manager at Squarespace, on how to make better product decisions with machine learning.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/inga-chen/">Product to Product: Squarespace&#8217;s Inga Chen on machine learning</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Welcome to the very first episode of </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/product-to-product-podcast" target="_blank"><strong>Product to Product</strong></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Roadmunk’s brand new podcast! <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.2.1/72x72/1f389.png" alt="🎉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Listen to the first episode below:</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/ca/podcast/product-to-product/id1293415837?mt=2" target="_blank"><img class="size-full wp-image-4037 alignnone" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/link-apple.png" alt="" width="289" height="67" /></a><a href="https://play.google.com/music/listen?u=0#/ps/Is7ibqzwhkqszuin6l2li7f3in4" target="_blank"><img class="wp-image-4036 size-full alignnone" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/link-google.png" alt="" width="289" height="67" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><iframe style="border: none;" src="//html5-player.libsyn.com/embed/episode/id/5831312/height/90/width/1500/theme/custom/autonext/no/thumbnail/yes/autoplay/no/preload/no/no_addthis/no/direction/backward/render-playlist/no/custom-color/32c7c0/" width="1500" height="90" scrolling="no" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For context: As a company that builds roadmapping software for product people, we’re immersed in the product community. We’ve seen how helpful product people are when it comes to helping their peers. They’re open to sharing their own experiences of working in product (both the good and the bad) in very honest ways—and they’re very generous with advice. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The candid conversations that are happening in product communities online make for excellent podcast material. So, we decided to start one. </span><strong>Product to Product</strong><i> </i><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>will feature two product people talking about one product-specific topic—</strong>like applying machine learning to the right problems and building a healthy PM culture (and what &#8220;PM culture&#8221; is). </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">We have really cool episodes coming up with <strong>product managers, designers, marketers and engineers</strong>.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This episode features <strong><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ingachen/" target="_blank">Inga Chen</a></strong>, a product manager at <a href="https://www.squarespace.com/" target="_blank"><strong>Squarespace</strong></a>. Inga manages the team responsible for Squarespace’s analytics platform—which their clients rely on to get data-driven insights about their websites and e-commerce stores. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Machine learning</strong> is a passion of Inga’s—and she&#8217;s specifically interested in helping other product teams build machine learning models that solve real problems for end users. </span>Inga spoke to my colleague Eleni Deacon about how product teams can properly prepare for machine learning, gathering user feedback and what to do when a model fails.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The episode can be listened to above, and we’ve also included a transcript below. </span>You can subscribe to Product to Product on <strong>iTunes</strong> (<a href="https://itunes.apple.com/podcast/product-to-product/id1293415837?mt=2https://itunes.apple.com/ca/podcast/product-to-product/id1293415837?mt=2" target="_blank"><strong>here</strong></a>) and <strong>Google Play</strong> (<a href="https://play.google.com/music/listen?u=0#/ps/Is7ibqzwhkqszuin6l2li7f3in4" target="_blank"><strong>here</strong></a>), or <strong>get the latest episodes delivered to your inbox</strong> by subscribing <strong><a href="https://hubs.ly/H08Tzz50" target="_blank">here</a>.</strong></p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3561" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/pp-icon-1.png" alt="" width="2273" height="150" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/pp-icon-1.png 2273w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/pp-icon-1-300x20.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/pp-icon-1-768x51.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/pp-icon-1-1024x68.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2273px) 100vw, 2273px" /></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>Can you clarify the difference between AI, machine learning, and deep learning? </strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">AI is the umbrella over machine learning. AI, to me, is our hope for human intelligence exhibited by machines. T</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">here are multiple goals of AI, which are all facets of human intelligence. We can reason, accumulate knowledge, plan for things, manipulate objects, and communicate with each other with our language. Learning, of course, is a part of what makes us human.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Machine learning is the ability to learn without being explicitly programmed. The reason why machine learning has become so popular in recent years is that teaching a machine to learn—or building a machine that can learn on its own—can achieve all the goals of AI. It can learn how to reason, and understand our language, and perceive and move objects. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">You give a machine learning algorithm lots and lots of data and that algorithm learns the concepts around this data. It&#8217;s then able to make a determination or prediction about something in the world. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Deep learning is the newest field of machine learning, and it has really catapulted us into the renaissance that we&#8217;re in today. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">The “deep” in deep learning comes from multiple hidden layers of transformation in data. Examples of things that are enabled by deep learning are self-driving cars or the Google Translate app in which the camera on your phone can immediately translate text that it sees into a different language. </span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>You&#8217;ve talked about how there are two schools of thought in the PM world about machine learning. Can you define how you see PMs&#8217; views of machine learning?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> There&#8217;s the one camp that says, “I&#8217;m not ready for machine learning.” That&#8217;s what I hear very often from PMs—“Machine learning is really exciting, I see the potential for it to transform my problem area or my product, but we&#8217;re not ready.” </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">The other camp is, “I&#8217;m so excited about machine learning—I want to use it for every one of my problems.”</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni:</b><strong> What would you say to those PMs saying they&#8217;re not ready? Is it something that&#8217;s more accessible than people actually think it is?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Yes. I think you can say, “I don&#8217;t have the data for it yet,&#8221; but i</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">f you ever want to be ready then you should start thinking about the data that you&#8217;ll need and start collecting it now. It takes time to collect data and to make sure that it is formatted properly. When you do get that data, and you do have a machine learning engineer take a look at it—you might need to make further product changes to collect a different type of data. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Think about the relationship between the inputs and outputs of your data, and how predictive it should be. An example is the Gmail spam filter. If you can manually outline what makes an email have spam characteristics versus not—maybe a flag is the word &#8220;hacker&#8221; or that it was sent from Nigeria. Getting the intuition around your inputs and outputs is one thing</span> you can do before building a full machine learning team.</p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>I really like this idea that you have about assessing whether machine learning is the right solution to apply to a problem. How did you come to such a practical view of machine learning? </strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think it&#8217;s a combination of talking to machine learning engineers and asking them, &#8220;What do you think makes a good machine learning problem? What excites you about machine learning problems?&#8221; It&#8217;s also talking to other product managers, reading blog posts by companies that have used machine learning in their products and seeing why and how they arrived at that decision. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Then it&#8217;s just kind of trial and error, honestly. T</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">he heuristic I use is to determine whether a solution is going to be 10x better if massive amounts of data are utilized to make a prediction. It&#8217;s important to </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">consider the manual option. Can you get 80% of the way there with a non-machine learning solution? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The things that machine learning can do, like predicting stock prices or recommending products are things we can all do as humans. If you manually do that on a small scale for a few users—like recommending products for a few users after studying their purchase behavior—you can gauge if it&#8217;s actually helpful. T</span>his is before you&#8217;ve done any machine learning, maybe before you&#8217;ve collected data to see if it&#8217;s important and if it solves a real pain point. If it does, then great. Ask yourself again, will lots and lots of data make this prediction or recommendation even better? And if it does, then that&#8217;s probably a good machine learning problem and you can start collecting data for it.</p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>Are there any other questions that PMs should be asking themselves when they&#8217;re evaluating whether or not to apply machine learning to a particular problem?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">It&#8217;s really important to think about when the prediction of the model fails and what you&#8217;re going to do about that/how bad that&#8217;s going to be. Predicting stock prices or predicting health outcomes have very different ramifications if you fail—compared to recommending a product.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"It’s really important to think about when the prediction of the model fails."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22It%E2%80%99s%20really%20important%20to%20think%20about%20when%20the%20prediction%20of%20the%20model%20fails.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3540' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>I think even for problems that are less serious, user trust is really important. You&#8217;re going to be wrong. You&#8217;re making predictions with some level of probability. In the 30% of the time that you&#8217;re wrong, can you design an experience that doesn&#8217;t make your user say, &#8220;This recommendation doesn&#8217;t really know me well so I&#8217;m not going to use it or trust it again&#8221;?</p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>What would you recommend to avoid this problem—where users are put off by the machine so clearly being a machine that&#8217;s getting it wrong?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> It&#8217;s setting the right expectation and gathering user feedback. This depends on what the feature and the use case is—but it&#8217;s important to educate the user that your model will improve over time. The</span> more they invest into it, the better predictions or recommendations the product can provide.</p>
<p>An example here is Netflix or Spotify Discover Weekly. My friends are in two huge camps of &#8220;Spotify Discover Weekly knows me extremely, extremely well and they always suggest songs I&#8217;ve never heard of but that I love&#8221; and then the other camp is like, &#8220;Spotify Discover Weekly is completely off. I will never look at it again because it always gives me terrible songs.&#8221;</p>
<p>I think you can do a better job of setting the expectation by being upfront. Present the idea that, &#8220;These are the top five songs we think are strong matches for you, but then we added another 10 that are kind of shots in the dark.&#8221; The user will understand that a risk is being taken and it may not be a perfect match.</p>
<p><b></b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> It&#8217;s about transparency.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>How does machine learning come into play in your day-to-day work?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b>W<span style="font-weight: 400;">e&#8217;ve grown significantly over the past few years and we have millions of Squarespace websites on the platform, and our user base is as diverse as the internet is. We&#8217;re always finding out about new interesting Squarespace websites, but doing this in a manual way is not scalable. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We&#8217;re constantly thinking about website templates that best serve our users&#8217; needs. We have a few different verticals like food/drink and building an online store—but there are verticals we&#8217;re missing when we identify those manual categories. So we built a tool, called visual search, to </span>get to know our users more intimately and make sure that we&#8217;re not missing any pockets.</p>
<p>Visual search is an internal tool that our machine learning team built. It allows us to take one website and then look for websites that are similar to it. We can search for any term and get websites that match the search term. If you searched &#8220;safari&#8221; within our visual search engine, you would get a bunch of different customer websites that have either &#8220;safari&#8221; within the content of their site or pictures of, say, lions. The cool thing about visual search is that we didn&#8217;t have to tell the machine learning model, &#8220;Watch out for &#8216;safari&#8217; and make sure that pictures with lions make it into that search result.&#8221; That&#8217;s kind of the magic, and also the black box of machine learning. We&#8217;re able to do this on millions of websites and in a way that is infeasible for humans to do.</p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>How did you guys decide that this particular issue was a good one to tackle with machine learning?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">I like to think about three different types of problems that are great for machine learning. One is a decision with many inputs. One is a decision with many outputs. And another is making decisions at scale. Visual search at Squarespace is the last two.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We now have millions of websites. When we had ten thousand, we could have potentially hired a team to go through them all and tag each of them. But there are too many now and we have everyone in the fringes of the different verticals. We thought, &#8220;How can we do this at scale, in a way that we can continue to do as we grow even bigger?&#8221; This indicated that this is a great machine learning problem and that we could not do this the manual way.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>What goes into planning a machine learning initiative? Walk us through your process as you start to undertake something new.</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b>W<span style="font-weight: 400;">e start with learning about the problem and talking to users. Then we prioritize that problem and put it on the roadmap. We build the solution, launch it, and measure it. Rinse and repeat. That&#8217;s software product development at a very high level. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">During the learning stage, if it is a machine learning problem, that&#8217;s when we would classify it as such. It&#8217;s also at that stage where we ask, &#8220;Do we have the right data for this problem and do we need to make product changes in order to gather that data?&#8221; We also consider the non-machine learning alternative, the manual option and whether it can get us 80% of the way there. We make all of those determinations and then if we have to gather and prep data, we do that. The build phase happens once we&#8217;re confident that the data and its format is what we need.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">During the build stage, the machine learning team tests different algorithms and builds a bunch of different models. We then establish KPI&#8217;s that we&#8217;re going to evaluate those models on. I like to think of this stage as a controlled aiming test where it&#8217;s very clear which model is most predictive. </span></p>
<p>It&#8217;s also at this stage where you might have to throw away a few models, or all the models if you find out that none of them are predictive enough for your use case. I think accuracy in this stage will vary widely based on your use case. For example, product recommendations: you can probably get away with being less accurate there. But with something like predicting health outcomes, the consequences of being wrong are so much higher that you&#8217;re accuracy is going to have to be so much higher.</p>
<p>Once you launch a production model, I think it&#8217;s really important to get user feedback on the predictions the model makes. Then you can identify weaknesses in the model and you can start gathering more data in that specific area to feed back into the model to make it better.</p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>One thing that is not super known when people talk about machine learning in broad strokes is the sheer amount of data needed. Can you speak to that a little bit?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think that&#8217;s why it&#8217;s so important that if you say you&#8217;re not ready for machine learning yet, you should still start collecting the data that you think you&#8217;ll need. Again, it takes time to gather that much data and get it in the right format. But then also look at public data sources. It varies widely based on what industry you&#8217;re in and what problem you&#8217;re solving. If you&#8217;re in the legal or political realm, there&#8217;s so much data out there for use—even in the healthcare realm. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Data is really distributed and messy in healthcare systems and hospitals, but it&#8217;s still possible and companies are doing it.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>Where do user interview and user testing come into play when you&#8217;re building a machine learning model? </strong></p>
<p><b>Inga:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> I think it&#8217;s so important to do a lot of it up front. When I was talking about validating the manual solution with users, you do that up front before you&#8217;ve even done machine learning. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think it&#8217;s also important to get user feedback once you launch in order to monitor if your model has weaknesses. You&#8217;ll see a lot of products do this. For example: Slack Highlights, which predicts the messages it thinks will be important to you, always includes a little feedback mechanism that asks if it was helpful or not. </span>Google does that with a lot of their search results, too.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"Get user feedback once you launch in order to monitor if your model has weaknesses."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22Get%20user%20feedback%20once%20you%20launch%20in%20order%20to%20monitor%20if%20your%20model%20has%20weaknesses.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3540' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>There&#8217;s definitely a balance at the launch phase. You don&#8217;t want to wait too long to push a model live because you want the user feedback as soon as possible. And I&#8217;ve always been surprised about user feedback that I&#8217;ve gotten.</p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>So how do you know when it&#8217;s that sweet spot—when it&#8217;s time to launch?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">To the extent possible, you should dog food internally. You&#8217;ll know you&#8217;ve hit the jackpot if people internally use it, really engage with it and say, &#8220;Wow, this feels like magic.&#8221; </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br />
</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>It&#8217;s interesting that you use a word like &#8220;magic&#8221; to describe something so technical. </strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think to the end user, it should feel like magic. It has to feel like something they weren&#8217;t expecting you to know about them. But internally, I think it&#8217;s dangerous to think of it as magic. If we think about it as magic, then we expect that it can do anything. We should know the limitations. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think the only part that is a little bit magic, particularly in deep learning, is that you might not always know how a machine learning model arrived at a specific prediction. However, this makes it really hard when you&#8217;re trying to debug things and find model weaknesses. </span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>You spoke earlier about making sure that the output from the machine learning product reflects what the user actually wants. How do you think about any biases that the learning process could be surfacing? And how do you deal with that?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think a good rule of thumb is garbage in, garbage out. How representative your data set is when you train the model is how representative it&#8217;s going to be when it starts predicting. This is a case for having a diverse set of people working on machine learning projects and problems. You might not consider edge cases if you haven&#8217;t thought about it before, experienced it or seen it. You also see this in the user feedback, and that&#8217;s a case for shipping your model sooner under a beta flag. </span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"I think a good rule of thumb is garbage in, garbage out."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22I%20think%20a%20good%20rule%20of%20thumb%20is%20garbage%20in%2C%20garbage%20out.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3540' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sometimes your model will make really bad mistakes. Something that just happened with Facebook was that their ad algorithm allowed advertisers to target people based on hate terms that they put in their profile. The machine learning model presumably isn&#8217;t able to distinguish between a racist thing that someone put in their profile as &#8220;interested in&#8221;, or &#8220;works at.&#8221; The machine learning algorithm might allow you to target a bunch of people based on where they work but then someone trolls the &#8220;works at&#8221; part of their profile and says, &#8220;works at I hate Jews&#8221;, for example. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">The machine learning model doesn&#8217;t know this is a hate term but we know this as human. You have to be really careful in monitoring that, and I think Facebook just came out with an apology about that.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>Is there anything else PMs need to be aware of to make sure that sort of thing doesn&#8217;t happen?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think it just goes back to designing for when the model fails—and making sure that the data that you feed into the model is really representative.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>How do you guys make sure of that at Squarespace?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">We try to keep in mind that our userbase is extremely diverse and that we probably don&#8217;t know all of their different use cases and nuances. We try to not focus too heavily on the big verticals that we know and are familiar with. For example, we have falconry websites on Squarespace. And then we have Chance the Rapper and Pixar. We&#8217;re always thinking about how we can design solutions for the really small businesses and the large ones.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong><span class="s1">Do you have any examples of models failing? Has that happened to you, and how did your team correct in that instance?</span></strong></p>
<p><strong>Inga:</strong> I think the model with always fail. It&#8217;s just about the amount of user patience and user trust you have—and what format you&#8217;re delivering your predictor determination in. I think it&#8217;s very different if it&#8217;s a mobile push notification or an email versus a thing that a user can easily dismiss or ignore. With push notifications, you need to be a lot more careful. If you fail a bunch of times and you send a bunch of push notifications that are useless, the user will never use it again.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There&#8217;s also a learning curve. Sometimes you might feel like a feature is really important, and you want to take the risk of being too intrusive and being too loud to get feedback. If you are less intrusive or less loud, you might not get the right feedback. It might be ignored.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>What are some of your favorite machine learning applications that you use in the real world?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> I love the Google Translate app whenever I&#8217;m traveling because it can translate things in real-time—like menus at a restaurant or signs. I think that&#8217;s an awesome application of deep learning. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With Spotify Discovery Weekly, I&#8217;m of the camp that it is really predictive and great for me. I think they really try to make a cohesive playlist for you. It&#8217;s a great example of all of the additional product decisions that they made on top of the machine learning algorithm. The fact that Discovery Weekly updates every Monday was an intentional decision. You have to save the songs that you get every week in order to keep. It seems obvious in retrospect. It makes sense to get a new feed every Monday to look forward to, but that&#8217;s not super obvious when you&#8217;re designing something like that.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>When you encounter a machine learning process in the wild, do you try to dissect it? What&#8217;s your reaction when you see something like that?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">I use a lot of different products and I seek out ones that I think use machine learning. It&#8217;s actually not super obvious all the time. Sometimes the company will publish blog posts about their models. I&#8217;ll also talk to my machine learning team and be like, &#8220;Spotify Discovery Weekly, how do you think they built that? What do you think the models they&#8217;re using are?&#8221; That&#8217;s how I continue to build intuition as a PM.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni:</b><strong> Let&#8217;s say there was a product team who was really overzealous with machine learning. What would be your words of advice to that team to kind of reign it in and self-correct?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Machine learning is quite expensive and time-consuming. So if you don&#8217;t need to use it, don&#8217;t. I think of machine learning as one tool of many that I could be using. You should apply it to the right problem. There&#8217;s a list of questions that I go through where I&#8217;m like, &#8220;Do we have the data? Is the solution going to be 10x better if you used massive amounts of data versus making a rules-based solution?&#8221; Asking yourself all those questions will probably weed out a lot of ideas.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>On the flip side, if there&#8217;s a product team who&#8217;s reticent and they haven&#8217;t yet dived into machine learning, what would you tell them?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you think machine learning could transform your product or your problem area (which I think it will in most industries), figure out what you can do today to get yourself ready for machine learning down the line—in six months, in one year. Do you have that data yourself? Are you collecting it? Is it in the right format?</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"Figure out what you can do today to get yourself ready for machine learning down the line."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22Figure%20out%20what%20you%20can%20do%20today%20to%20get%20yourself%20ready%20for%20machine%20learning%20down%20the%20line.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3540' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you ultimately determine machine learning isn&#8217;t going to transform your product area or product problem, then at least you considered it and you&#8217;re being intentional about it.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>What do you think is the most surprising thing you&#8217;ve learned about machine learning since you started working on it as a product manager?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> In some ways, machine learning is still super, super early. It is actually really hard to determine how a machine learning model got to a certain decision—and sometimes when you&#8217;re trying to get to model weaknesses, you&#8217;re not actually really sure how it got to that decision. It is a little bit of a black box.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>What makes you really excited about this technology?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">The fact that we&#8217;re now in a world where there&#8217;s so much data everywhere. The Internet of Things has given us so much data for physical objects that we can now harness all of it to help make our lives better and easier. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Machine learning is able to harvest and process a lot more data than we can as humans. We can use the power of machine learning to help us improve our lives and solve our problems so we can hopefully focus on even bigger problems that only we can solve. I think there&#8217;s all this talk about, &#8220;Will AI eventually overtake us and become our overlord?&#8221; I think we&#8217;re still far away from that.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>What is your reaction when someone says something like that? Is AI going to become our overlord?</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">It&#8217;s funny. When you dig deeper into the state of the art of machine learning, you&#8217;ll realize how early it is. W</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">e are very, very far away from a sentient AI that is able to perform all the complex human tasks that we do over our lifetime. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think a good example or heuristic of that is from Andrew Ng, one of the major thought leaders and contributors on machine learning. He says that tasks that take less than one second of human thought are great for machine learning. These tasks are not that complex. They&#8217;re a lot more complex than maybe rule-based solutions, but they&#8217;re not very complex yet. That&#8217;s kind of where we are so far.</span></p>
<p><b>Eleni: </b><strong>Inga, thanks so much for doing this chat. It was really awesome talking to you.</strong></p>
<p><b>Inga:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Definitely. I really enjoyed it.</span></p>
<hr />
<p><em>Subscribe to Product to Product on iTunes (<a href="https://itunes.apple.com/podcast/product-to-product/id1293415837?mt=2https://itunes.apple.com/ca/podcast/product-to-product/id1293415837?mt=2"><strong>here</strong></a>) and Google Play (<a href="https://play.google.com/music/listen?u=0#/ps/Is7ibqzwhkqszuin6l2li7f3in4"><strong>here</strong></a>), or get the latest episodes delivered to your inbox by subscribing <strong><a href="https://hubs.ly/H08Tzz50">here</a>.</strong></em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/inga-chen/">Product to Product: Squarespace&#8217;s Inga Chen on machine learning</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What is a technology roadmap, really?</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/what-is-a-technology-roadmap/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 15:29:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jillean Kearney]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IT systems]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IT systems roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmap templates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmapping process]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology roadmap templates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[templates]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3365</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Even with a loosey-goosey moniker, a technology roadmap helps teams make smarter decisions and plans for their technology stack.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/what-is-a-technology-roadmap/">What is a technology roadmap, really?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the most popular roadmaps in our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=whatisatechnologyroadmap" target="_blank">template library</a></strong> is the <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/technology-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=whatisatechnologyroadmap" target="_blank">technology roadmap</a></strong>. Now, ‘technology” is kind of a loosey-goosey moniker—but the ambiguity is a result of its broad application (and this broad application also happens to be why this roadmap is so popular).</p>
<p>A technology roadmap illustrates <strong>how an organization’s goals will be achieved through the development, deployment and use of software and/or hardware</strong>. The broadest—and most universal—application of this roadmap, however, is defining and documenting the administration of an organization’s internal IT system.</p>
<p>Since most organizations utilize a hefty collection of technologies, maintaining this stack is often complex and taxing on resources. An internal IT systems roadmap helps teams implement a clear plan of action and make smarter decisions about technology.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3370" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-divider_1.png" alt="What is a technology roadmap - Divider" width="1747" height="95" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-divider_1.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-divider_1-300x16.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-divider_1-768x42.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-divider_1-1024x56.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<h1>So much tech, too little time</h1>
<p>The amount of technology that organizations use in day-to-day operations is a little bananas. Think of all the business apps and tools that make it possible for you and your co-workers to get shit done—customer relationship management, marketing automation, content management systems, accounting platforms, HR portals, video conferencing, and on and on.</p>
<p>The technology roadmap can be used to <strong>plan when/how new apps and tools will be implemented—</strong>as well as who will be involved in the process. It can also be used to outline when upgrades and improvements to an existing stack will take place and when parts of it will be moonlit.</p>
<p>For example, retiring a CRM system to onboard a new one is an arduous project that involves multiple stakeholders and a lot of finicky tasks like data migration. A technology roadmap can break this process into bite size pieces over a quarter. It sets <strong>expectations for all impacted team members</strong>, <strong>keeps everyone on track</strong>, and <strong>aligns everyone to the goal</strong> of pushing the new system live.</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p>Charting IT initiatives helps organizations determine <strong>which apps and tools to prioritize based on their impact on achieving bigger short-term and long-term goals</strong>. Maybe the new CRM system will boost the productivity of the sales team by “X” amount and therefore help them close “Y” amount of deals to get annual recurring revenue to “Z” amount. So, maybe onboarding the marketing team’s new analytics platform gets pushed out to next quarter because its impact on the organization’s bigger goal of getting that $ is slightly less significant.</p>
<p>Ultimately, the IT systems roadmap exists to align the organization on the when and why of what’s happening to IT. <strong>This type of roadmap is most effective when managed by the administrators of tech</strong>—be it a dedicated IT team or an operations manager. However, just as <span style="font-weight: 400;">important is the <strong>input from each stakeholder team </strong>to enable the keepers of IT to clearly understand the needs and objectives that each function requires from their technology stack.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3371" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-divider_2.png" alt="What is a technology roadmap - Divider" width="1747" height="95" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-divider_2.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-divider_2-300x16.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-divider_2-768x42.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-divider_2-1024x56.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<h1>What an IT systems roadmap looks like</h1>
<p>There are a couple ways to approach this type of roadmap. The swimlane view of our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/technology-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=whatisatechnologyroadmap" target="_blank">technology roadmap template</a></strong> is particularly helpful for getting a <strong>high-level understanding of what’s going on in IT for each department</strong>. Marketing will be able to understand, at a glance, the status of the latest tech to be added or upgraded.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3368" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-swimlane.png" alt="What is a technology roadmap - Swimlane example" width="1748" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-swimlane.png 1748w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-swimlane-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-swimlane-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-swimlane-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1748px) 100vw, 1748px" /></p>
<p>For teams that want to get really granular with the administration of their IT system, I recommend the timeline view.</p>
<p>The timeline view makes it easy to <strong>visualize the timing and resourcing for the technology resources</strong> in your pipeline.</p>
<p>You can pivot your roadmap to tell a very detailed story of how IT administration will roll out over a specific time period. For example, you can showcase which employee is spearheading each initiative and when it will be completed, like in the example below.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3367 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-timeline.png" alt="What is a technology roadmap - Timeline example" width="1747" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-timeline.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-timeline-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-timeline-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/technology_roadmap-timeline-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<p>The timeline view also lets you add milestones to your roadmap. Milestones are they key achievements of your IT administration strategy—like releasing upgrades. <strong>Milestones showcase progress and rally the team around deadline-oriented goals</strong>, keeping everyone on course.</p>
<p>So, give our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/technology-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=whatisatechnologyroadmap" target="_blank">technology roadmap</a></strong> a whirl to organize your IT systems administration and build a solid plan of action. <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.2.1/72x72/1f47e.png" alt="👾" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/what-is-a-technology-roadmap/">What is a technology roadmap, really?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment &#038; communication</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/roadmap-templates/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 17:03:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jillean Kearney]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hr roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[innovation roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marketing roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product roadmaps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[project roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmap templates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmapping process]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmaps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[strategic roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[templates]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=3218</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Roadmapping isn’t solely for product teams. Here are seven roadmap templates for all kinds of teams to share strategy across their entire organization.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/roadmap-templates/">7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment &#038; communication</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Roadmapping isn’t an exercise reserved solely for product teams—or rather, it shouldn’t be. <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/what-is-a-product-roadmap/" target="_blank">Roadmaps are communication tools</a> and are perfect vehicles for teams of all kinds to <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/get-buy-in-for-your-product-roadmap-from-each-department/" target="_blank">share their priorities and goals with the rest of the organization</a>.</p>
<p>To help you out, we created <strong>seven templates</strong> that can be used across your organization to boost visibility into high-level business strategy and more tactical team-based goals.</p>
<h1>1. The product roadmap</h1>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3221 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-product_tl.png" alt="7 roadmap templates - Product roadmap timeline" width="1747" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-product_tl.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-product_tl-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-product_tl-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-product_tl-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Let’s start with the bread and butter of roadmaps: <strong>product</strong>. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For product-driven companies—be it B2B SaaS shops or consumer-facing apps—a product roadmap is essential to organizational alignment. A product roadmap illustrates <strong>high-level product strategy and demonstrates how a product will evolve over time</strong>. It includes upcoming features and the nitty gritty of product development—like technical considerations and resourcing.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A product roadmap is a powerful communication tool that product managers use to align different departments on one vision. <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-roadmaps-sales/" target="_blank">It empowers the sales team to lead informed product conversations with prospects</a>, the marketing team to plan campaigns that align with feature releases and HR to determine who to hire and when.</span></p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/product-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-product" target="_blank"><strong>product roadmap template</strong></a> was built knowing that <strong>there isn’t just one way to create a product roadmap</strong>. Some product teams love key dates, while others prefer an agile approach. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For deadline-sticklers, our template’s timeline view charts how your product will grow and evolve over time. You can organize your team’s tasks into pre-set buckets—including new features, infrastructure and stickiness. You can also highlight important events, like a feature release, with milestones.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3222 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-product_sw.png" alt="7 roadmap templates - Product roadmap swimlane" width="1747" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-product_sw.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-product_sw-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-product_sw-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-product_sw-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The swimlane view (above) sorts your tasks according to progress, not time.</span></p>
<p><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/product-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-product" target="_blank"><b>Give our product roadmap template a whirl. </b></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">P.S.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> For organizations with multiple product lines, our </span><b>portfolio roadmap template</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> makes it possible to illustrate and communicate a high-level overview of how each different products will evolve and how they relate to each other. </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/portfolio-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-product" target="_blank"><b>Try the portfolio roadmap template.</b></a></p>
<h1>2. The strategic roadmap</h1>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3223 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-strategic_tl.png" alt="7 roadmap templates - Strategic roadmap timeline" width="1748" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-strategic_tl.png 1748w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-strategic_tl-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-strategic_tl-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-strategic_tl-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1748px) 100vw, 1748px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A strategic roadmap is used to <strong>communicate an organization’s vision and mission</strong>, illustrating the key steps required to bring these two things to fruition. This roadmap is accessible to every employee, and it helps ensure that every department is ideating and working on initiatives that serve the organization&#8217;s bigger strategic aims.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This particular roadmap is created and championed by <strong>senior-level stakeholders</strong>. Business objectives are generally mapped out across the long-term. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Unlike a product roadmap that outlines what plans need to be executed in the short-term, <strong>a strategic roadmap is all about the long game</strong>. An organization’s vision and mission are often hefty, audacious goals that can be broken down into smaller, bite-size initiatives across many years.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/strategic-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-strategic" target="_blank"><strong>strategic roadmap template</strong></a> includes a timeline view. Use this view to track your key strategic initiatives and milestones over upcoming months, quarters and years.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3224 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-strategic_sw.png" alt="7 roadmap templates - Strategic roadmap swimlane" width="1748" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-strategic_sw.png 1748w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-strategic_sw-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-strategic_sw-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-strategic_sw-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1748px) 100vw, 1748px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Alternately, if you wish to be less strict with dates, our swimlane view visualizes your strategic initiatives based on progress.</span></p>
<p><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/strategic-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-strategic" target="_blank"><b>Lay out your vision and mission-critical business objectives with our strategic roadmaps.</b></a></p>
<h1>3. The innovation roadmap</h1>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3225 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-innovation_tl.png" alt="7 roadmap examples - Innovation roadmap timeline" width="1747" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-innovation_tl.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-innovation_tl-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-innovation_tl-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-innovation_tl-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">An innovation roadmap is a great companion to the strategic roadmap. A roadmap can and should be used to <strong>map new areas for growth opportunities, testing new ideas, tracking competitors and keeping up with advancing technologies</strong>. Organizations only remain competitive within their markets when they continuously look forward to discover new business models and ways to bolster their products with value-added improvements.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">An innovation roadmap is generally built and managed by an organization’s product managers and its executives to align all departments on strategic initiatives. They help companies <strong>achieve disruption and avoid getting disrupted themselves</strong>.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Track innovative achievements, like shipped features, against the work that your team is doing to keep sharp—like competitive benchmarking and breaking down barriers preventing new and exciting things from shipping.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/innovation-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-innovation" target="_blank"><strong>innovation roadmap template</strong></a> includes a timeline view to plan and track what your organization is doing in upcoming quarters and years, while also accessing and preparing for risks.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3226 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-innovation_sw.png" alt="7 roadmap templates - Innovation roadmap swimlane" width="1747" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-innovation_sw.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-innovation_sw-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-innovation_sw-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-innovation_sw-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The swimlane view provides a flexible way to keep track of your game-changing ideas by visualizing progress across key verticals like product and efficiency gains.</span></p>
<p><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/innovation-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-innovation" target="_blank"><b>Document your disruption tactics with our innovation roadmap template.</b></a></p>
<h1>4. The marketing roadmap</h1>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3227 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-marketing_tl.png" alt="7 roadmap templates - Marketing roadmap timeline" width="1747" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-marketing_tl.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-marketing_tl-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-marketing_tl-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-marketing_tl-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Marketing teams are generally project-oriented, and it’s very common for marketing teams to be slammed with multiple deliverables and initiatives at once. It gets hectic and unmanageable if not documented. Enter the marketing roadmap. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A marketing roadmap highlights <strong>key projects and priorities across all marketing channels and functions</strong>, creating clarity in the chaos. It charts all priorities and initiatives across all channels that marketing is responsible for—such as content, digital advertising and events. Creating an in-depth marketing roadmap surfaces a team’s highest priorities and keeps all of its marketers on track. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As an added bonus, a marketing roadmap also serves as a key communication tool for marketing teams to share their plans across their whole organization.</span></p>
<p>Our <b><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/marketing-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-marketing" target="_blank">marketing roadmap template</a> </b>comes with two types of views baked in. The timeline view allows you to meticulously plan when key initiatives will unfold across each of your marketing channels.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3228 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-marketing_sw.png" alt="7 roadmap templates - Marketing roadmap swimlane" width="1747" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-marketing_sw.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-marketing_sw-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-marketing_sw-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-marketing_sw-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our swimlane view groups your marketing initiatives into channels and manageable, easy-to-understand timeframes, like quarters.</span></p>
<p><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/marketing-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-marketing" target="_blank"><b>Organize your marketing team and initiatives with our marketing roadmap template.</b></a></p>
<h1>5. The HR roadmap</h1>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3229 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-hr_tl.png" alt="7 roadmap templates - HR roadmap timeline" width="1747" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-hr_tl.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-hr_tl-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-hr_tl-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-hr_tl-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">An HR roadmap is owned by an organization’s recruiters and human resources team to <strong>build and manage hiring plans and chart HR initiatives</strong>. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">It visualizes how each department within an organization will evolve and provides a snapshot of the roles being added and when. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This type of roadmap is extremely helpful for <strong>catching gaps in talent</strong>, <strong>ensuring that your organization is adequately resourced</strong> and that <strong>growth is properly balanced across departments</strong>. Each department leader can also use this roadmap to flag what resources they need and identify when their team will burst. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This roadmap also provides insight into what HR is working on to make employees happier in their day-to-day like changes to benefits plan, new referral bonuses, etc.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/hr-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-hr" target="_blank"><b>HR roadmap template</b></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> includes a timeline view so that your organization can see which new hires will be added to the team in upcoming months, quarters or years.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3230 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-hr_sw.png" alt="7 roadmap templates - HR roadmap swimlane" width="1748" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-hr_sw.png 1748w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-hr_sw-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-hr_sw-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-hr_sw-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1748px) 100vw, 1748px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Predicting exact hiring dates isn’t always possible given that some roles are more difficult to fill than others. Our swimlane view brings flexibility to your HR plan. </span></p>
<p><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/hr-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-hr" target="_blank"><b>Start mapping your hiring and HR initiatives with our HR roadmap template.</b></a></p>
<h1>6. The technology roadmap</h1>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3232 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-technology_tl.png" alt="7 roadmap templates - Technology roadmap timeline" width="1747" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-technology_tl.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-technology_tl-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-technology_tl-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-technology_tl-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A technology roadmap outlines <strong>how an organization plans to use technology to achieve their goals</strong>. It can be used in a couple of different ways. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Some organizations employ a technology roadmap to <strong>monitor technology considerations and resources</strong> within their product’s research and development strategy. Other organizations use a technology roadmap to <strong>visualize the administration of internal processes and systems</strong>, like information security audits and tracking employee hardware.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In both cases, a technology roadmap communicates complex initiatives within an easy-to-follow, actionable plan.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/technology-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-tech" target="_blank"><strong>technology roadmap template</strong></a>’s timeline view enables you to simply visualize timing for all technology initiatives coming up in your pipeline.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3231 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-technology_sw.png" alt="7 roadmap examples - Technology roadmap swimlane" width="1747" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-technology_sw.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-technology_sw-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-technology_sw-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-technology_sw-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our swimlane view provides a high-level snapshot of your technical priorities, and it tracks the progress of initiatives that are in progress, completed or within the backlog.</span></p>
<p><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/technology-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-tech" target="_blank"><b>Turn your complex technology initiatives into an easy-to-read roadmap with our template.</b></a></p>
<h1>7. The project roadmap</h1>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3235 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-project_tl.png" alt="7 roadmap templates - Project roadmap timeline" width="1747" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-project_tl.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-project_tl-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-project_tl-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-project_tl-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A project roadmap can be used by <strong>various departments across your organization</strong>—sales, customer success, admin, etc. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s a roadmap that can be applied to a wide range of projects that involve multiple stakeholders and moving parts. It provides <strong>a high-level overview of a project’s objectives, initiatives and deliverables</strong>. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A project roadmap is different from a project plan. While a project plan tracks each and every tactical detail, a project roadmap instead provides an overview of the most important components and milestones (i.e. the big picture). It aligns teams on key milestones and keeps everyone on the right path.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Use the timeline view of our <strong><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/project-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-project" target="_blank">project roadmap template</a></strong> to see key tasks and deadlines, and how your resources will be allocated over time.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-3234 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-project_sw.png" alt="7 roadmap templates - Project roadmap swimlane" width="1747" height="1079" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-project_sw.png 1747w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-project_sw-300x185.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-project_sw-768x474.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/roadmap_templates-project_sw-1024x632.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1747px) 100vw, 1747px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our swimlane view makes it easy to quickly visualize which tasks are complete, in progress or waiting in the backlog. </span></p>
<p><a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/project-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=roadmaptemplates-project" target="_blank"><b>Align your project team with our template.</b></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/roadmap-templates/">7 roadmap templates for creating organization-wide alignment &#038; communication</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
