<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Eleni Deacon &#8211; Roadmunk Blog</title>
	<atom:link href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/author/eleni/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog</link>
	<description>Product Management and Product Roadmaps</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 19:44:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.7.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/favicon.png</url>
	<title>Eleni Deacon &#8211; Roadmunk Blog</title>
	<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Product velocity is as much emotional as tactical</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/anna-marie-clifton/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2017 17:35:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[anna marie clifton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[influencer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product delivery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product velocity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yammer]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2694</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>It's not just on-paper processes impacting product velocity—interpersonal factors matter too. Anna Marie Clifton, Product Manager at Yammer, discusses a people-first approach to product delivery. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/anna-marie-clifton/">Product velocity is as much emotional as tactical</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here’s a word we didn’t expect to hear in a conversation about product velocity: “voodoo.” Although velocity can be considered a hard measure of time, the factors that </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">impact</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> velocity are a lot more mercurial. And during our chat with Yammer product manager </span><a href="https://twitter.com/tweetannamarie" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Anna Marie Clifton</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, she made it clear that product delivery is </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">not</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> just a function of a well-oiled dev team. “It’s easy to consider velocity a thing that your engineers do or don’t do,” she says, “but it’s a much, much, much bigger problem than that.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s been more than a year since Anna Marie joined Yammer, where she currently leads the growth initiative. She also hosts a podcast, </span><a href="http://www.clearlyproduct.com/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Clearly Product</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, with Quibb founder </span><a href="https://twitter.com/sandimac" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sandi MacPherson</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, and shares a mix of personal insights and meaty product reads on </span><a href="https://medium.com/@tweetannamarie" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">her Medium account</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet tw-align-center" data-lang="en">
<p dir="ltr" lang="en" style="text-align: left;">Prepping the next episode of <a href="https://twitter.com/ClearlyProduct">@ClearlyProduct</a>—a discussion on Andy Grove&#8217;s classic book: High Output Management. Super excited to share soon!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">— Anna Marie Clifton (@TweetAnnaMarie) <a href="https://twitter.com/TweetAnnaMarie/status/866465602352721920">May 22, 2017</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
<p><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/8-product-managers-share-trends-goals-2017/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">We recently chatted with Anna Marie about her goals for the coming year</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, and her answer was all about building a sense of </span><b>psychological safety</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> with her team. Her approach to velocity is an extension of that </span><b>people-first thinking</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: achieving and maintaining velocity is as much an emotional question as a tactical question. How you talk to colleagues, how you approach uncertainty, the energy you bring to the project—all of these factors can unlock or impede velocity as much as your on-paper processes.</span></p>
<p><strong><big>First of all, give us some context. What does velocity mean to you?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think about velocity in terms of: how long does it take from deciding that something is possible to getting it in front of customers? What is that total time? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There’s the velocity of idea iteration on that early side. How quickly do you validate or invalidate ideas with your research team? Or with your data analytics team, before you even bring an idea into the design phase? And then how quickly do you work with the designer to drive towards the goal and get to a point where you’re comfortable presenting your designs for review with the head of product?</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"The reason velocity is so important is because it’s literally survival for your company."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22The%20reason%20velocity%20is%20so%20important%20is%20because%20it%E2%80%99s%20literally%20survival%20for%20your%20company.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2694' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And then how quickly do you get your engineering team up to speed on what it is you’re trying to accomplish and why. How bought-in are they to those goals? Because that can derail your velocity later on.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And then there’s always the question of, what happens during project execution? What does it take to get that final mile out to customers? Are you doing messaging? Is there any change management? Did you think about that enough in advance? So really when I think about velocity I’m thinking about laying down the tracks in front of your team, and making sure you’ve thought of and uncovered a bunch of things before your team hits them.</span></p>
<p><strong><big>Jussst in case it’s not obvious: why is velocity so important to a product org?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s one of those heartbeats of the company. The question of how much you’re going to get in front of customers. How viable you’re going to be, how quickly you’re going to be able to respond to market trends. And you only have so many resources. Every single organization in the world feels like they’re understaffed and they don’t have enough resources to approach the problems they want to approach. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The reason velocity is so important is because it’s literally survival for your company. Velocity and direction are the two things that control whether or not you’ll be around in a few years. First of all, there’s the entire product direction: where are you going, your thesis, why is this the angle that you’re betting on? The combination of those two will determine if you survive. It determines if your competitor is going to outpace you or go in a better direction than you and acquire all the customers.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2766" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-confused_emojis.png" alt="Anna Marie Clifton - Confused emojis divider" width="384" height="128" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-confused_emojis.png 384w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-confused_emojis-300x100.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 384px) 100vw, 384px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>Can you tell me about a time you really struggled with velocity on a project? What happened?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Really early on when I first joined Yammer, I was working on a project that was, engineering-wise, not that expensive. It was a pretty small UI change. We were trying to promote a different type of behaviour and a different flow in the product. But the visual design of it was a really big piece. And I didn’t have a lot of clarity with my designers around what the goal was. And because of that, we floundered for a little while trying to land on a design that everyone was happy with.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We came to a head at one point, where I was like, “Okay, people are frustrated, I’m frustrated, designers are frustrated.” We peeled it back and uncovered that the reason why everything was stuck was that we had two competing goals that were kind of antithetical. And the designers didn’t know how to prioritize between those goals. We wanted users to both feel a sense of completion and we wanted to give them the next thing to do. And those are antithetical goals.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s really easy to look back and talk about that, but at the time I had no idea what was going on. I had no idea that the goals were unclear. I didn’t even really internalize that the goals were antithetical. It took a serious moment of, “Oh fuck, this is about to go real south.” And then we sat down and talked about: what’s going on? And through those conversations, figured out that goals weren’t being clearly established, prioritized and communicated. </span></p>
<p><strong><big>It sounds like it can be really hard to see the things that could impede velocity when you’re in the moment. Is this a skill—or “spidey sense”—you’re constantly working on?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s something that I’m learning about every single week. I’m in probably 8 different projects right now in various stages, and so every single week each of those projects is in a different stage. I can lean into what I’ve learned from one early stage project as I start the next one. I don’t think you ever resolve or finish or uncover or unlock velocity. I think one of those things you have to constantly work towards.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"I don’t think you ever resolve or finish or uncover or unlock velocity."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22I%20don%E2%80%99t%20think%20you%20ever%20resolve%20or%20finish%20or%20uncover%20or%20unlock%20velocity.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2694' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I just made an ongoing list in my brain of things that have gone wrong before. And so as you encounter those problems, you add them to your shitlist. And then you can also have an institutional list that other people have reference points for. “Hey, remember how this goes wrong?” One of the things I’ve done is try to bring in touchpoints into our process that remind us to think about the things that have gone wrong with other projects. Because that can save you a lot of time in the long run if you uncover it early.</span></p>
<p><strong><big>You’ve worked at high-growth companies like Yammer and Asana. How have they paved the way for a healthy amount of product velocity?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">At Yammer a major motivation that we tap into is motivation from autonomy. We have a really strong mode of working where we expect that whoever is closest to the problem should be the one to call what the answer is going to be. I’d had this problem where I had a project team where we wanted to do something, and I had a product manager say, “I don’t think that’s a good idea.” I was like, “Look, I’ve looked into this, I’ve done a lot of work on the ground floor, and I think it’s a good idea, and we’re going to do it.” And he was like, “Okay, cool. I don’t think it’s a good idea, but you’re closer to the problem, so go ahead.” So making sure people who are closest to the problem are the ones who make the calls about what to do.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the things that Asana leans into to promote velocity is that they have a lot of transparency about who’s doing what and when. And that’s by nature, since their product is a tool to figure out who’s doing what. The product you’re building internally is going to have a lot to do with how you operate. Especially when you’re building a workplace collaboration tool. Asana was also very much aligned with the expectation that whoever is closest to the problem should solve it. And they have a lot of explicit transparency into who is supposed to be solving what problems, because every problem is listed in Asana and every Asana task has an assignee. That’s how their product works, and so that’s the way the organization works.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2767" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-angry_emojis.png" alt="Anna Marie Clifton - Angry emojis divider" width="384" height="128" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-angry_emojis.png 384w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-angry_emojis-300x100.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 384px) 100vw, 384px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>We’ve talked about the importance of direction and clarity for velocity. What are some less common pain points you’ve experienced when trying to increase or maintain velocity?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here’s one that’s not very obvious. We have a localized product, which means we have 37 different languages that our product can be used in, and the UI is translated. That means that whenever we add a new piece of UI that has a copy addition, we need to get that localized into 37 different languages. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These are problems that you face at scale; this is not a problem that startups have. But in order to get something shipped, if we want a last-minute copy change, we have to go through our translation service. One of the things you can do as a PM is have your copy really thoroughly vetted, and make sure you get all the right eyes on it and no one’s going to say, “I didn’t see this. I think it needs a few tweaks.” Because a little change like that can mean a couple weeks of delay.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the jobs of the PM is to consider all these different inputs and make sure that you, as you kick off the project, are thinking about what other teams need to get involved. Our engineers run the project management of the actual engineering themselves, but there are a lot of other inputs in user research and analytics and copy design and translation. We could bring in someone to do an accessibility audit too late, and then find there’s a whole bunch of voiceover missing or some elements of the UI aren’t accessible. It’s important to get the right people to consider your feature earlier on in the process. Because if you have to go back and redesign something because someone who only uses a keyboard can’t use it, that’s going to put a huge, huge slowdown on the project.</span></p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><strong><big>With so many inputs and stakeholders to consider, how can interpersonal issues affect velocity?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As we discussed, one of the things that’s been an issue on some of my teams is ambiguity about what to do. If no one knows what you should do about a problem, the whole team will just kind of halt. That’s one of the big roles of a PM: making sure to shelter your team from ambiguity.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sometimes issues comes up where I’m like, “Huh, I have no idea what we should do about that.” If it’s not obvious, I’ll be very explicit about the fact that we’ll handle this at a future point. Then I make a point of figuring out when it’s going to become a blocking issue, versus how many things we’re working on that we would do the same, no matter what we do about this issue. Then I’m like, “Okay, up until next Friday, we can continue working on the project as we were working on it, because everything we’re doing right now does not impact this issue, and no matter how we deal with it, we’d still have to do this other work anyway. So carry on, don’t worry about this one right now. But I’ll be bringing this up in a product team meeting, or I’ll get user research involved, or maybe I’ll dig into analytics and figure out what the answer is or what the answer should be.” And then come back to the team with, “Hey, here’s what we should do.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think it’s a big, big problem if you, as a PM, sit in a meeting and are like, “Yeah, I don’t know what we should do.” I’ve done that before, and I’ve seen my team totally lose all their mojo.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2768" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-happy_emojis.png" alt="Anna Marie Clifton - Happy emojis divider" width="384" height="128" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-happy_emojis.png 384w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-happy_emojis-300x100.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 384px) 100vw, 384px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>So is a big part of velocity giving people a sense of comfort that they’re not going to be wasting time, or making people feel a sense of security?</big></strong></p>
<p><center class="aligncenter"></center><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here’s the thing. A lot of the stuff that we do in software development is really uncertain. And that’s kind of nerve-wracking. Like, I don’t know if this feature is going to be well-received. That’s one level of uncertainty. I don’t know if this feature is going to accomplish what we want to accomplish. I don’t know if the way I’m building this feature is the best way. I don’t know if this is actually going to work in this way. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are so many different things that people on your team don’t know, and it can be debilitating. So whenever something looms up, and it looks like it’s going to threaten my team’s ability to have confidence in what they’re doing, I try and absorb as much of that and deal with that on the PM side. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It comes back to what we said earlier about how it’s so imperative for the PM to align the whole team around the goals. Because those goals will be a guiding light in those times. And there really aren’t right answers; that’s the uncomfortable truth about product management. There are “best guesses” and “probably rights” and “mostly rights,” but there’s not “definitely rights.” And that’s something that is very, very emotionally difficult for a lot of people. I think that’s one of the challenges that you sign up for as a PM, is dealing with that existential angst. One of your jobs is to absorb it away from the team, so they feel confident in moving forward.</span></p>
<p><strong><big>It seems like velocity is as much an emotional question as a tactical question. What “soft skills” are important to velocity?</big></strong></p>
<p><b></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Energy and optimism. That’s so imperative to have on the team, and it doesn’t necessarily have to come from the PM. But the more optimism and energy you have inherent in the humans you’re working with, the more oomph there is to take to a challenge. It’s also really nice to balance the team with a few pessimists so you find those problems.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"That’s one of the big roles of a PM: making sure to shelter your team from ambiguity."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22That%E2%80%99s%20one%20of%20the%20big%20roles%20of%20a%20PM%3A%20making%20sure%20to%20shelter%20your%20team%20from%20ambiguity.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2694' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But a single optimist on the team can bring that energy for everyone. I think there’s a lot of voodoo around that. And that’s something that I’m still spending a lot of time focusing on and trying to understand and lean into a bit more. One of my personal strengths is having a whole bunch of energy. There are always tradeoffs. But it’s a strength that I’m trying to find the best sides of and bring them to my team.</span></p>
<p><strong><big>What are the emotional consequences if velocity just isn’t there?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There’s the compounding issue where it can give you a moral feeling of delay. And that’s really sticky, because you’re not working with contractors, you’re not working with a one-time crew, you’re working with people you’re going to keep working with. And it’s really important to keep thinking about, whatever you do with this project, if it feels like it slowed down a lot at the end, then they’re going to feel that way about you and about your projects and working with you moving forward. You have to manage the feelings as much as anything else.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2769" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-worried_emojis.png" alt="Anna Marie Clifton - Worried emojis divider" width="384" height="128" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-worried_emojis.png 384w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/Anna_Marie_Clifton-worried_emojis-300x100.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 384px) 100vw, 384px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>Let’s get tactical. What are the concrete ways you try to enhance velocity?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We’ve already talked about uncovering problems in advance. There’s a system that I like to use here. We have a meeting that we run with our engineers shortly after we kick off work on a project called the edge case bash. And we sit the whole team in a room and have a list of edge cases that have been problems in the past. And then we go over all of the edge cases and we think about, “Okay, how could this edge case affect this product?”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I’ll give you an example. We start with the empty case. And we think about, “What are all the different ways that, if there’s no data here, this could impact this feature?” What happens if someone doesn’t have an image? Or what if they don’t have their name; they just have their email address? Or what if there’s no content in this group yet? Or what if this is a brand new network and they don’t have any groups?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We have a list of about 25 types of edge cases that we go through as a team. And we think about, “How could this be a problem in our project?” And we usually end up with 30 or 40 different edge cases that we come up with in that one hour meeting. And then the PM will go back and consider, okay, how likely are these edge cases to happen, and how bad are they if they do?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You’ll always, always be finding more issues as you go. But this is a super-charged way to uncover as many ugly issues as you can at the beginning. </span></p>
<p><strong><big>What other essential boxes do you check to maintain velocity?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the things a PM can do early on is bring in people from other product domains and bring in issues that might surface.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"You have to manage the feelings as much as anything else."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22You%20have%20to%20manage%20the%20feelings%20as%20much%20as%20anything%20else.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2694' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We have someone who is an accessibility guru and champion internally. I always schedule a meeting with that person really early in the ideation phase to just go over what I’m planning to build and see if there’s anything we should consider. Because what happens at the end of the project is if you didn’t do an accessibility audit early on, someone will come by and be like, “Hey, these are accessibility issues.” And you’ll have to address them and you’ll think you’re about to launch and then you end up delaying a couple weeks because you have to go back and rethink something.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the other things I try to do really studiously is that whenever anything changes during the execution phase, I make the point of surfacing that information as quickly as possible up the chain in product, in case there’s some chance that there’s something I don’t know about, or product may have a competing reason why we shouldn’t do that. So just in case something is going to be a problem, they can surface it early. </span></p>
<p><strong><big>You mentioned the “final mile” in getting a feature to market. What are some of the challenges around velocity in that final mile, and how do you alleviate them?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So much of what we’ve been talking about has been: how do you anticipate problems, and then get them in front of the right people in time so it’s not going to end up delaying your engineers? Your engineers are on one track of work, but there’s a whole bunch of other stuff that happens on other tracks. And the point is, kick those off as early as you can. So that by the time that train comes to the end of the station from an engineering perspective, you don’t have other trains that are still pushing along from accessibility or copy or marketing getting the right messaging out, or things like that. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So the tactical solution there is just, constantly be messaging with your partners in other teams, or partner teams, around what you’re working on or what your timelines are. And make sure you’ve gotten that information to them so you know how much time they need to react.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"One of the ways you can promote velocity best is just by exhibiting it internally."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22One%20of%20the%20ways%20you%20can%20promote%20velocity%20best%20is%20just%20by%20exhibiting%20it%20internally.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2694' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When you join a new team, it’s figuring out, do I need to talk to marketing? Who’s the security person that I talk to about security concerns? Figuring out what all those steps are is a big part of PM onboarding. And every time you run a project, I find something else that I want to add to my list of things that I check for next time. There’s really something about having tenure at an organization that can help you understand what you should be kicking upwind in order to make sure that things don’t drag on at the end. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">My advice there is just that PMs should lean on PMs; shadow other PMs’ projects well into your tenure at a new company. Go to their weekly meetings and listen to the challenges that they’re bringing up and stock that away in your mind when you’re running your projects. </span></p>
<p><strong><big>What is the #1 thing you do to promote velocity in your day-to-day?</big></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the ways you can promote velocity best is just by exhibiting it internally. People see what you do and they watch how you do it. When you come to a project with a lot of energy, and when you’re knocking things off and treating it as a priority, and ensuring that you get back to people quickly, close those loops fast, that communicates to other people what’s reasonable. What your baseline expectations are. They see that that’s what you’re doing for yourself. The biggest signal you can send to people is how you operate.</span></p>
<hr />
<p><em><strong>Shameless self-plug: </strong>One way to stop impeding product velocity? Try one of our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=annamarieclifton" target="_blank">roadmap templates</a> to align the right people on your strategy ahead of time.</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/anna-marie-clifton/">Product velocity is as much emotional as tactical</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The new, more powerful Roadmunk</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/new-roadmunk/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 14:03:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Updates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product updates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmunk]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2366</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>We made it easier than ever to share strategy across your entire organization. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/new-roadmunk/">The new, more powerful Roadmunk</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today we’re launching some game-changing updates inside Roadmunk that make it easier than ever to share strategy across your entire organization. Since launching Roadmunk, we’ve been obsessed with making roadmapping <strong>fast</strong>, <strong>simple</strong> and <strong>collaborative</strong>. Now we’re taking roadmapping to the next level—what we like to think of as &#8220;roadmapping at scale.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>Here’s how we see it.</strong></p>
<p>You’ve got one user. Let’s call her Jen. She makes a roadmap, shares it, gets alignment. Great.</p>
<p>Now let’s say Jen has a colleague, Claudia, who works in another part of the organization. She’s also making a strategy. She uses a totally different tool and shares it in a totally different meeting. Fine. But what happens when Jen and Claudia need to <strong>see how their strategies line up?</strong></p>
<p>It can get complicated and finicky, especially when everyone’s roadmaps live in different places and tools.</p>
<p>Our new system makes it easy to see the biggest picture, no matter how complex or sprawling your organization. Users can <strong>roll up multiple roadmaps into a Master</strong>, but it’s<strong> a lot more than that</strong>: we’ve overhauled our navigation and added a bunch of new features to make roadmapping more intuitive and collaborative. Here’s a quick tour of our new platform.</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<h2>Master roadmapping</h2>
<p>Roadmaps aren’t tactical documents. They’re high-level strategies. <strong>Master roadmapping</strong> creates transparency at the highest level by offering a bird’s-eye view of what’s happening across your entire organization. Roll up views from multiple roadmaps into a shareable, editable Master. See—at a glance—how different <strong>teams</strong>, <strong>products</strong>, <strong>product lines</strong> or <strong>programs</strong> fit together.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2373" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/master.png" alt="Master Roadmapping" width="1504" height="834" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/master.png 1504w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/master-300x166.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/master-768x426.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/master-1024x568.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1504px) 100vw, 1504px" /></p>
<p><strong>A few more things you can do with Master Roadmapping:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Masters can be visualized in <strong>timeline</strong> or <strong>swimlane </strong></li>
<li>Edit, attach files and comment on Masters (same as you would any other roadmap)</li>
<li>Any changes to your Master will be reflected in the original roadmap, and vice-versa</li>
<li>Organize your Master by any field: Date, Status, Owner—whatever is valuable to your audience.</li>
<li>Filter the data represented in your Master, so you’re always showing what’s relevant</li>
</ul>
<p>Our <a href="http://support.roadmunk.com/" target="_blank">support centre</a> has more information on how to use Master Roadmapping. You can also watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1NqCQfy24CI&amp;t=4s" target="_blank">this walkthrough</a> or <a href="mailto:support@roadmunk.com">contact our customer success</a> team for some hands-on help.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SccAUfRg7_M&amp;list=PLt4hNYAIL6uavPJGzLI0RREHSIrsQbMg3"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2378" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/video-link.png" alt="" width="1131" height="348" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/video-link.png 1131w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/video-link-300x92.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/video-link-768x236.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/video-link-1024x315.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1131px) 100vw, 1131px" /></a></p>
<h2>A central hub for strategy</h2>
<p>“Roadmapping at scale” also means being able to keep track of all the different roadmaps your organization is using (i.e. not having to dig for email attachments or random files). We’ve introduced a handy dashboard where you can manage your roadmaps and permissions.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone wp-image-2369 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/homescreen-animation.gif" alt="Roadmunk dashboard" width="900" height="499" /></p>
<h2>Templates = zero-effort onboarding</h2>
<p>We wanted to take all of the friction out of making your first roadmap (or getting teammates to make their first roadmap). So we built <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates" target="_blank">a library of templates</a> filled with customizable roadmaps that match different use cases. Find a template, copy it to your account, then edit from there. We’ve got templates for roadmapping<strong> products,</strong> <strong>projects</strong>, <strong>technology plans</strong>, <strong>marketing strategies</strong>, and lots more.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone wp-image-2370 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/templates.png" alt="Roadmunk roadmap templates" width="1524" height="851" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/templates.png 1524w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/templates-300x168.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/templates-768x429.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/templates-1024x572.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1524px) 100vw, 1524px" /></p>
<p>From the day we launched Roadmunk, one of our key goals was to make roadmapping <strong>collaborative</strong>. We’re pushing that objective even further, helping users collaborate beyond their own roadmap to have <em><strong>a roadmapping system</strong></em> that covers their whole organization.</p>
<p>In addition, we&#8217;ve incorporated several new features to enhance your overall roadmapping experience. These include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Item activity field</strong>: Track what has happened on items since you last viewed your roadmap.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Saved filters</strong>: Save and copy filters from one roadmap view to another.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Starred fields</strong>: Encourage common language and structure across your organization’s roadmaps. (Watch a walkthrough <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uiRnOqfUOLM&amp;index=3&amp;list=PLt4hNYAIL6uavPJGzLI0RREHSIrsQbMg3" target="_blank">here</a>.)</li>
</ul>
<p>We couldn’t be more excited to share the new Roadmunk—and hear your feedback. Take a look, play around, and don&#8217;t hesitate to <a href="mailto:support@roadmunk.com">get in touch</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Want to know more? <a href="http://www.roadmunk.com/new-roadmunk" target="_blank">Read the full story on our new system.</a></strong></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/new-roadmunk/">The new, more powerful Roadmunk</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Inside Breather: Working in product at a rapidly scaling startup</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/christine-montgomery/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 16:46:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[growth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management career]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[startup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[startup culture]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2258</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Since starting as employee 100 at Breather, Christine Montgomery has seen the startup double in size. She chats with us about her first year as a product manager at a rapidly scaling startup.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/christine-montgomery/">Inside Breather: Working in product at a rapidly scaling startup</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Christine Montgomery was employee 100 at <a href="http://www.breather.com" target="_blank">Breather</a>, a Montreal-based startup that rents on-demand, <em>Architectural Digest</em>-esque workspaces by the hour. In the year since Christine joined the company, Breather’s headcount has doubled. And their product has expanded to new markets across North America and around the world.</p>
<p>That’s a lot of growth. And with that much growth comes huge opportunity—but also way more complexity. After years working in product at a legacy media company, where processes were deeply entrenched, Christine traded tried-and-true for chaotic-but-way-more-creative. She shares some observations from her first year as a product manager at a rapidly scaling startup.</p>
<p><strong><big>Why did you want to join Breather?</big></strong></p>
<p>It was one of those things where I went to the website and immediately understood what they were trying to do. It clicked right away. But I was particularly attracted to working with a physical product and working in the realm of service design where software actually meets the way people interact with space. And I was really attracted to the idea of working with an interior design team. Immediately when I saw Breather, it clicked.</p>
<p><strong><big>Coming from a corporate background, were there any “habits” you had to break?</big></strong></p>
<p>At my last company, despite it being large, the digital team very much worked in an agile environment. We were almost in a silo for a good portion of when I was there. We were heavily, heavily processed, but that process worked very effectively. And when I came to Breather, we did not have any process at all. I was used to having a partner and a scrum master. I had to readjust and embrace the chaos of a startup. And figure out how to deliver value in that environment.</p>
<p>And the other thing, which was so extremely positive, was I think when you work in large companies, there’s almost a manipulation of the facts. At Breather, there are so many really strong people who work here who want a really honest understanding of how effective our product is. I like the upfrontness of a startup. That was super refreshing.</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><strong><big>What are biggest product lessons you’ve learned since you started at Breather?</big></strong></p>
<p>So the first one, as I was touching on before, is to embrace chaos, be comfortable with vagueness, and focus on value. If I had to pick one thing, it’s absolutely that. It’s really challenging. But you always have to be thinking: what’s the most valuable? It’s okay that we don’t have a process for this. It’s okay that we’re still figuring it out, because we know what the mission is, and we’re going to find what’s valuable.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"I have no idea what this is. And I have to lead this team. And everyone knows more than me."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22I%20have%20no%20idea%20what%20this%20is.%20And%20I%20have%20to%20lead%20this%20team.%20And%20everyone%20knows%20more%20than%20me.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2258' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>Another thing is: treat everything you build like it could be thrown out. In product management now everyone has really embraced this MVP and fast delivery culture, which is amazing. And you really need to be able to live and breathe that, because we’re still discovering what our product is. So everything we do must be fast and unprecious.</p>
<p><strong><big>What are some of the ways you focus on value amid chaos?</big></strong></p>
<p>I try not to worry too much about frameworks. I do think they’re important, and becoming increasingly important as we grow. But one of the mistakes we made as a product org in the past year is to be very focused on process, versus people-focused.</p>
<p>It can definitely be challenging to focus on value when you’re a scaling startup. In my last position, it was very easy to be data-driven because it was a legacy product where we knew everything about it, we had a very established API. We had all of our tools in place to measure. Whereas at a startup, we’re still building those things. You really have to focus on how well an initiative aligns with the mission of the company and the key strategies.</p>
<p><strong><big>Are there business advantages that come out of chaos?</big></strong></p>
<p>The advantage of chaos in a scaling business is speed and independence. There are times when it’s been unclear what’s going on, or who owns what, but the benefit is that innovation can come out of that. It gives people autonomy to try new things.</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-2309 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.20.32-PM-copy-300x182.png" alt="" width="874" height="530" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.20.32-PM-copy-300x182.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.20.32-PM-copy-768x465.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.20.32-PM-copy-1024x620.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.20.32-PM-copy.png 1076w" sizes="(max-width: 874px) 100vw, 874px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>What are the hardest parts of being on a product team at a company that’s growing so quickly?</big></strong></p>
<p>One major challenge for us is that Breather became international very quickly. We have spaces in Canada, in the UK, all over the US, and we’re expanding elsewhere very soon. So ensuring there’s strong communication and a strong feedback loop when you get international so quickly is definitely a challenge. We have people all around the world who really understand the business and especially understand it on the ground in their city. And keeping those communication lines open has been a challenge that we’ve had to overcome.</p>
<p>I think you go through a bit of a pendulum when you’re scaling. We have gone from being very, very centralized and very slow as a product team, but very thorough, to being very chaotic. We did this whole cross-functional transformation that made us very, very tied with the engineering team. We were going a lot quicker, but then we suffered on the communication side.</p>
<p>So now we’ve swung the pendulum another way towards being an engineering-focused product team. I think a big challenge has been that pendulum back-and-forth. We’ll probably continue to swing, but that’s what the job is.</p>
<p><strong><big>Can you map out more specifically how your product org has evolved since you started at Breather?</big></strong></p>
<p>When I started, we had an independent product team, and we very much worked in a waterfall. We had a pretty dry backlog, and it was very heavy in terms of actually getting to the point where we would work with the delivery team. We recognized this as a problem, and said, “What can we do about it?”</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"You can’t solve communication, but oftentimes the answers to improving it are quite simple."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22You%20can%E2%80%99t%20solve%20communication%2C%20but%20oftentimes%20the%20answers%20to%20improving%20it%20are%20quite%20simple.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2258' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>So we went cross-functional. And we just went headfirst into it. And then we had product managers very integrated into delivery teams, but we did not maintain the centralized function of a product org at that time. At this point we did not have dry backlogs anymore, but coordination suffered and vision suffered, and being able to connect the work to the mission was also something that we had to work through. So Breather right now is moving into this dual-track product discovery methodology where we maintain a centralized product org, who collectively think about the delivery of our product and the whole customer journey.</p>
<p><strong><big>How do you stay close to the customer when also dealing with the pressures (and chaos) of rapid growth?</big></strong></p>
<p>We have a user research team here. We have an insights team that leads the charge on ensuring that we know our personas and that we’re doing analysis on qualitative and quantitative data. But we’re still figuring out how to account for local nuances. I see that as a challenge that we’ll always have.</p>
<p>When you go into new countries, there are certain things that we didn’t think about in terms of product. We’re used to certain kinds of search methods, whereas in a different country they’re actually used to a very different pattern. Payment methods differ from country-to-country. So it’s great to have global teams embedded and to be listening to them, because they provide a great feedback loop for us in terms of: what are the major considerations we need to bring to the product to be able to understand localization?</p>
<p><strong><big>What are some of the strategies you put in place to improve communication?</big></strong></p>
<p>One thing we’re working on right now, it sounds really simple, but it’s release checklists and communication checklists. I was reading a book recently—this was kind of how this came about—called <a href="http://atulgawande.com/book/the-checklist-manifesto/" target="_blank">The Checklist Manifesto</a>. It’s written by a surgeon who talks about implementing checklists in surgery. Surgeons, because they have such a complicated job and they have so much to consider, often forget about the basics. They don’t remember the patient’s name. This happens when you work in complex environments. People always think that simple things are redundant. But I’m trying to find those simple wins.</p>
<p>I really believe communication will never be solved by anybody in a company. It will never be perfect. You have to repeat things a hundred times. You can’t solve communication, but oftentimes the answers to improving it are quite simple.</p>
<p><strong><big>Are there any other processes you would like to put in place to help manage growth?</big></strong></p>
<p>On the delivery side, I’m a huge fan of self-organizing, agnostic, cross-functional teams. I actually am not super keen with developers being associated to a function. I think they should first and foremost form small teams based on people they think they work well with. Then you have teams that are made up of people who like working with each other, and those are always the most successful teams.</p>
<p>What I’ve seen in the past is that you end up having certain teams that like the more business-as-usual, administrative stuff. And there are other teams who want to do the crazy, hacky stuff. And you let them float there. So I would love to see that happen.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"Everything we do must be fast and unprecious."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22Everything%20we%20do%20must%20be%20fast%20and%20unprecious.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2258' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>The other one, which I’m very keen on, is this idea of iterative research. We’ve gotten really, really good at rapid delivery. And understanding MVP and getting small chunks of software out that provide incremental value. We’re so good at that. But I think where the product community still has so much opportunity to grow is applying the same methodology to how we research and how we understand what our products are. So we get away from the point where we’ve done a 4-month project on building user segments and those are our segments for the next year. It’s like, “How do we break that up?” We can learn a lot from MVP, agile delivery methods and be a lot more iterative about research.</p>
<p><strong><big>How would iterative research manifest in reality?</big></strong></p>
<p>I think an example of that would be, let’s say you’re building your personas. You don’t need to wait until you know exactly who your personas are and you’ve synthesized the data and done all the quantitative and qualitative analysis to understand your persona. You can do an interview and ship it and that becomes part of it. And then you can do a survey, put it out there, and iterate again. You don’t have to wait until all the pieces are together.</p>
<p><strong><big>From a personal perspective, what’s been your most stressful moment and your most gratifying moment from the past year?</big></strong></p>
<p>In terms of personal chaos, I moved into an operations role in the company having no idea what I was doing. My boss was like, “I think this would be an amazing focus for you, I think it really complements your skill set. As product manager, communication and organization are some of your strong suits, so I think you’ll be really good at this.” And I was like, “What is he talking about? I have a demand background. I come from a content and marketing space, I have no idea what this is. And I have to lead this team. And everyone knows more than me.”</p>
<p>It ended up that my most stressful moment is my most gratifying, because I actually did end up loving it. And found out that it was something that worked really well for me. And it was gratifying in the sense that I got to learn about this entirely new side of the business that I had no familiarity with, but that I’m actually super interested in and very excited about.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone wp-image-2311" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/14294732_168958650175365_4510570780198699008_n-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="360" height="360" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/14294732_168958650175365_4510570780198699008_n-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/14294732_168958650175365_4510570780198699008_n-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/14294732_168958650175365_4510570780198699008_n-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/14294732_168958650175365_4510570780198699008_n-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/14294732_168958650175365_4510570780198699008_n-1.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 360px) 100vw, 360px" />  <img class="alignnone wp-image-2312" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.18.25-PM-300x300.png" alt="" width="360" height="360" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.18.25-PM-300x300.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.18.25-PM-150x150.png 150w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.18.25-PM-768x765.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.18.25-PM-1024x1020.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Screen-Shot-2016-10-14-at-3.18.25-PM.png 1077w" sizes="(max-width: 360px) 100vw, 360px" /></p>
<p><strong><big>Looking forward to the next year, how do you see your product team and yourself as a product manager evolving to meet the needs of growth?</big></strong></p>
<p>I think as we grow what I’m really looking forward to is focus. You wear many, many hats as a product manager in a scaling startup, and you do a lot of different roles that are outside of what you would traditionally consider product management. And that’s awesome. It’s really cool to be able to do that, but I also look forward to focusing on long-term product initiatives. And just as I said you have to treat everything like you can throw it out in a minute, it’s going to be awesome as well to do some long-term thinking.</p>
<p>We have some room to think about these really cool, innovative, R&amp;D-oriented product things. And because we work with physical space and software, there’s going to be a lot of really interesting things coming out of Breather in next year or two in terms of product that are very—for the lack of a better word—futuristic.</p>
<p>What fun. What more could a product-and-technology-oriented person want than to be working on the latest things and to be working on innovation?</p>
<hr />
<p><em><strong>Note from Roadmunk: </strong>If you&#8217;re an organization experiencing rapid scaling, a roadmap miiight be just what you need. Check out our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=christinemontgomery" target="_blank">template library</a> to start aligning that growing headcount.</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/christine-montgomery/">Inside Breather: Working in product at a rapidly scaling startup</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Self-disrupting with Wattpad&#8217;s head of emerging products</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/tarun-sachdeva/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 16:30:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product strategy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tarun sachdeva]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wattpad]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1844</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>We chat with Tarun Sachdeva, Head of Emerging Products at Wattpad, about his lab-style, experimental process for self-disruption and what that disruption actually looks like in the real world. Spoiler: It’s not just about making cool shit.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/tarun-sachdeva/">Self-disrupting with Wattpad&#8217;s head of emerging products</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For early-stage companies, reaching product-market fit is an enormous milestone. But it’s hardly the finish line. Every product—even a young, shiny, super-popular product—is at risk of disruption.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tarunsachdeva/" target="_blank">Tarun Sachdeva</a> leads the Emerging Products team at <a href="http://www.wattpad.com" target="_blank">Wattpad</a>, a Toronto startup that’s built a massive platform for storytellers. Wattpad is a thriving community of creative folks. And while they’re going strong—almost 50 million users strong (!)—they’re taking a proactive approach to potential disruption. <strong>Tarun’s team was specifically created to preempt new players in their market.</strong></p>
<p>But while Tarun engages a lab-style, experimental process, his team is not conducting &#8220;maybe someday&#8221; experiments. They are explicitly driven towards solving real problems for their current and new markets. We chatted with Tarun about what self-disruption actually looks like in the real world (i.e. for real users).</p>
<p><strong>Spoiler:</strong> It’s not just about making cool shit.</p>
<p><strong><big>Tell us about your role. How are you self-disrupting?</big></strong></p>
<p>My role at Wattpad right now is head of emerging products and partnerships. The team was formed with the objective to find new markets and value networks for Wattpad. If you’re familiar with the <a href="http://www.claytonchristensen.com/key-concepts/" target="_blank">Clay Christensen school of thought</a>, you know what that means: trying to find a way to disrupt Wattpad from within Wattpad.</p>
<p>When we look at Wattpad’s growth over the last five years, we’ve seen us get to <strong>almost 50 million users across the world</strong>, and we’ve done a really great job in building this incredible community of storytellers and audiences and brands that are interacting with each other.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><hr /><p><em>"My role explores what else is out there, based on a hypothesis that things will change."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22My%20role%20explores%20what%20else%20is%20out%20there%2C%20based%20on%20a%20hypothesis%20that%20things%20will%20change.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1844' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></span></p></blockquote>
<p>And now, in some senses, we’re seen as the incumbent.<strong> And we want to make sure we are constantly exploring the next frontiers.</strong> We’re constantly reevaluating how we achieve our vision to connect and entertain the entire world through stories, but with the tools and the technology that are available to us today. So if Wattpad were reinvented today, would it look the same as it does right now? Probably the answer to that is “no.”</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><strong><big>Wattpad is still a startup. How did you realize it was already time to think about self-disruption?</big></strong></p>
<p>We’ve started to see—and this is true not just for Wattpad, but for a lot of products—the market around us has started to move. There are new capabilities in terms of what phones can do today. And those are different, obviously, than what was available when Wattpad started. There are new technologies like machine learning and artificial intelligence that are making it possible to interact with technology in new and interesting ways.</p>
<p>The ways in which we’re interacting with technology is becoming more frictionless, and the concept of us going to technology to accomplish a task is becoming less and less relevant. It’s more that we speak to our technology; we live in our technology. It’s also very immersive, so we’re noticing a lot of these larger trends that are happening around us: new platforms, new technology, that have forced us to say, “Hey, let’s take a step back and explore what that next frontier of storytelling looks like.”</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1908 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/TS_divider-2.png" alt="Round-bottom flask - divider" width="128" height="128" /></p>
<p><strong><big>So is your central question: &#8220;If we were to start all over, what would we do?&#8221;</big></strong></p>
<p>It’s more that we always look to our vision as the North Star. Which is to entertain and connect the world through stories. So we think about: how can we do that based on what is available today? We built a really, really incredible product and community, and a really great operation to support that and make sure that continues growing.</p>
<p>My role explores what else is out there, based on a hypothesis that things will change. <strong>The world around us will change whether or not we like it. It’s our choice to respond to that actively or to let it happen to us, and react to it.</strong> So what we’ve decided to do is choose the former path, and take an active stance in exploring that, understanding it better, trying a lot of different things, and seeing what sticks.</p>
<p><strong><big>Tell us about some of the “different things” you’re trying.</big></strong></p>
<p>We’re trying a lot of things along a few different horizons. One of the horizons is looking at new platforms of computing—things like new consumer technologies like Alexa and Echo. There are these new consumer products that people have started to interact with that didn’t exist before. What is the role of storytelling in those products?</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"Ultimately, our goal as an organization is to make sure that we’re continuing to innovate."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22Ultimately%2C%20our%20goal%20as%20an%20organization%20is%20to%20make%20sure%20that%20we%E2%80%99re%20continuing%20to%20innovate.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1844' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>There’s looking at existing platforms like mobile, and looking at new ways that you can enable storytelling on those platforms. And it’s also thinking about—because Wattpad is a network and we believe strongly in community—how people share and network around stories today. It’s effectively trying out new mediums of storytelling in existing networks and existing mediums, and trying out new mediums altogether.</p>
<p><strong><big>Is there any particular structure or constraints you have around your processes of exploration?</big></strong></p>
<p>There is always a purpose to what we are doing. And we want to make sure that we’re not just building for the sake of building. We are building based on a specific hypothesis. We work under this umbrella of <strong>hypothesis-driven development</strong>, where we make a hypothesis around what effect we believe a certain trend is going to have, or how this platform is going to grow. We make that hypothesis, and then we test that out. If you build without that, you don’t really know what success looks like. You build something, and then you’re like, “Okay, well, what was the objective?” What were you actually trying to prove or disprove?</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1915 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/TS_divider-5.png" alt="Test tubes - divider" width="128" height="128" /></p>
<p>And by consistently making sure we have a hypothesis, that helps us make sure that we don’t end up—I don’t want to call it pointless, because I think there’s a place for directionless exploration. But we want to make sure we avoid that being the modus operandi. We’re not the kind of organization that just builds cool shit for the sake of building cool shit.</p>
<p><strong><big>How can a PM ensure they’re self-disrupting in a way that adds real-world value?</big></strong></p>
<p>There’s a couple things I would say here. The first is to try to adopt what Elon Musk coined as the <a href="http://99u.com/workbook/20482/how-elon-musk-thinks-the-first-principles-method" target="_blank">First Principles approach of thinking</a>. That’s where you think about: what is always going to be true about the people that you’re trying to serve? How does your product serve them today and how can your product do that in new and better ways? You can apply that not just to your entire product, but to a very small part of your product, as well. Or an experience in your product.</p>
<p>Product development typically goes, you make a bet and you get to a product-market fit, and then you just iterate and iterate and iterate to make things better and better and better. But then you get to a certain point where all those iterations stop paying off as much as they used to. You’re sort of plateauing in the effort you’re putting into it.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"We want to make sure that we’re not just building for the sake of building."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22We%20want%20to%20make%20sure%20that%20we%E2%80%99re%20not%20just%20building%20for%20the%20sake%20of%20building.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1844' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>And so that’s probably a good time to ask yourself: <strong>well, what are people actually trying to do?</strong> What problems are you actually solving? And try to get to that first principle of what people are trying to solve, and solve that again with the learning, the technology, the ability that you have today. That doesn’t mean redesign. <strong>It means rethink how you approach the problem.</strong></p>
<p><strong><big>How does the validation process differ from more traditional product development?</big></strong></p>
<p>It doesn’t differ too much. What you’re looking for is product-market fit. You’re looking for some kind of validation from users that you’ve solved a problem and tapped into a need for them. And you’re doing it in a market segment that is growing, so there’s a larger opportunity out there. The way that we go about validating a product is kind of like how you would do it in regular product development. It’s applying the same sort of experimental product development thinking, just in a different place.</p>
<p><strong><big>What does success look like for your team?</big></strong></p>
<p>Ultimately, our goal as an organization is to make sure that we’re continuing to innovate, we’re continuing to keep an eye out for those market opportunities and making the right investments in areas where makes sense. Right now it makes sense for us to do a lot of that exploration. Three years from now, will it mean that we will take a product that may have worked in emerging products and turn that into something bigger? I’m not sure.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1909 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/TS_divider-3.png" alt="Microscope - divider" width="128" height="128" /></p>
<p>But definitely I think that the spirit of constant observation of the world around us and constant reevaluation of where we need to make investments—to either explore or put more fuel on the fire—those are business decisions that we will make. Those become less about, “Hey, this is a framework that we should always follow.” It’s about, “We need to get to our vision. What is the best thing we need to do to get to our vision?&#8221;</p>
<p><strong><big>Can you share any ideas or new products you’ve been really excited about?</big></strong></p>
<p>There’s a couple of things we worked on last quarter. The first one was a new storytelling product for mobile that is very much in development. And we also explored things with the Alexa platform and using voice as a medium for enjoying stories—which is really fun.</p>
<p>We worked on some smaller projects, as well, based on an observation of how rich messaging experiences were getting, and how storytelling and messaging were starting to converge in an interesting way. We launched some iMessage apps for that.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"Speed and experimentation are the fundamental of everything we do."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22Speed%20and%20experimentation%20are%20the%20fundamental%20of%20everything%20we%20do.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1844' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>We look forward to more of those types of things, and probably also looking to things like AR and VR: looking at how machine learning and artificial intelligence plays a role in the creative storytelling process. We’re looking at how ubiquitous and sort of frictionless interactions with our consumer technology has an effect on storytelling.</p>
<p><strong><big>What are 3 guiding principles any emerging products department should keep in mind?</big></strong></p>
<p>I think the <strong>first</strong> is, if you’re building out a new part of your business, you want to make sure that you build the right business case for it, so the reason for that team’s existence is very, very clear to both the team and the rest of the organization.</p>
<p>The <strong>second</strong> thing is, I would make it very clear what success actually looks like. Defining what success means for a team that is working on lab, skunkworks type of thing needs to be very, very clear.</p>
<p>And I think the <strong>third</strong> is defining a clear working model that allows for speed and experimentation. I think speed and experimentation are the fundamental of everything we do. If we don’t operate with speed, and if we don’t operate in an environment where we’re constantly experimenting with things, then it hinders that team’s ability to actually learn. Through speed and experimentation you learn, and that learning helps you understand and develop the right product.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1910 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/TS_divider-4.png" alt="Test tube - divider" width="128" height="128" /></p>
<p><strong><big>What have you learned about experimentation that you didn’t know before doing this particular role?</big></strong></p>
<p>We have a very, very strong culture of experimentation here at Wattpad. And we are highly evidence-driven. We want to make sure that the things that we build for 45 million users or 500 users have evidence of something. Whether that evidence comes through qualitative, latitudinal studies or through A/B testing, we put a lot of effort into building out our experimentation and data infrastructure that has given the product organization a massive amount of leverage, and it’s been a huge service to the rest of the organization.</p>
<p>When I think about product management in its nature, what you are doing is you are facilitating problem-solving. <strong>And you’re facilitating problem-solving through experimentation.</strong> And the scope of that experimentation can sometimes be: you’re making a big bet on the market. Or sometimes the scope of that experimentation can be red button, blue button.</p>
<p>But at the end of the day, it’s all an experiment. So, when I think about product management, it’s just facilitating an experimental problem-solving process. It should always be experimentation.</p>
<hr />
<p><em><strong>How Roadmunk can help: </strong>Whether you&#8217;re self-disrupting or getting ahead of a disruptive market, a roadmap can help you navigate through the process. Try any of our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=tarunsachdeva" target="_blank">roadmap templates</a> to get in front of disruption.</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/tarun-sachdeva/">Self-disrupting with Wattpad&#8217;s head of emerging products</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How FreshBooks’ creative director bridges product &#038; brand</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/jeremy-bailey/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 14:59:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[freshbooks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jeremy bailey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[user experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ux]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1693</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>We talk to Jeremy Bailey, Creative Director for Product at FreshBooks, about stripping brands back to their studs, ditching your biases, and the Wild West. Like, the literal Wild West.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/jeremy-bailey/">How FreshBooks’ creative director bridges product &#038; brand</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Since its launch more than a decade ago, <a href="https://www.freshbooks.com/" target="_blank">FreshBooks</a> has achieved an unlikely end-goal: making DIY accounting feel painless, quick and even fun. Going cross-eyed over spreadsheets isn&#8217;t <em>usually</em> part of the self-employed dream—but it can easily become part of the reality.</p>
<p><a href="https://ca.linkedin.com/in/jeremy-bailey-0327052" target="_blank">Jeremy Bailey</a>, FreshBooks’ Creative Director for Product, played an instrumental role in establishing FreshBooks as the go-to cloud accounting software for small-business owners. Initially hired as a freelance art director, he joined the team full-time in 2010, delving deeply into users’ problems to connect a relatable marketing experience to a product that genuinely helps its customers. Marketing and product can often seem like their own realms, but Bailey has a foot firmly planted in both worlds. (He also works as a visual artist under his tongue-in-cheek alter-ego, <a href="http://jeremybailey.net/" target="_blank">Jeremy Bailey: Famous New Media Artist</a>.)</p>
<p>As part of our ongoing interview series with awesome product people, we chatted with Bailey about stripping brands back to their studs, ditching your biases, and the Wild West. Like, the literal Wild West.</p>
<p><big><strong>Your title is pretty unusual. How did you come to be Creative Director for Product?</strong></big></p>
<p>I was freelancing and FreshBooks was a client that came to me with a problem. I think a lot of startups probably have this problem: different people have come and gone really rapidly over the first few years. And different people have put their flag in the ground. So there were a lot of arbitrary and sometimes well-guided decisions, but altogether they don’t add up to a cohesive whole. That was definitely true for FreshBooks, not for any mal-intent, but just for the sheer speed at which they were operating.<br />
<img class="aligncenter wp-image-1699 size-medium" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-1-300x110.png" alt="Design elements - Divider" width="300" height="110" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-1-300x110.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-1.png 561w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><br />
They hired me to help bring that all together. And the first thing I did was wrong, too. I proposed a sweeping new look. And the humbling lesson that I learned is to figure out what their customer needs. So that became my job. And what I discovered by talking to the customers and spending time with the staff was that what they already had was wonderful. People already loved what they were doing. There were certain aspects of their brand, not visual, that people were over the moon for. Like their support, or the little things their product did to make them laugh. And the things the customers really loved could be applied more broadly across the whole product and platform. The whole image of the company.</p>
<p><big><strong>How did you calibrate design changes that went &#8220;too far” vs. changes that would have value?</strong></big></p>
<p>It was a very simple strategy that’s the same strategy every home renovator uses on a home decorating show. Which is to strip it all the way back down to the studs. And say, “What is the least we can have and still evoke these emotions?” So visually it would be removing all the drop shadows, the gradients, the additional flourishes, and saying, “Hey, we’re going to stick to a really simple color palette, and exercising some restraint will help us find out what’s essential. And when we hit a roadblock, we’ll add to that palette. And by pulling all the way back and then adding, we’ll understand how each decision was made.”</p>
<p>I was able to help arbitrary decision-making become more structured decision-making.</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><big><strong>How far back did you strip it, exactly?</strong></big></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We went back to blue and white and black. Which were the colors of the logo. And green for calls to action. And I got rid of all the non-heritage, non-long-lasting typefaces, because I knew they’d have to be replaced. And we just stuck with that.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"You don’t invent the brand, the customer invents it and then you just reflect it back to them."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22You%20don%E2%80%99t%20invent%20the%20brand%2C%20the%20customer%20invents%20it%20and%20then%20you%20just%20reflect%20it%20back%20to%20them.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1693' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We were using stock photos for our illustration, and I knew that wasn’t going to help us stand out. This was Web 2.0 era, and there were probably 30 competitors doing the exact same thing at the exact same point in their progress in the market. So there were 30 other brands people loved. My experience told me that if you want to stand out, you need to do something other people can’t do. And you don’t copy what others are doing. So constrain our palette, and then start to do things that others couldn’t copy.</span></p>
<p>It’s really basic. I kind of feel that anyone could apply that tomorrow and improve their brand. But then the more difficult thing in the longer term is: “How do we translate that same approach to the product?” At first we just did a visual scrub of the product, but for the last three years I’ve been really focused on bringing that same decision-making, consistency and restraint to the product.</p>
<p><big><strong>Do you have some advice around how to exercise effective constraint?</strong></big></p>
<p>One thing we did at FreshBooks was make it really hard for a single individual to make an arbitrary decision. As an example, we formed a little council that supervises every visual decision. We call it “art director’s circle.” When you want to change an element that’s core and that impacts different aspects of the brand, you come to that council and you make a case for it. It’s not like a tribunal in a negative way, but there’s a structure to the argument. And every time we’ve thought, “This is going to be an easy decision,” it ends up being a really hard decision. And I’m glad we make those decisions early on, and not after it’s out in the wild—when we’re like “oh shit.”</p>
<p><big><strong>What kinds of considerations go into that decision-making process?</strong></big><br />
There are different vectors. There’s some standard stuff. Is it accessible? Is it on-brand in terms of just the pure guidelines that we have?</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"I don’t think any customer wakes up wishing for their company to rebrand."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22I%20don%E2%80%99t%20think%20any%20customer%20wakes%20up%20wishing%20for%20their%20company%20to%20rebrand.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1693' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>The conversation goes something like, “Here’s the problem.” We show the problem, then we ask, “How are others solving this problem today?” So we might look at how other brands are solving that problem. Then we’ll stress test the solution. When you’re building those guidelines, you’re trying them out, not just on your marketing, but you’re also trying them out on the product. You’re also trying them out on your advertising or your corporate communication.</p>
<p>This whole exercise doesn’t take more than a week, but we do that for each major decision.</p>
<p><big><strong>It can be hard to correlate design changes directly to, say, a boost in conversions or revenue. How do you make a case that design changes add value? </strong></big></p>
<p>All these things add up to emotion, and if you feel like you’re coming out with a message and you’re not reinforcing that message, then of course you want to align them with that, because that’s going to help people understand with greater impact. You only have a few seconds of a person’s time when they first meet you, and if they’re wearing bedroom slippers outdoors in the snow, you’re going to be like, “What’s going on here?”</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1702 size-medium" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-2-300x111.png" alt="Pen and money - divider" width="300" height="111" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-2-300x111.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-2.png 561w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>I think it’s best to think about brands as people. And I always think of them as a reflection of the people we serve. Basically you’re trying to reflect back to that person, “Hey, I’m for you.” Not only am I for you—I look like you, I sound like you. It’s a trust thing. You don’t invent the brand, the customer invents it and then you just reflect it back to them.</p>
<p><big><strong>Why do you think it’s often a challenge to create consistency between product and brand?</strong></big></p>
<p>Most companies are organized in silos for product and marketing. And they do their thing. And in fact, they often become enemies. I don’t think that that’s always the intent. But, “Oh marketing did this” is a common refrain I’ve heard in my career. There’s exclusive language to both disciplines, and they’re sometimes in opposition.</p>
<p><big><strong>What mechanisms have you tried to break down silos?</strong></big></p>
<p>I’ll be very honest, I’ll say that’s my biggest challenge. But in the past, where I’ve seen the most success is when you have everyone on the same team.</p>
<p>So no more, there’s a marketing team or a product team. You have a team that delivers an experience. And a marketer is a part of that team. And a marketing designer is part of that team. And a product designer is part of that team. And everyone understands the goal, and they’re all pushing forward together toward that goal. I’ve never seen a team work better together and produce higher-quality work at as great a capacity without any friction or tension.</p>
<p><img class="size-medium wp-image-1716 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-3-300x110.png" alt="" width="300" height="110" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-3-300x110.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-3.png 561w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>The problem is when you create two different goals that aren’t aligned. On two different teams in two different sides of the building. Geography actually matters. Just like talking to a customer, the same thing is true internally. Sitting next to the person that you’re going to work with creates at least some sort of empathy for the other person’s predicament.</p>
<p><big><strong>How does it benefit a company to have more consistency between the branding and the product?</strong></big></p>
<p>When you have consistency you can put arguments to rest over taste. I don’t care that your husband or boyfriend or girlfriend or wife has an opinion on the color we should use. Let’s just establish this is what we’re going to do, this is performing well, and move forward because there are so many other challenges that are as important or more important. I don’t think any customer wakes up wishing for their company to rebrand. They’re more likely to switch brands, frankly, if you do that. One of the decisions I had to make was not to update our logo seven or eight years ago. Because that was the thing people recognized and loved and they weren’t complaining about it.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"The gut instinct you have in your corporate office is 9 times out of 10 absolutely not correct."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22The%20gut%20instinct%20you%20have%20in%20your%20corporate%20office%20is%209%20times%20out%20of%2010%20absolutely%20not%20correct.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1693' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>I always explain this cocktail party analogy. A logo is a lot like someone’s face. And if you meet someone and they’ve changed a little bit over time, you’re usually like, “Wow, it’s been so long, I haven’t seen you, you’ve changed so much.” But if you come back two weeks later and they’ve changed their face again, you’re like, “Something’s wrong.”</p>
<p>With consistency, you’re taking that objection off the table. This is a trustworthy company. That’s why brands existed in the first place, was to establish trust. Because there was a Wild West out there, literally, where companies were making all kinds of elixirs and stuff like that.</p>
<p><big><strong>How can product managers support design in creating symbiosis between product and brand?</strong></big></p>
<p>That’s really easy. For us, anyway, we always thought of the product manager as a designer. Or working alongside the designer as a perfect couple. If they’re working well, those two people are essentially two halves of a whole solution for building product. So the designer leans towards design, and the manager leans toward the practicality of development. But together they form a whole unit that can deliver outstanding results.</p>
<p><img class="size-medium wp-image-1717 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-4-300x110.png" alt="" width="300" height="110" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-4-300x110.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/JB_interview-4.png 561w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>At FreshBooks the research used to be entirely done by product managers. But now they share it evenly. Design decisions used to be entirely by the designer, but we have several meetings where we do critique, and the product managers and designers critique together. They also ideate together. So at all the key junctures, they’re considered the same person. They’re reporting together, they’re demoing together, they’re like a little pair.</p>
<p><big><strong>Can you tell us about your research process at FreshBooks?</strong></big></p>
<p>We’re either talking on the phone or inviting people in to look at products, or going to their offices to learn about the problems they have. So every designer talks to four people a week. That kind of customer intimacy is irreplaceable and it creates an intuition for what the right thing is, instead of going on your gut. The gut instinct you have in your corporate office is 9 times out of 10 absolutely not correct. It’s informed by privilege. And those privileged decisions are informed by an unintentional bias that unfortunately makes us make wrong decisions on behalf of our customers.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"The worst thing you can do is look at your competitor and copy that."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22The%20worst%20thing%20you%20can%20do%20is%20look%20at%20your%20competitor%20and%20copy%20that.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1693' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>Last year we spoke to over 1000 people, this year we’ll probably speak to twice that many. When you do it on a regular basis it becomes natural. Our natural instinct is to defend our position because we don’t want to admit we’re wrong. And we find data to back up our biases, and confirm our biases. And so I think it’s really important to get out and talk to the real people.</p>
<p><big><strong>What’s the worst mistake a company can do when trying to create consistent design that runs through product and marketing?</strong></big></p>
<p>I think the worst thing you can do is look at your competitor and copy that. It’s worth emphasizing, because it’s a natural instinct when you’re small to look at what the big guys are doing. But I can’t emphasize enough how backward that strategy is. The fact that you’re small is actually your biggest advantage.</p>
<p>A great company that came to my attention—probably too late, but who I’m in love with right now—is <a href="http://www.everlane.com" target="_blank">Everlane</a>. Their concept is radical transparency. And as a very small online retailer, they leverage the fact that they have no brick-and-mortar stores to offer a cheaper price and to be transparent about their markup, and to show you their factory. So all the things the big guys couldn’t do, they’re like, “This is our brand.”</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter" src="https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/564x/fd/9b/03/fd9b032bce5636e08fea8448e8888f06.jpg" alt="Diagram showing Transparent Pricing at Everlane" width="564" height="439" /></p>
<p><big><strong>How have you leveraged this idea at FreshBooks?</strong></big></p>
<p>With accounting software, they’d say it should look like business software. “This is too playful.” Right? But that’s precisely how we distinguish ourselves versus the most corporate giants in the world. If we went out and did exactly what Intuit or Quickbooks did, we’d look like a lesser version of them.</p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>"For me, it’s the humility to understand that big problems require teams to solve."</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%22For%20me%2C%20it%E2%80%99s%20the%20humility%20to%20understand%20that%20big%20problems%20require%20teams%20to%20solve.%22&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1693' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p>But we come out and we do what they can’t do. They can’t use a playful tone, they can’t be transparent, they can’t pick up the phone. You can’t talk to the CEO. You have to play to your weaknesses as your strengths.</p>
<p><big><strong>Looking back at when you started at FreshBooks to now, what’s the most significant way you evolved as a designer?</strong></big></p>
<p>For me, it’s the humility to understand that big problems require teams to solve. You need to push down your problems to the team and collectively solve them, because ultimately they need to be implemented collectively.</p>
<p>That’s something I still work on today: how do we create organizations that emerge from the bottom? That aren’t driven from the top. Organizations where every day you come into work, and when there’s a problem you don’t just say, “Ugh, well I guess we have to deal with it because it’s the corporate way.” But where you’re like, “This problem could be solved if we work together.”</p>
<hr />
<p><em><strong>A Roadmunk sidenote: </strong>Whether you&#8217;re doing a complete rebrand or you just need to bridge that product-design gap, a roadmap can be your best friend. Use any of our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=jeremybailey" target="_blank">roadmap templates</a> to help build product-brand consistency.</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/jeremy-bailey/">How FreshBooks’ creative director bridges product &#038; brand</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Roadmap challenges at startups vs. SMEs vs. enterprise</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-roadmap-challenges/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2016 16:33:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmap challenges]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmaps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[strategic alignment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1406</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>No matter how slick your final roadmap might look, the roadmapping process can be anything but straightforward.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-roadmap-challenges/">Roadmap challenges at startups vs. SMEs vs. enterprise</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Effective product roadmaps are often <strong>simple on the surface</strong>. The cleaner and clearer your visualization, the cleaner and clearer your organization’s sense of shared purpose.</p>
<p>But no matter how slick your final roadmap might look, the roadmapping process can be anything but straightforward. In fact, we talk about “roadmapping” as a skill because it requires such a tricky combination of research, planning and empathy. (And maybe some psychology and/or hypnosis?) To get really good at roadmapping, product managers can’t just show up to the final meeting. They must learn to navigate a whole smorgasbord of roadmap challenges.</p>
<p>Case in point: a few months back, the following tweet popped up in our mentions.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet tw-align-center" data-lang="en">
<p dir="ltr" lang="en"><a href="https://twitter.com/RoadmunkApp">@RoadmunkApp</a> Ur tagline should be &#8220;create legible product roadmaps without wanting to stab yourself in the face in only 30 min!&#8221;</p>
<p>— Ellen Beldner (@elbeldner) <a href="https://twitter.com/elbeldner/status/733495571319640068">May 20, 2016</a></p></blockquote>
<p><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
<p>It <em>is</em> a punchy tagline! But more importantly, this tweet speaks to the <a href="https://roadmunk.com/company" target="_blank">exact reason our founders launched Roadmunk</a>: to make it easier for PMs to <strong>quickly</strong> build <strong>well-designed</strong> roadmaps. (Try our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=challenges" target="_blank">template library</a> to see what we mean.)</p>
<p>Roadmap challenges, however, go far beyond “it’s so annoying to build a roadmap in a spreadsheet or slides.” And the pain points can differ if you’re at a <strong>startup</strong>, <strong>SME</strong> or <strong>enterprise</strong>. With this fact in mind, we decided to take a holistic view of some of the roadmapping difficulties product managers encounter at different companies.</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-1414 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Universal_divider-300x84.png" alt="product roadmap challenges" width="450" height="126" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Universal_divider-300x84.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Universal_divider-768x215.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Universal_divider-1024x287.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /></p>
<h1>Universal pain points</h1>
<p>Some roadmap challenges are equally difficult, regardless of the size or maturity of your company or product.</p>
<p><strong>Setting priorities.</strong> This is a biggie. What should actually go INTO the roadmap? When you have lots of ideas (and demands) swirling around, it&#8217;s difficult to identify which initiatives to tackle and which to sacrifice. Product managers often need to make “big bets”—meaning some smaller projects get the axe. Understanding the benefits and tradeoffs of these decisions is a central challenge not just for roadmapping, but for product management as a whole. <a href="http://www.twitter.com/listentodaniel" target="_blank">Daniel Zacarias</a> wrote an <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-prioritization-techniques/" target="_blank">epic guide to product prioritization</a> that outlines several excellent prioritization methods, including the <strong>Kano Method</strong>, <strong>Value vs. Cost</strong> and a popular technique from <strong>Airbnb’s Director of Product </strong><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ianmcallister" target="_blank">Ian McAllister</a>.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet tw-align-center" data-lang="en">
<p dir="ltr" lang="en">Huge fan of <a href="https://twitter.com/listentodaniel">@listentodaniel</a>&#8216;s thoughtful writing on <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/prodmgmt?src=hash">#prodmgmt</a>. His guide to <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/prioritization?src=hash">#prioritization</a> is a must-read <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.2.1/72x72/1f4da.png" alt="📚" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> <a href="https://t.co/efmMb4xZaj">https://t.co/efmMb4xZaj</a></p>
<p>— Latif Nanji (@LatifNanji) <a href="https://twitter.com/LatifNanji/status/786630406816854021">October 13, 2016</a></p></blockquote>
<p><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
<p><strong>Managing expectations.</strong> What product manager hasn’t struggled with this? Sales is hungry for features. Executives are wondering why the next release wasn’t released last week. When you arrive at a roadmap meeting, everyone at the table will be fretting over (and expecting) different things. Is this roadmap going to help me close a deal? How can I build excitement in the market? Am I going to have to go back to the board and say we missed a target? Executives can be especially demanding and/or unrealistic, which is why we wrote <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/managing-executives-roadmapping-process/" target="_blank">an extensive blog on managing execs in the roadmapping process</a>.</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><strong>Connecting data to the roadmap.</strong> Solid roadmaps are strongly rooted in both empirical and qualitative data that supports the direction of the strategy. Empirical data includes <strong>engagement stats</strong>, business <strong>growth metrics</strong>, and <strong>impact on your market or customers</strong>. Qualitative data includes more emotional—but equally essential—feedback from your customers. Data is crucial, but it’s not always easy to <strong>a)</strong> get your hands on it, and <strong>b)</strong> represent data explicitly in your roadmap. New PMs are often enthusiastic about talking to customers—then start making assumptions 6 months into their role. Maintaining that energy and curiosity is time-consuming… but critical.</p>
<blockquote><p>Building roadmaps in legacy tools is a finicky, limiting time-suck.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>How to structure your roadmap.</strong> Our roadmap should be on a timeline! No, it shouldn&#8217;t have no dates! No, it should be finger-painted onto the bathroom wall! We often encounter strain around the structure of the roadmap, especially as pressure from the market comes into conflict with the ethos behind agile. We believe this decision should be rooted in culture. If your company values deadlines, your roadmap should reflect that approach. If plans are more loosey-goosey, your roadmap should be, too. Of course, a PM can affect how that culture evolves. <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/create-product-roadmap/" target="_blank">Our handy guide</a> outlines 3 basic ways to create a product roadmap, depending on the stage of your product and your culture.</p>
<p><strong>It’s annoying to actually build and share your roadmap.</strong> This goes back to the root of the problem we’re trying to solve here at Roadmunk. (And what that tweet was all about.) Building roadmaps in legacy tools is a finicky, limiting time-suck. Roadmaps should be living documents that foster transparency, but it’s very difficult to maintain that spirit without a collaborative dashboard where you can comment, update and view your plan from different angles. If this is a particular sticking point for your organization, <a href="https://roadmunk.com/enterprise-features" target="_blank">check out our full list of features.</a></p>
<h1><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1412" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Startup-divider-2-300x80.png" alt="startup roadmap challenges" width="450" height="120" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Startup-divider-2-300x80.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Startup-divider-2-768x205.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Startup-divider-2-1024x273.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /></h1>
<h1>Startup challenges: dealing with uncertainty</h1>
<p>In certain ways, roadmapping at a startup is much simpler than roadmapping at a bigger company. There’s just not as much detail to include. But that lack of certainty and structure introduces other key snags.</p>
<p><strong>Resisting the urge to over-complicate things.</strong> Startup CEOs tend to be ambitious and operationally driven. They want to feel like they’re a big, multi-million dollar organization right off the bat—and with a roadmap to match. But including oodles of detail in your early days can actually be counter-productive: it focuses too much on “operations” and “plans” at a time when the focus should be your product. Also, it doesn’t leave the door open for enough adaptability. We recommend keeping your roadmap super-simple—it might just be a simple list of features—for as long as possible.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet tw-align-center" data-lang="en">
<p dir="ltr" lang="en">Psst, <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/startups?src=hash">#startups</a>. You&#8217;re not an enterprise. And you shouldn&#8217;t build your roadmap the same way they do 🤔 <a href="https://t.co/TtOK6BE7dH">https://t.co/TtOK6BE7dH</a></p>
<p>— Roadmunk (@RoadmunkApp) <a href="https://twitter.com/RoadmunkApp/status/777532719941185536">September 18, 2016</a></p></blockquote>
<p><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><br />
<strong>Accepting change (and guesswork).</strong> Not only should a startup roadmap be simple, it should be 100% subject to change. At this stage, roadmaps are often a “best guess” of where the market is going and how your product will fit into the landscape. Again, it can be difficult to know when to pivot off your plans. Having a strict roadmap can actually be dangerous for early companies, because it can psychologically commit you to the wrong direction. Big challenge for startup founders and PMs: not getting too married to what’s on the roadmap.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1415" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/SME-divider-300x84.png" alt="small and medium size enteprise roadmap challenges" width="450" height="126" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/SME-divider-300x84.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/SME-divider-768x215.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/SME-divider-1024x287.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /></p>
<h1>SME challenges</h1>
<p>As your company becomes more complex, so does your roadmap. And so do the challenges associated with roadmapping.</p>
<p><strong>Simplifying complex strategies.</strong> For startups, a key challenge is not over-complicating things. But as departments expand and your company begins to tackle bigger initiatives, the roadmap needs to accommodate this new complexity. It’s at this stage that we generally recommend <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/create-product-roadmap/" target="_blank">moving your roadmap onto some form of timeline</a>. Finding a way to effectively visualize and communicate all the moving parts can be a head-spinning exercise. Our blog below outlines some startup-specific tactics.</p>
<blockquote><p>The challenge for the roadmap champion is to deeply understand the mindset, progress and problems the product team is facing.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Understanding of your product team.</strong> At this stage, there’s probably more than one PM in the picture. The person who owns the roadmap might not be the same PM who’s writing stories or communicating regularly with the devs. So the challenge for the roadmap champion is to deeply understand the mindset, progress and problems the product team is facing. Are they resource-strapped? Are they having trouble communicating? Are they in trouble with the competition? Are projects delayed? The challenge: really understanding the internal struggles of the product team and being able to present and communicate that information in a meaningful way.</p>
<p><strong>Knowing the voice of the customer better than anyone else.</strong> As we mentioned above, motivation to talk to customers often peters out. As a company grows and becomes more complex, product managers can get more removed from the central problem and the voice of the customer. Thing is, other departments don’t lose sight of the customer. Sales can easily derail the roadmap because they’re in is in constant communication with users, while marketing is tapped into the pulse of the community surrounding your market. If you show up to a roadmap meeting alienated from your customer and their interests, it will show. It should be a daily and conscious task to understand that landscape—or your roadmap will flop.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1416" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Enterprise-divider-300x80.png" alt="enterprise roadmap challenges" width="450" height="120" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Enterprise-divider-300x80.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Enterprise-divider-768x205.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Enterprise-divider-1024x273.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /></p>
<h1>Enterprise challenges</h1>
<p>Pretty much every SME roadmap challenge also applies to enterprise. But when a company reaches enterprise status, they also have some new wrenches to deflect.</p>
<p><strong>Responding to market trends.</strong> Enterprise is big. Enterprise is slow. Enterprise can be committed to what’s working now—even if it’s not going to be working for much longer. In the enterprise sphere, product managers must be several steps ahead of the market. It takes a while to turn a big ship, and PMs should anticipate the extra lead time they’re going to need. And while every PM should be a world-class communicator, enterprise PMs need to be extra savvy when it comes to building stakeholder trust. Otherwise no one will listen—and your roadmap will soon be stuck in the past.</p>
<blockquote><p>Would you rather be disrupted by yourself or someone else?</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Disrupting yourself.</strong> Once you’re at enterprise level, you’ve pretty much “made it.” But you’re also vulnerable to the “next big thing.” Which begs the question: would you rather be disrupted by yourself or someone else? To avoid the latter fate, your roadmap can’t just add feature after feature onto your existing schtick. It’s crucial to <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/02/technology/to-gain-the-upper-hand-amazon-disrupts-itself.html?_r=0" target="_blank">think like Amazon</a> and self-disrupt. At enterprise level, a product manager’s biggest challenge is to come up with innovative ways to evolve its own product—then convince everyone else to get on board. Instead of keeping the wheels in motion, your roadmap needs to lead you on an entirely new path.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-roadmap-challenges/">Roadmap challenges at startups vs. SMEs vs. enterprise</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>5 product managers share their rookie mistakes</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-mistakes/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2016 16:22:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management mistakes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1361</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Don’t just learn from your product management mistakes. Learn from the blunders of others!</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-mistakes/">5 product managers share their rookie mistakes</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Don’t just learn from<em> your</em> product management mistakes. Learn from the blunders of others!</p>
<p>We asked <strong>five awesome product managers</strong> to share mishaps from early in their careers—and what they learned as a result. From testing blind spots to over-building to obsessions with (not-so-useful) tools, these anecdotes run the gamut of product management gaffes. The good news: they each contain <strong>valuable insights</strong> for PMs at<strong> any stage</strong> of professional growth.</p>
<h1>The “facepalm” A/B testing moment</h1>
<p><img class="alignleft wp-image-1362 size-medium" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Lulu-300x294.png" alt="Lulu Cheng pinterest" width="300" height="294" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Lulu-300x294.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Lulu-768x753.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Lulu.png 779w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Who:</strong> Lulu Cheng<br />
<strong>Find her at:</strong> <a href="https://twitter.com/lulu_cheng" target="_blank">@lulu_cheng</a><br />
<strong>Current company:</strong> Pinterest<br />
<strong># years as a PM:</strong> “a little over 2”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Tell us what happened. </strong><br />
When I was on the growth team at Dropbox, we ran this experiment—I’ve actually totally forgotten what it was. But we got the results back and we were like, “Wow, this is really positive!” Particularly in growth, when you’re experimenting, it’s very, very rare to get big wins like that. So we were kind of surprised, but obviously really excited, and we decided to ship it.</p>
<blockquote><p>Any time experiments look like they’re too good to be true, <strong>you should probably dig in&#8230;</strong> It’s just very rare to find a silver bullet.</p></blockquote>
<p>So we launch it to everyone, and we’re looking at the results again, and we’re like, “Wait a second. Why are these results not as good as the experiment?” We start digging, and we realize that we made a mistake when we set up the original experiment. We had accidentally removed a step in the signup flow. And any time you remove steps from the signup flow, you get more people going through. That ended up being the reason why the experiment was so positive. It was kind of one of those facepalm moments.</p>
<p><strong>Ack! That sucks. But what did you learn?</strong><br />
It comes down to a pretty unglamorous lesson of “test, test, test.” Really vetting your experiments. Oftentimes testing is the last thing that anyone wants to do, but it’s so crucial to ensure that when you run A/B tests, you really only change one variable at a time. And then the other thing is: any time experiments look like they’re too good to be true, you should probably dig in. Because in growth, particularly, it’s just very rare to find a silver bullet.</p>
<h1>When <em>you’re</em> the blocker</h1>
<p><strong><img class="alignleft wp-image-1370 size-medium" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_John-300x294.png" alt="john cutler pendo" width="300" height="294" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_John-300x294.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_John-768x753.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_John.png 779w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Who:</strong> John Cutler<strong><br />
Find him here:</strong><a href="https://twitter.com/johncutlefish" target="_blank">@johncutlefish</a><strong><br />
Current company:</strong>Pendo<strong><br />
# years as a PM:</strong>“almost two decades”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>So, what’s your mistake?</strong><br />
Early in my career, I was very focused on planning. I was very focused on lining up all the stories and “feeding the machine.” It wasn’t like I wrote one crappy story. It was more a gradual accumulation of story after story without poking my head up and seeing the forest through the trees.</p>
<p>At that point in my career, I assumed the role was about listening to customers very carefully and then somehow codifying them in a spec. The irony of it is that I think the engineers appreciated that someone was feeding the machine. But I wasn’t thinking holistically about the problem, and I wasn’t helping bring the context of the customer to the team. I was being really good at one part of the role—so much so that the team became very reliant on me doing that particular thing. <strong>And then I became the blocker.</strong> My perspective became the blocker on whether were were solving the problem.</p>
<p><strong>How can others avoid this trap?</strong><br />
You need to schedule a block to reflect on your own work, step back, do your own internal retro. Is this working? Isn’t this working? Give yourself time to think strategically, instead of running between meeting after meeting after meeting. Ask yourself, “Am I doing the best work that I can? Is this effective work or am I just doing busywork?” Even 20 minutes to half an hour of just reflecting. And I would suggest that every product person keep a diary, like how a lot of designers keep sketchbooks.</p>
<h1>When you build way too much</h1>
<p><img class="alignleft wp-image-1373 size-medium" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Brandon-300x294.png" alt="brandon chu shopify" width="300" height="294" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Brandon-300x294.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Brandon-768x753.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Brandon.png 779w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Name:</strong> Brandon Chu<br />
<strong>Find him here:</strong> <a href="https://twitter.com/BrandonMChu" target="_blank">@BrandonMChu</a><br />
<strong>Current company:</strong> Shopify<br />
<strong># years as a PM:</strong> 7</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Tell us your story.</strong><br />
This is going to sound terrible, but the mistake is actually the entire way that we built and ran Tunezy. [Brandon co-founded <a href="https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/tunezy#/entity">Tunezy</a>, a social platform for YouTube musicians, in 2011.] Before we got acquired, we went through two major pivots. Fundamentally, we were trying to solve the monetization problem for YouTube musicians. The first way we planned to do that was to create a discovery tool for consumers. So it was almost like GrooveShark for YouTube musicians. The second was a big pivot into virtual concerts. And then the final thing, the one that actually started working, was a crowd-sourcing platform for fans to wish for experiences that they would have with these artists.</p>
<blockquote><p>Even if you can’t necessarily think of the product that will scale to solve that problem, by <strong>attacking it directly</strong> in a scrappy way, you learn about the right system to build on top of it.</p></blockquote>
<p>The mistake that we made, if I was to wrap everything up, is that we built way too much—instead of just trying to be scrappy and validate ideas. We had this whole system built up, how it’s going to scale. But the biggest problem was that we tried to attack the problem indirectly. We tried to build out a big system that would eventually solve a problem, as opposed to realizing that we knew the problem: musicians can’t get paid. Let’s just attack it directly.</p>
<p><strong>What did pivoting teach you?</strong><br />
Two major learnings. One of them is never forget the root problem. And attack it directly. Even if you can’t necessarily think of the product that will scale to solve that problem, by attacking it directly in a scrappy way, you learn about the right system to build on top of it. We should have honestly just been the artists’ agents and started getting them money. We should have started at the crux of the problem, which is “get them paid,” and then built the right product on top of it.</p>
<p>Another one is just a general principle to look for the hack. Don’t build something big and ship it into a vacuum. Find a way to fake things.</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<h1>When you <em>think</em> you think like the customer (but you don’t)</h1>
<p><img class="size-medium wp-image-1376 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Aran-300x294.png" alt="aran rasmussen frank and oak" width="300" height="294" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Aran-300x294.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Aran-768x753.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Aran.png 779w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Name:</strong> Aran Rasmussen<br />
<strong>Find him here:</strong> <a href="https://twitter.com/aranr" target="_blank">@aranr</a><br />
<strong>Current company:</strong> Frank + Oak<br />
<strong># years as a PM:</strong> “In one way or another it’s been 15 years.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>What went wrong? </strong><br />
The biggest moment for me was early on, this would have been 2006, 2007. Facebook was just catching on and social networks were the hot thing. I was working on a social network for athletes. And a lot of it was built around the idea of, “How can you create relationships between athletes and their fans?” It was a great idea, but we hadn’t really considered the athletes’ lifestyles and basic stuff like, “Okay, if the athlete has the account, if they are the person with the login, the problem is when they’re running a race, they are not actually generating content. They’re not the ones photographing or taking video.” We didn’t seriously think about the way the user would be able to interact with our platform. And ultimately the whole product flopped.</p>
<p><strong>What did you learn from this experience?</strong><br />
I still find myself needing to teach myself to give enough thought to how the customer will interact with your product. Oftentimes we build products and we expect the customer to change his or her behaviour in the way that we’ve designed the product. But customers generally won’t change their behaviour. They can’t change their behaviour. They don’t want to change their behaviour. They want you to solve a problem that they have. Or they want you to create some kind of enjoyment for them without them having to change. I think it comes down to more testing. I don’t know if there’s anything else that you could do besides testing.</p>
<h1>A problem with &#8220;the problem&#8221;</h1>
<p><img class="size-medium wp-image-1378 alignleft" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Magdalena-300x294.png" alt="magdalena georgieva hubspot" width="300" height="294" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Magdalena-300x294.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Magdalena-768x753.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Rookie_Magdalena.png 779w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Name:</strong> Magdalena Georgieva<br />
<strong>Where to find her:</strong> <a href="https://twitter.com/mgieva" target="_blank">@mgieva</a><br />
<strong>Current company:</strong> HubSpot<br />
<strong># years as a PM:</strong> “just over 3”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Explain your problem with “the problem.” </strong><br />
I started at HubSpot on the marketing team, so I wasn’t a product manager by training, if there is such a thing. I started out as an associate product manager, which was a pilot program for something that is now pretty established. So I was picking up a lot of product management on the job.</p>
<blockquote><p>Over time, I’ve realized that product management is basically <strong>the art of asking questions</strong>. It’s very much like journalism, where you have to ask a lot of open-ended questions and investigate.</p></blockquote>
<p>But at the beginning, I ended up being convinced of a specific solution pretty early on. I thought I had the imagination for what the solution would look like, and how it should look. A specific example: we were thinking about how our forms tool should evolve. There were a lot of good ideas, but I was getting married to the solution early on. And I did a bit of design myself, which is not bad—I think a product manager should have knowledge of how design comes together. But sometimes that behaviour affected the developers and the team. They started relying on me for not just the problem and requirements, but also, “What is the solution going to be?”</p>
<p><strong>How did you change your approach?</strong><br />
One of the things that our then-Chief Product Officer mentioned was to stop spending that much time in Trello or whatever product management tool you’re using. I think we were giving way too much detail and obsessing over how something is going to be done, as opposed to talking to customers or analyzing the data. So that led me to think, “Okay, why am I using these tools? Is it appropriate usage?” And then being more careful and selective with that.</p>
<p>And then the other thing was asking more questions. Over time, I’ve realized that product management is basically the art of asking questions. It’s very much like journalism, where you have to ask a lot of open-ended questions and investigate. And oftentimes the deeper you dig, the more you find. So if you’re willing to get on the phone with customers and find out what exactly is happening and educate your team, that can be really successful.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>We want to help alleviate rookie mistakes, so here are <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=rookiemistakes" target="_blank">20+ customizable templates</a> to kickstart your roadmap. It&#8217;s the least we can do here at Roadmunk.</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-mistakes/">5 product managers share their rookie mistakes</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to ace your roadmap presentation</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/roadmap-presentation/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 15:35:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presentations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product roadmap presentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product roadmaps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product strategy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmap presentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmapping]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1311</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Your roadmap is just words on a page (or screen or whiteboard or wall) until it’s been validated in some form of roadmap presentation or meeting. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/roadmap-presentation/">How to ace your roadmap presentation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Roadmapping doesn’t end once you’ve built your product roadmap. The purpose of your roadmap is to <strong>visualize a transparent plan across your organization</strong>. To ensure your roadmap is effective (and actually, you know, <strong><em>executed</em></strong>), you’ll need to align each team in a roadmap presentation.</p>
<p>Basically, your roadmap is just words on a page (or screen or whiteboard or wall) until it’s been validated in some form of roadmap presentation or meeting. During a well-executed roadmap presentation, you have the chance to show stakeholders that you understand their motivations—and they have a chance to publicly affirm their alignment. But if your presentation flops, so might your product strategy.</p>
<h1>What is a roadmap presentation?</h1>
<p>The <strong>most important point</strong> to remember before your roadmap presentation: <strong>this is <em>not</em> the place to get buy-in for your plans</strong>. That might seem contradictory. (After all, we just described roadmap presentations as an opportunity for stakeholders to “publicly affirm their alignment.”) But it should be <strong>just that</strong>: an <em>affirmation</em> of alignment that was already established <em>prior</em> to the meeting.</p>
<p>(If you’re butting heads over the alignment process itself, we’ve previously written about <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/get-buy-in-for-your-product-roadmap-from-each-department/" target="_blank">how to get roadmap buy-in from each department</a>. And, more specifically, <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/managing-executives-roadmapping-process/" target="_blank">how to get buy-in from executives</a>.)</p>
<p>A roadmap presentation is far more than the words you actually say. <strong>Think of it as an alignment exercise whose success depends on what happens before, during and after you take the stage.</strong> This is an essential chance to <strong>understand stakeholder motivations</strong> and <strong>forge consensus</strong> before moving forward with your plans.</p>
<p>To get nuts-and-bolts-y, we’ve found that roadmap presentations generally fall into one of two categories:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Short-term updates:</strong> Taking place <strong>weekly</strong> or <strong>biweekly</strong>, these frequent syncs tend to get in the weeds, covering the particularities of what’s getting built and how that affects other departments. This type of sit-down would be more common on smaller teams. And because these catch-ups happen regularly, formal buy-in before the presentation is not imperative. But the roadmap still needs to be communicated prior to the meeting to avoid any major surprises or backlash.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Long-term updates:</strong> For bigger organizations and teams, the roadmap presentation will likely happen <strong>monthly</strong>, <strong>bimonthly</strong> or even <strong>quarterly</strong>. For these conversations, buy-in before the meeting is critical. These meetings can often involve high-stakes projects that rely on massive alignment and dependencies. Show up to your presentation without everyone on board, and you’ll probably leave feeling pretty beat-up.</li>
</ul>
<p><img class="wp-image-1338 size-thumbnail aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Divider_prep-150x150.png" alt="Divider_prep" width="150" height="150" /></p>
<h1>Before your roadmap presentation: how to prepare</h1>
<p>When it comes to roadmap presentations, the pre-game is just as important as the main event. There are 5 areas you should learn inside-out to ensure a productive meeting:</p>
<p><strong>Know the high-level strategy.</strong><br />
So you’re going to build feature X, Y and Z—but what’s the big-picture goal those features address? Without being able to speak to the <strong>high-level strategy</strong>—and the <strong>tradeoffs</strong> that must be made to <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-prioritization-techniques/" target="_blank">prioritize within that strategy</a>—everyone will just start asking for whatever is most advantageous to <em>them</em>. Be able to speak to <strong>product vision</strong><em> and</em> <strong>company vision</strong>—and how your roadmap aligns with both targets.</p>
<p><strong>Know the business model.</strong><br />
This goes deeper than just knowing the product goals and company vision. As a product manager, you’re facilitating <strong>revenue growth</strong>. You should be able to articulate how your roadmap will increase ARR or ACV (or your acronym of choice), create demand, and help you hit (or exceed) sales forecasts. Not only does this tie your roadmap to the hard realities of your business&#8230; it will help you win your sales team’s heart.</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><strong>Know your customers.</strong><br />
Qualitative data can be just as important as numbers. Before any roadmap presentation, make sure you’ve spoken to (at least) a handful of key customers, and can relay their views. This is essential for building trust that your roadmap is grounded in the <strong>real-life needs of the market</strong>—not just projections in a spreadsheet.</p>
<p><strong>Know the stakeholders.</strong><br />
We mean <em>actually</em> get to know them: their <strong>motivations</strong>, their <strong>deadlines</strong>, their <strong>pressures</strong>, what’s keeping them up at night. <strong>Again, trust is crucial.</strong> Marketing and sales needs to feel that product decisions are sound—otherwise they might go rogue. This won’t happen overnight. But it’s important to invest the time.</p>
<p><strong>Know the resource constraints.</strong><br />
One of the most common (inevitable?) pushbacks you’re going to get is related to<em> time</em>.<strong> “Why can’t we move faster?”</strong> To counter this complaint, it’s absolutely crucial that you have an inside-out knowledge of your resources at any given time. You must be able to clearly articulate the resources required to execute a given task—and the tradeoffs that will be made if you swap in something else. It can also be useful to discuss historical timelines, reminding the room of how long things have taken in the past.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1340 size-thumbnail" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Divider_what-to-show-150x150.png" alt="Divider_what to show" width="150" height="150" /></p>
<h1>During your roadmap presentation: What to actually present</h1>
<p>As we’ve discussed, <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/create-product-roadmap/" target="_blank">there’s no<strong> one</strong> way to slice your roadmap</a>. So what should you actually show during your roadmap presentation?</p>
<p>We can’t tell you exactly how to build a roadmap that suits your particular organization or product (that&#8217;s where our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=presentation" target="_blank">template library</a> comes in handy), but we do recommend that you aim to meet at least a few of the following criteria:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Flexibility:</strong> Does your roadmap distinguish between what’s <strong>planned</strong> and what’s still <strong>TBD</strong>?</li>
<li><strong>Personalization:</strong> Does it address the individual needs of each department and/or stakeholder?</li>
<li><strong>Collaboration:</strong> Can you iterate on the roadmap <em>during the presentation itself</em>?</li>
<li><strong>Clarity + Attractiveness:</strong> Does it look good? Is the plan visualized in a clear manner? Don’t underestimate the power of good design.</li>
</ol>
<p>Below, we’ve included some options for structuring your roadmap for your presentation. With a <a href="https://roadmunk.com/">dedicated roadmapping tool like Roadmunk</a>, you can easily create and present multiple pivots of the same data. For these examples, we used our <strong>C-Level Roadmap Template</strong>, <a href="http://support.roadmunk.com/Roadmap-Templates">available here.</a></p>
<h2>1) Flexibility</h2>
<p>Many product managers find it helpful to communicate which initiatives are actually in the pipeline, and which are still subject to change. One of our favourite ways to structure a roadmap is to organize items by <strong>In Progress</strong>, <strong>Scheduled</strong> and <strong>Proposed</strong>. If your organization works on a timeline, you can simply colour code the items on your roadmap.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone wp-image-1312 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.35.49-PM.png" alt="Timeline flexible roadmap presentation" width="1147" height="630" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.35.49-PM.png 1147w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.35.49-PM-300x165.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.35.49-PM-768x422.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.35.49-PM-1024x562.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1147px) 100vw, 1147px" /></p>
<p>If your organization prefers to avoid timelines, you could also create a <strong>Swimlane View</strong> with the headers <strong>In Progress</strong>, <strong>Scheduled</strong> or <strong>Proposed</strong>.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1314" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Flexible_swimlane-276x300.png" alt="Flexible swimlane roadmap presentation" width="550" height="599" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Flexible_swimlane-276x300.png 276w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Flexible_swimlane.png 686w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></p>
<p>We’ve found this roadmap structure very effective for reducing backlash during a roadmap presentation. Stakeholders get a clear and immediate visual indication of which features are <strong>actually committed</strong>, and which are <strong>still being decided</strong>. Overall, it means you’re less likely to hear knee-jerk peanut gallery protestations.</p>
<h2>2) Personalization</h2>
<p>As we mentioned above, it can also be effective to visualize ownership during your roadmap presentation. A great way to do this is to organize your roadmap by department or even by the individual responsible for each task.</p>
<p>The roadmap below includes the same data as the roadmaps above, but we’ve included subheaders indicating individual ownership over each project.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone wp-image-1320 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.47.45-PM.png" alt="Screen Shot 2016-11-02 at 5.47.45 PM" width="1289" height="749" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.47.45-PM.png 1289w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.47.45-PM-300x174.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.47.45-PM-768x446.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.47.45-PM-1024x595.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1289px) 100vw, 1289px" /></p>
<p>If you really want to get granular with ownership, you could create a <strong>Swimlane View</strong> roadmap that highlights department, resource or individual owner. This puts the focus on who’s doing what for which department—not the timeline.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1322" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.48.58-PM-300x212.png" alt="Swimlane ownership roadmap presentation" width="600" height="425" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.48.58-PM-300x212.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.48.58-PM-768x543.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.48.58-PM.png 886w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></p>
<h2>3) Collaboration</h2>
<p>There’s a reason why the sticky-notes-on-a-wall method is such an enduring way to make a roadmap: it’s easy to change things up on the fly. Although you’d ideally have buy-in for your roadmap before the presentation, your meeting will go much smoother if you are also able to update your roadmap during the conversation.</p>
<p>With a tool like Roadmunk, you can easily add comments or adjust your roadmap directly within the app during the meeting. This makes for a much more dynamic and participatory presentation.</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-1331 size-full aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Roadmap-gif2_-optimized-1.gif" alt="Roadmap gif2_ optimized" width="443" height="245" /></p>
<h2>4) Clarity + Attractiveness</h2>
<p>The core purpose of your roadmap is to visualize your strategy and make it crystal-clear to everyone in your organization. “Make something pretty!” may sound trite, but you’ll undermine your end-goal if your roadmap is unattractive or unclear.</p>
<p>Obviously, the content of your roadmap is more important than the appearance of your roadmap. But it will be a lot easier to highlight key information—no matter how complicated—if your visualization is easy on the eyes. Also recommended: custom branding.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1326 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.58.38-PM.png" alt="Screen Shot 2016-11-02 at 5.58.38 PM" width="1370" height="730" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.58.38-PM.png 1370w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.58.38-PM-300x160.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.58.38-PM-768x409.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-02-at-5.58.38-PM-1024x546.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1370px) 100vw, 1370px" /></p>
<h1>What pushback should you prep for?</h1>
<p>No matter how much you prepare, there are some common points of friction that come up again and again in roadmap meetings. A great way to ace your presentation: prepare for the pushback before it starts pushing. Here are some common questions to expect.</p>
<p><strong>“Are you actually going to achieve this timeline?”</strong><br />
You’ll most frequently hear this from sales or execs. They want to confirm that your roadmap is realistic so they can plan accordingly. If you have a history of late delivery, be prepared to address why <strong><em>this time</em></strong> will be different. (Then make sure your deliver.)</p>
<p><strong>“How can we scope this down?”</strong><br />
Just because stakeholders are skeptical that you can hit your deadlines doesn’t mean they don’t want things to go faster. One way to ship features quicker: scope them down. Especially at startups, executives might push the “M” in MSP when they see scope creep getting out of hand. Be prepared to answer why you’ve scoped each feature to its current specs—and be flexible when it’s possible to scope things down.</p>
<p><strong>“What’s the value of this roadmap?”</strong><br />
Don’t just speak to the qualitative value of each new feature. Be prepared with hard numbers. How will this roadmap help achieve your revenue targets? What specific clients or market segment does it address? You should be able to tie items on your roadmap to specific dollar-sign potential, and articulate value vs. effort. (<a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-prioritization-techniques/">More on that here.</a>)</p>
<p><strong>“What are the maintenance costs going to be?”</strong><br />
The cost of maintenance is one of the things most commonly neglected on the roadmap—<a href="http://firstround.com/review/The-one-cost-engineers-and-product-managers-dont-consider/">even though it’s one of the most important and resource-draining aspects of any organization.</a> Expect more technically inclined team members to pipe up with maintenance questions, or simply visualize maintenance initiatives directly on your roadmap.</p>
<p><strong>“Where are the risks or dependencies?”</strong><br />
Sure, the roadmap looks great.. But what factors that could derail its execution? What risks does each stakeholder need to be aware of, and how will that affect their department’s ability to reach their targets? Also, what steps can stakeholders take to pitch in and mitigate those dangers? The more honest you are about the realities facing your roadmap, the more likely you’ll build trust—and get buy-in for your plan.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1341 size-thumbnail" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Divider_rm-done-150x150.png" alt="Divider_rm done" width="150" height="150" /></p>
<h1>What happens after the presentation?</h1>
<p>Alignment is a continuous process. <strong>It doesn’t just end when your meeting is finished.</strong> Make sure you follow up your roadmap presentation with thorough meeting notes and the updated roadmap. (Check out <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/writing-for-product-strategy-alignment/" target="_blank">our recent interview</a> with <strong>Ellen Chisa</strong>, <strong>VP of Product at Lola</strong>, for some tips on writing kickass meeting notes and sync emails.) Create a concrete space—whether it’s within an email, a shared document, or your roadmap itself—where stakeholders can share feedback.</p>
<h1>Reminder! The #1 way to fail your roadmap presentation</h1>
<p>Don’t forget that the fastest way to fail your roadmap presentation is to <strong>not talk to anyone beforehand</strong>. Your presentation is <em>all about alignment</em>. Set the tone <em>before</em> your presentation by talking to—and, more importantly <em>listening to</em>—each stakeholder.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/roadmap-presentation/">How to ace your roadmap presentation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Managing executives in the roadmapping process</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/managing-executives-roadmapping-process/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 17:04:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[executives]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product roadmaps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[products]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmapping process]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1196</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p> The goal of the roadmapping process isn’t to present a perfect plan that everyone immediately loves. Getting feedback—even negative feedback—is the goal.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/managing-executives-roadmapping-process/">Managing executives in the roadmapping process</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>“I spend all this time working on my roadmap, then it gets picked apart. How can I wrangle execs in the roadmapping process?”</p>
<p>It’s one of the questions we hear most often from product managers when it comes to roadmapping. The product manager has one plan—executives see things differently. They butt heads, tweak plans, shift priorities, and ultimately who knows if the right thing gets built. Or gets built well. It’s not only frustrating, it can hurt both the success of the product and the product manager’s career.</p>
<p>Roadmunk’s CEO, <a href="https://twitter.com/LatifNanji" target="_blank">Latif</a>, learned this lesson the hard way. About two years into his PM career, he was given the opportunity to start creating and managing his own roadmap. Latif is currently on vacation in Portugal (which is not relevant to this blog post, but we’re jealous?), so he emailed his story:</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-1232 size-large aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Managing-execs_email-1-1024x397.png" alt="Managing execs_email" width="640" height="248" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Managing-execs_email-1-1024x397.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Managing-execs_email-1-300x116.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Managing-execs_email-1-768x298.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Managing-execs_email-1.png 1342w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></p>
<p>Latif failed to understand the importance of executive feedback to the roadmapping process. He was used to dealing with devs, product managers and customers—so that’s who he spoke to. But product managers need to be horizontal across an <em>entire organization</em>. And they need to understand the business side as much as the technical side. Which means getting buy-in from those at the top of <em>every</em> department.</p>
<p>The process isn’t easy. We previously wrote about <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/get-buy-in-for-your-product-roadmap-from-each-department/">getting buy-in for your roadmap from each department</a>, but we wanted to delve deeper into <strong>executive</strong> buy-in, since it can be particularly challenging. Here’s a quick survival guide for your next exec meeting.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="alignnone wp-image-1239 size-thumbnail" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Managing-execs_dividers-1-150x150.png" alt="Managing execs_dividers 1" width="150" height="150" /></p>
<h1>Pushback isn’t a bad thing</h1>
<p>Reminder to PMs: It can be frustrating when your airtight roadmap gets punctured by an exec. But the goal of the roadmapping process isn’t to present a perfect plan that everyone immediately loves. Getting feedback—even negative feedback—<em>is</em> the goal. The purpose of presenting your roadmap, then iterating (and iterating again) is to get everyone on the same page. It’s about managing and aligning expectations. Yes, the snags can be frustrating. But if no one is criticizing, no one is listening. Think of it as a opportunity to fill gaps in your knowledge about the other departments you work with.</p>
<h1>Before showing your roadmap to an exec…</h1>
<p>There’s no point in showing your roadmap to an executive until you have a shared understanding of where you want the roadmap to take you. Generally, this means that everyone in the room understands:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Company vision:</strong> What’s the longterm goal of the company? Is it to grow as big as possible, or is it to get acquired? Are you after exponential growth or a more gradual trajectory? Have there been significant changes in company vision lately? These are the types of questions that should be understood <em>before</em> the roadmap meeting.</li>
<li><strong>Product strategy:</strong> What problem does your product solve for? <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/create-product-roadmap/">At what stage of the chasm</a> are you currently operating? What’s your plan of attack or differentiation in the market? Is your goal to have <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/valleyvoices/2015/07/17/every-startups-go-to-market-strategy-has-to-answer-the-100-million-question/#ae42112523ff">10 customers paying $1,000,000 per year, or 1,000,000 customers paying $10 per year?</a> These questions will heavily impact what’s on your product roadmap.</li>
<li><strong>Prioritization method:</strong> How do you prioritize? Having an established prioritization method, and being transparent about that method, is essential when explaining how you built your roadmap in the first place. (And if you don’t know where to start, our friend <a href="https://twitter.com/listentodaniel">Daniel Zacarias</a> wrote <a href="http://foldingburritos.com/product-prioritization-techniques/">an epic post on prioritization over at his site, Folding Burritos</a>.)</li>
</ul>
<p>Each of these points is a blog post unto itself, so we’re not going to get into too much detail here. (The purpose of <em>this</em> post is to discuss what happens when you show the first iteration of your roadmap to an exec.) Just keep in mind that you’ll need a strong sense of these three items to productively communicate with an executive.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="alignnone wp-image-1241 size-thumbnail" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Managing-execs_dividers-2-150x150.png" alt="Managing execs_dividers 2" width="150" height="150" /></p>
<h1>Know your audience</h1>
<p>Speaking of executives, remember that they are not all clones of each other. The CEO does not have the same concerns as the CPO, who does not have the same priorities as the CMO. Yes, you’re all working towards the same company vision—but you’re each chipping away at different areas of that vision. Your roadmap discussion should be tailored to the specialization of whichever exec happens to be in the room with you.</p>
<p>Here are a few things to keep in mind when addressing a few different types of execs:</p>
<p><strong>The CEO:</strong> Especially at startups, the CEO tends to be pretty hands-on with the product roadmap. CEOs think high-level and inter-departmental. They’re not just going to want to see what features you’re adding, but rather how the evolution of the product will touch the other teams and grow the business. They also want to understand risk and internal efficiencies (or inefficiencies).</p>
<p><strong>The sales exec:</strong> Sales tends to be more timeline-focused. And they have lots of competing demands. Come prepared to show what they’ll be able to offer customers, how you arrived at that decision (including any tradeoffs that were made), and how you&#8217;re allocating resources (in case they make demands). Especially if you’re a new PM, be sure to unearth any promises sales has made to customers—that’s one of the main reasons roadmaps get bumped off course.</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><strong>The marketing exec:</strong> They don’t need to know every detail of how a feature is going to get built, but they do need to know the stories they can tell. As best you can, flag what’s coming up in the long-term so they can prepare.</p>
<p><strong>The product exec:</strong> Roadmapping is always about getting feedback, but that’s especially relevant when the exec is a fellow product manager. Here’s where you can really get in the weeds on your market. Explain what direction your market is going, and how your roadmap builds a competitive advantage.</p>
<p>Along with not<em> telling</em> each exec the same thing, you also don’t have to <em>show</em> them the same thing. We recommend tailoring your roadmap to its specific audience. For example, your complete product roadmap might look something like this when plotted on a timeline:</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-1235 size-full aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/managing-execs-in-the-roadmapping-process_roadmap1.png" alt="managing execs in the roadmapping process_roadmap1" width="1135" height="653" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/managing-execs-in-the-roadmapping-process_roadmap1.png 1135w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/managing-execs-in-the-roadmapping-process_roadmap1-300x173.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/managing-execs-in-the-roadmapping-process_roadmap1-768x442.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/managing-execs-in-the-roadmapping-process_roadmap1-1024x589.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1135px) 100vw, 1135px" /></p>
<p>However, when showing your roadmap to an exec in marketing or sales, you could show the same data plotted according to what&#8217;s <strong>in progress</strong>, <strong>in design</strong> or <strong>in the backlog</strong>. This is a simple framework that can go a long way when it comes to managing expectations.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1237" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/managing-execs-in-the-roadmapping-process_roadmap2-272x300.png" alt="managing execs in the roadmapping process_roadmap2" width="640" height="705" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/managing-execs-in-the-roadmapping-process_roadmap2-272x300.png 272w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/managing-execs-in-the-roadmapping-process_roadmap2.png 672w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></p>
<p>Regardless of how you build or format your specific roadmap, remember: tailor it to your specific audience. Our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=execs" target="_blank">template library</a> can help with creating the right roadmap for the right audience.</p>
<h1>Common reasons for pushback</h1>
<p>Why would an executive question your roadmap? A good way to prevent pushback: be prepared for some of the obvious points of contention.</p>
<p><strong>1. They don’t think the roadmap is aggressive enough.</strong> Is that all? Shouldn’t you be able to complete, oh, at least three more features this quarter? Obviously, everyone wants more and they want it last week. Executives are highly incentivized to over-deliver—and they won’t be timid about asking for “extra.”</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Quick tip:</strong> Be very transparent about resourcing. Explain how your available manpower will be used to execute each item on your roadmap. In fact, show resources right on your roadmap. Also, show history. Remind them how long past features took to execute, and how the new items will compare.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2. They think the roadmap is too aggressive (i.e. unrealistic).</strong> One thing you don’t want to do: over-promise and under-deliver. If an exec sees a roadmap that just isn’t doable, they are likely to push back. Especially if sales will be sharing their roadmap with clients.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Quick tip:</strong> This is most commonly a problem for more junior PMs who don’t yet understand the cadence of their team. Take the feedback, apply it&#8230; and learn for next time.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>3. They have their own agenda.</strong> Remember Latif’s story? He didn’t communicate with sales, and it turned out they had made a major promise to a customer that was not accounted for in the product roadmap. He was blindsided—then scrambling to catch up.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Quick tip:</strong> Long before you present your roadmap to an exec, make sure you know if they have any unspoken-for priorities. That way these items can be properly assessed and prioritized, without derailing your plans.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>4. They don’t understand the technical side.</strong> This often goes hand-in-hand with #1. A non-technical executive might look at your roadmap and wonder: why is everything taking so long? Do we really need that many resources allocated to technical maintenance and debt?</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Quick tip:</strong> From Day 1, explain the process. The explain it again. If an executive doesn’t have a technical background, they probably have never been exposed to the huge amount of resources that must go into simply maintaining a system. Remember, <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/how-non-technical-product-managers-can-jump-the-skills-gap/">product managers are translators</a>: it&#8217;s your job to interpret your roadmap for each department.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>5. They want to see more of the big picture.</strong> Really early products can get away with a roadmap that’s just a list of features. But once your product begins to mature, you’re going to have to account for other departments, dependencies and risks, and be able to position your roadmap within the wider market. If an exec doesn’t see this on the roadmap, they’ll probably ask about it.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Quick tip:</strong> Check yourself on granularity. Yes, you need to know every detail about how a feature will be built. But does the executive? Be able to explain your roadmap not just in terms of how/why you prioritized the way you did, but how this will lead to your specific goals within your specific market.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>6. They’re jerks:</strong> Sometimes people just suck. It wouldn’t be the first time an executive was confrontational or egocentric. It can be very challenging when someone pushes back on your roadmap because they just, well, want to be difficult.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Quick tip:</strong> Fight aggression with questions. Ask what they would like to be different. This doesn’t mean saying yes, but make yourself open to the conversation—then explain the tradeoffs if you execute “their” way.</li>
</ul>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="alignnone wp-image-1242 size-thumbnail" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Managing-execs_dividers-3-150x150.png" alt="Managing execs_dividers 3" width="150" height="150" /></p>
<h1>A few more things to keep in mind</h1>
<p>Seasoned product managers are <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/what-makes-a-good-product-manager/">world-class communicators</a>. But it takes work to get there. Here are a few key points to keep in mind when presenting your product roadmap to an executive.</p>
<p><strong>Know your market better than anyone else.</strong> At least, that’s the goal. Executives will often “win” a roadmapping debate because they have been in the business longer and simply know the landscape better. Your goal: learn everything you don’t know, everything they know, and more. Talk to more customers than them, keep tabs on your competitors more closely than them, and be the expert on your market.</p>
<p><strong>Be radically transparent.</strong> Don’t just show your roadmap. Explain how you got there. Resourcing, risk and prioritization should all be crystal clear. Then you’ll be able to show how all the pieces will move if anything changes.</p>
<p><strong>Show tradeoffs.</strong> When a change to your roadmap is suggested, make sure you articulate the tradeoffs. Sure, we could do X—but we’d have to sacrifice Y. What will the domino effect be from that? Be open to any change—but make sure you articulate the full picture of the consequences.</p>
<p><strong>Remind them of history.</strong> Not sure how long something will take? Look backwards. Due to the cost of maintaining your existing tech, features often take longer to build over time, not faster. Come to the conversation with both a strong sense of where you’re going, and knowledge of your past.</p>
<p><strong>Tailor what you show.</strong> Not all execs are the same. And they shouldn’t all see the same version of your roadmap. To ensure a successful roadmapping process, show each stakeholder the information that best applies to them.</p>
<p><strong>Remember: feedback isn&#8217;t a bad thing!</strong> Feedback is what you<em> want</em> as a PM. If you’re not getting feedback (even bad feedback), no one is listening.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/managing-executives-roadmapping-process/">Managing executives in the roadmapping process</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>50 product management blogs you should be reading</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-blogs/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2016 19:02:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eleni Deacon]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management blogs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management resources]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management writing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product strategy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1131</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Regardless of whether you’re a newbie PM or a veteran in your field, there are tons of product management blogs worth checking out. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-blogs/">50 product management blogs you should be reading</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Regardless of whether you’re a newbie PM or a veteran in your field, there are tons of product management blogs worth checking out. Getting ready for your first PM interview</span>? There’s a blog for that. Need a detailed how-to on some obscure product challenge? There’s a blog for that. Just feeling kind of “stuck” today? There are definitely <em>many</em> blogs for that.</p>
<p>One of the really awesome things about the PM community is the degree to which knowledge-sharing has become second-nature. So we decided to compile our favorite product management blogs. Note: this is <em>not</em> a complete list. There are some great sites we ended up having to leave on the table—at least for now. We’re planning to update this list soon, so let us know if we forgot an essential entry!</p>
<p>To help parse the sheer volume of PM writing out there, we’ve organized this list into 8 categories:</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="#classics">The Classics</a></li>
<li><a href="#communities">The Communities</a></li>
<li><a href="#influencers">The Influencers</a></li>
<li><a href="#educators">The Educators</a></li>
<li><a href="#medium">Best of Medium</a></li>
<li><a href="#design">Design &amp; UX</a></li>
<li><a href="#startups">For Startups</a></li>
<li><a href="#misc">Misc. but not least</a></li>
</ol>
<p>Obviously, there is overlap between these buckets. Most influencers are educators, and most of our favourite Medium writers are definitely influencers, as well. These categories are intended as a loose guide, not pigeonholes.</p>
<h1><img class="alignnone wp-image-1154" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/classics_icon-1.png" alt="classics_icon" width="100" height="116" /></h1>
<h1 id="classics">The Classics</h1>
<p><strong>1. <a href="http://pragmaticmarketing.com/resources/blogs" target="_blank">Pragmatic Marketing</a></strong><br />
Our own CEO, <a href="https://twitter.com/LatifNanji" target="_blank">Latif</a>, often credits Pragmatic Marketing for getting him up to speed during his early years in product. They actually have <a href="http://pragmaticmarketing.com/resources/blogs" target="_blank">five different product management blogs</a>, each hosted on their own domain. But beyond their designated “blog” content, the site includes <a href="http://pragmaticmarketing.com/resources" target="_blank">pretty much every other type of resource</a> for product managers. Infographics! Webinars! A magazine! They do everything.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first: </strong><a href="http://pragmaticmarketing.com/resources/A-Product-Managers-Worst-Nightmare" target="_blank">A product manager&#8217;s worst nightmare</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2. <a href="http://www.mindtheproduct.com/" target="_blank">Mind the Product</a></strong><br />
You’ve been to <a href="http://www.mindtheproduct.com/meetups/" target="_blank">the meetups</a>. <a href="http://mtpcon.com/" target="_blank">The conference</a> is in your calendar. Now read the <a href="http://www.mindtheproduct.com/" target="_blank">dang blog already</a>! Could MTP be the mother of all product management sites? They feature writing from some of the most interesting and insightful people in the business. Must-read stuff.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.mindtheproduct.com/2015/10/history-evolution-product-management/" target="_blank">The history and evolution of product management</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>3. <a href="https://280group.com/" target="_blank">280 Group</a></strong><br />
280 Group is there for you when you want to beef up on product strategy—or when you need a pep talk. This training and consulting firm is one of the most established (and prolific) hubs for PM content.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://280group.com/product-management-blog/coping-product-manager-burnout/" target="_blank">Coping with product manager burnout</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>4. <a href="https://www.siriusdecisions.com/Blog" target="_blank">Sirius Decisions</a></strong><br />
Home to product management heavyweight <a href="http://Jeff Lash" target="_blank">Jeff Lash</a> (more on him in the <a href="#influencers">Influencers</a> section), Sirius Decisions is a global B2B advisory firm. Their blog is a serious informational resource covering a broad range of relevant topics—from meat-and-potatoes product advice to marketing and sales.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://www.siriusdecisions.com/Blog/2014/Jan/What-You-Need-to-Know-About-Aligning-Innovation-With-Strategy" target="_blank">What you need to know about aligning innovation with strategy</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>5. <a href="http://svpg.com/" target="_blank">Silicon Valley Product Group</a></strong><br />
This no-frills website features product advice from Silicon Valley coach <a href="https://twitter.com/cagan" target="_blank">Marty Cagan</a>, whose former gigs include eBay, AOL, Netscape and HP. Cagan’s writing is both helpful and personal. He offers insider advice gained from his deep roots in the Valley’s tech community.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://svpg.com/product-success/" target="_blank">Product Success</a></li>
</ul>
<h1><img class="alignnone wp-image-1157" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/communities_icon-1.png" alt="communities_icon" width="100" height="119" /></h1>
<h1 id="communities">The Communities</h1>
<p><strong>6. <a href="https://www.productmanagerhq.com/" target="_blank">Product Manager HQ</a></strong><br />
This is one of our favorite PM resources. The world’s largest Slack product community, PMHQ often hosts AMAs with leading product managers. Their site also includes articles and guest posts on career development. TL;DR: Go here to get hired/inspired.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://www.productmanagerhq.com/2016/03/19-lessons-i-learned-during-my-first-year-as-a-product-manager/" target="_blank">19 lessons I learned during my first year as a product manager</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>7. <a href="http://www.productmanagerclub.com/" target="_blank">Product Club</a></strong><br />
This content hub, led by “product hustler” (and bulldog lover) <a href="https://twitter.com/timothydplatt" target="_blank">Tim Platt</a>, offers real talk for peers. Posts like <a href="http://www.productmanagerclub.com/2016/05/21/stop-improving-your-product/" target="_blank">“Stop Improving Your Product”</a> and <a href="http://www.productmanagerclub.com/2016/05/19/cut-the-crap-and-build-with-empathy/" target="_blank">“Cut the Crap and Build with Empathy”</a> exemplify their no-nonsense approach to product advice.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.productmanagerclub.com/2016/05/11/average-manager-vs-great-manager/" target="_blank">Average manager vs. great manager</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>8. <a href="https://productcoalition.com/" target="_blank">Product Coalition</a></strong><br />
Medium has become such a popular outlet for product managers that we’re dedicating <a href="#medium">an entire section of this roundup to Medium all-stars</a>. But if you don’t have the bandwidth for yet <em>another</em> online community, just visit Product Coalition. Run by <a href="https://twitter.com/jaystansell" target="_blank">Jay Stansell</a>, this publication aggregates awesome product writing from around Medium. And they have a <a href="http://productcoalitionslack.herokuapp.com/" target="_blank">Slack community</a>, too.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://productcoalition.com/the-four-villains-of-product-management-361cf61ef3c6" target="_blank">The four villains of product management</a></li>
</ul>
<h1><img class="alignnone wp-image-1164" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/companies_icon.png" alt="companies_icon" width="100" height="121" /></h1>
<h1>The Companies</h1>
<p><strong>9. <a href="http://firstround.com/review/" target="_blank">First Round Review</a></strong><br />
Learn from the smartest product managers at the coolest companies. First Round Review specializes in long-form interviews with superstar PMs. Like <a href="http://firstround.com/review/the-power-of-the-elastic-product-team-airbnbs-first-pm-on-how-to-build-your-own/" target="_blank">Airbnb’s Jonathan Golden</a>. And <a href="http://firstround.com/review/to-build-great-products-build-this-strong-scalable-system-first/" target="_blank">Reddit’s co-VPs of product Alex Le and Kavin Stewart</a>. And <a href="http://firstround.com/review/harnessing-happiness-to-build-your-career-advice-from-an-uber-product-leader/" target="_blank">Uber’s Frederique Dame</a>. And, and, and&#8230;</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://firstround.com/review/slacks-first-product-manager-on-how-to-make-a-firehose-of-feedback-useful/" target="_blank">Slack&#8217;s first product manager on how to make a firehose of feedback useful</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>10. <a href="https://blog.intercom.com/" target="_blank">Inside Intercom</a></strong><br />
We’re a little obsessed with Intercom’s intelligent, highly opinionated approach to product management content. They don’t do the usual “how to” schtick. They’ve got smart people on staff with ideas to share. Extra points for their gorgeous illustration.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://blog.intercom.com/first-rule-prioritization-no-snacking/" target="_blank">The first rule of prioritization: No snacking</a></li>
</ul>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p><strong>11. <a href="http://blog.invisionapp.com/" target="_blank">InVision</a></strong><br />
Design conundrum? InVision has you covered, whether you’re looking for tactical tips or more, er, existential guidance. A LOT of design challenges are political—and InVision gets that. They write extensively on psychology, productivity and <a href="http://blog.invisionapp.com/dealing-with-ux-disagreements/" target="_blank">dealing with disagreements</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://blog.invisionapp.com/statistics-on-user-experience/" target="_blank">13 impressive statistics on user experience</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>12. <a href="http://www.freshtilledsoil.com/blog/" target="_blank">Fresh Tilled Soil</a></strong><br />
This Boston-based product and UX firm writes a consistently engaging product management blog covering the intricacies of strategy, design and productivity. You can also <a href="https://medium.com/fresh-tilled-soil" target="_blank">follow them on Medium</a>, if that’s how you roll. In short: a lovely, helpful read.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.freshtilledsoil.com/onboarding-experience-is-everything/" target="_blank">Onboarding: experience is everything</a></li>
</ul>
<h1><img class="alignnone wp-image-1165" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/influencers_icon.png" alt="influencers_icon" width="100" height="118" /></h1>
<h1 id="influencers">The Influencers</h1>
<p><strong>13. <a href="https://www.kennorton.com/" target="_blank">Ken Norton</a></strong><br />
Wait, what? You DON’T subscribe to <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/5-new-product-management-newsletters-worthy-of-your-inbox/" target="_blank">Ken Norton’s weekly newsletter</a>? Please correct that. Then get caught up by reading his site. A Google Ventures Partner, <a href="https://twitter.com/kennethn" target="_blank">Ken Norton</a> is one of the most creative and encouraging thought leaders in the field.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://www.kennorton.com/essays/meetings-that-dont-suck.html" target="_blank">Meetings that don’t suck</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>14. <a href="http://www.nirandfar.com/" target="_blank">Nir and Far</a></strong><br />
Attn: armchair psychologists (and regular-chair product managers). Author <a href="https://twitter.com/nireyal" target="_blank">Nir Eyal</a> is essential reading for anyone interesting in user behavior and psychology. His popular book, <a href="http://www.nirandfar.com/hooked" target="_blank"><em>Hooked: How to Build Habit-Forming Products</em></a>, proposes a four-step process for building sticky products. Visit <a href="http://www.nirandfar.com/past-articles-and-resources" target="_blank">his archives</a> for a trove of insightful content.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.nirandfar.com/2016/03/hooked-good-habit-forming-products-improve-lives.html" target="_blank">Hooked for good: How habit-forming products improve lives</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>15. <a href="http://andrewchen.co/recent/" target="_blank">Andrew Chen</a></strong><br />
Uber’s <a href="https://twitter.com/andrewchen" target="_blank">Andrew Chen</a> delivers essays via his weekly(ish) newsletter, but you can also read his writing <a href="http://andrewchen.co/recent/" target="_blank">directly from his personal site</a>. According to his LinkedIn, Chen has written OVER 700 ESSAYS. So, a lot.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://andrewchen.co/breaking-down-671-million-push-notifications-by-hour/" target="_blank">What 671 million push notifications say about how people spend their day</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>16. <a href="https://medium.learningbyshipping.com/" target="_blank">Learning by Shipping</a></strong><br />
On his Medium-hosted publication, Andreesen Horowitz partner <a href="https://twitter.com/stevesi" target="_blank">Steven Sinofsky</a> delves into technology, productivity and the business side of product management. Also, <a href="https://medium.learningbyshipping.com/my-tablet-has-stickers-8f7ab9022ebd" target="_blank">why his tablet has stickers</a>. (Spoiler: They’re not just there for decoration.)</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://medium.learningbyshipping.com/disruptions-long-slow-complex-journey-c43872788423#.krclieqiu" target="_blank">Disruption’s long, slow, complex journey</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>17. <a href="https://medium.com/@joshelman" target="_blank">Josh Elman</a></strong><br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/joshelman" target="_blank">Josh Elman</a>’s resume almost reads like a parody of a dream PM resume: it’s got Twitter, Facebook AND LinkedIn. These days, Elman is a partner at <a href="https://www.google.ca/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiZi5Gni6HPAhWk7YMKHR6eCe4QFggeMAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.greylock.com%2F&amp;usg=AFQjCNGkwli7osHyk4374ZSsKKfAw_NFRA" target="_blank">Greylock Partners</a>. He blogs on Medium, naturally—it’s in Greylock’s portfolio.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://news.greylock.com/the-five-types-of-virality-8ba42051928d#.winklldh2" target="_blank">The five types of virality</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>18. <a href="http://www.bhorowitz.com/" target="_blank">Ben Horowitz</a></strong><br />
If you haven’t read Ben Horowitz’ classic piece <a href="http://a16z.com/2012/06/15/good-product-managerbad-product-manager/" target="_blank">Good Product Manager/Bad Product Manager</a>, then… well, you’re probably not even reading THIS piece because any human interested in product management would have read that first. Horowitz’ product management blog isn’t updated very frequently these days, but it’s got more than enough archive content to keep your eyeballs busy. Also: THE RAP LYRICS.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.bhorowitz.com/high-output-management" target="_blank">Andy</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>19. <a href="https://medium.com/@jasonfried" target="_blank">Jason Fried</a></strong><br />
Basecamp Founder &amp; CEO <a href="https://twitter.com/jasonfried" target="_blank">Jason Fried</a> draws on his extensive experience as an entrepreneur and product leader to deliver inspiring—and cliché-busting—ideas via his Medium account. The ideal PM pick-me-up.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://m.signalvnoise.com/ive-never-had-a-goal-c89219aedddf#.owcjf299m" target="_blank">I’ve never had a goal</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>20. <a href="https://medium.com/@rrhoover" target="_blank">Ryan Hoover</a></strong><br />
In recent years, <a href="https://www.producthunt.com/" target="_blank">Product Hunt</a> has emerged as a crucial source for intel on product trends, releases and quirky ephemera. Its founder, <a href="https://twitter.com/rrhoover" target="_blank">Ryan Hoover</a>, maintains a fun blog on Medium—just in case you didn’t get enough geek-out time on Product Hunt&#8217;s main site.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://medium.com/@rrhoover/a-dangerous-new-game-called-camera-rollette-2f89a9d5f4f1#.lp44wcgun" target="_blank">A dangerous new game called camera rollette</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>21. <a href="http://davidcancel.com/" target="_blank">David Cancel</a></strong><br />
Currently the CEO of <a href="http://www.drift.com">Drift</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/dcancel" target="_blank">David Cancel</a> has a long and impressive history as an entrepreneur and product leader. In short: he knows how to build and scale worthwhile products. Another thing he’s good at: sharing knowledge with others. (Bonus: you also might want to check out the <a href="http://blog.drift.com/" target="_blank">Drift blog</a> and the <a href="https://seekingwisdom.io/" target="_blank">Seeking Wisdom podcast</a>—we’re fans.)</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://davidcancel.com/customer-driven-product-machine" target="_blank">Creating a customer-driven product machine</a></li>
</ul>
<h1><img class="alignnone wp-image-1166" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/educators_icon.png" alt="educators_icon" width="100" height="117" /></h1>
<h1 id="educators">The Educators</h1>
<p><strong>22. <a href="http://www.romanpichler.com/" target="_blank">Roman Pichler</a></strong><br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/romanpichler" target="_blank">Roman Pichler</a> is definitely a fan favourite when it comes to product management learning. A product consultant, Pichler offers in-depth posts on some of the more complex product challenges, as well as leadership guidance for up-and-coming PMs. A must-have on any product management reading list.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.romanpichler.com/blog/scaling-the-product-owner/" target="_blank">How to scale the scrum product owner</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>23. <a href="http://www.producttalk.org/" target="_blank">Product Talk</a></strong><br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/ttorres" target="_blank">Teresa Torres</a> is one of the smartest people writing about product today. She publishes meaty, longform articles that explain, IN DETAIL, how product managers can revolutionize their work. Reading Torres, you get the sense that she cares deeply about her work.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.producttalk.org/2016/08/opportunity-solution-tree/" target="_blank">Why this opportunity solution tree is changing the way product teams work</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>24. <a href="http://foldingburritos.com/" target="_blank">Folding Burritos</a></strong><br />
Portugal-based product consultant <a href="https://twitter.com/listentodaniel" target="_blank">Daniel Zacarias</a> has mastered the quality vs. quantity conundrum. He doesn’t churn out volume, but rather attacks key product management topics in exhaustive detail. Really great for wrapping your head around dense—but important—PM concepts.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://foldingburritos.com/kano-model/" target="_blank">The complete guide to the Kano Model</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>25. <a href="https://under10consulting.com" target="_blank">Under 10 Consulting</a></strong><br />
Another veteran consultant, <a href="https://twitter.com/sjohnson717" target="_blank">Steve Johnson</a> publishes fun, thought-provoking posts via the blog for his firm, <a href="https://under10consulting.com" target="_blank">Under 10 Consulting</a>. Read it when you’re feeling burned out and need a quick hit of inspiration to get back on your game.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://under10consulting.com/articles/technical/" target="_blank">Do product managers need to be technical?</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>26. <a href="http://www.mironov.com/" target="_blank">Rich Mironov</a></strong><br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/RichMironov" target="_blank">Rich Mironov</a>’s product management blog is probably the most longstanding on our list: it started back in 2002. <em>Two thousand and two.</em> But even his earliest posts are still relevant, addressing topics like <a href="http://www.mironov.com/mo_beta/" target="_blank">recruiting beta customers</a> and <a href="http://www.mironov.com/secret_shopper/" target="_blank">the role of the &#8220;secret shopper.&#8221;</a></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.mironov.com/8mistakes/" target="_blank">Eight mistakes you’ll (probably) make in your first product management job</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>27. <a href="http://melissaperri.com/blog/#.V-P5wZMrJ-V" target="_blank">Melissa Perri</a></strong><br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/lissijean" target="_blank">Melissa Perri</a> does not whip off PM puff pieces. Her posts are in-depth and thought-provoking, tackling some of the most knotty product management challenges. Also, if you don’t already know about <a href="http://melissaperri.com/2014/08/05/the-build-trap/#.V-P6y5MrJ-U" target="_blank">the Build Trap</a>, you might be at risk of getting caught in it.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://melissaperri.com/2016/01/17/pmvsux/#.V-P6a5MrJ-U" target="_blank">Changing the conversation about product management vs. UX</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>28. <a href="http://pmhardcore.com/" target="_blank">Hardcore Product Management</a></strong><br />
“To handle complexity, you need preparation and the ability to respond with creativity.” This idea is at the heart of <a href="https://twitter.com/nilsie" target="_blank">Nils Davis</a>’ blog, which helps product managers find creative solutions to the difficult, messy, headache-inducing problems.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://pmhardcore.com/2016/09/02/toolset-creative-blocks-product-managers/" target="_blank">A toolset for getting unstuck when your creativity is blocked</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>29. <a href="http://www.goodproductmanager.com/" target="_blank">How to Be a Good Product Manager</a></strong><br />
Sirius Decisions’ <a href="https://twitter.com/jefflash" target="_blank">Jeff Lash</a> founded his blog wayyyyy back in 2006, and maintains it to this day. The archive includes thoughtful writing on pretty much all aspects of product management—but we’re especially fond of the posts about self-improvement.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.goodproductmanager.com/2008/11/10/reconsider-your-jack-of-all-trades-strategy/" target="_blank">Reconsider your jack-of-all-trades strategy</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>30. <a href="http://tynerblain.com/blog/2016/07/22/minimum-valuable-problem/" target="_blank">Tyner Blain</a></strong><br />
Product management veteran <a href="https://twitter.com/sehlhorst" target="_blank">Scott Sehlhorst</a> has been sharing ideas at <a href="http://tynerblain.com/blog/about/" target="_blank">Tyner Blain</a> for over a decade. He’s a trusted source for astute insights into some of the more complex dimensions of product management.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://tynerblain.com/blog/2016/04/12/product-owner-manager/" target="_blank">Product owner manager</a></li>
</ul>
<h1><img class="alignnone wp-image-1167" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/medium_icon.png" alt="medium_icon" width="100" height="118" /></h1>
<h1 id="medium">Best of Medium</h1>
<p><strong>31. <a href="https://medium.com/@BrandonMChu" target="_blank">Brandon Chu</a></strong><br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/brandonmchu" target="_blank">Brandon Chu</a> writes fun, personal posts based on his experiences working for companies like Shopify and Freshbooks. We really appreciate his frank tone and in-the-trenches anecdotes. Plus, he’s Canadian. <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.2.1/72x72/1f1e8-1f1e6.png" alt="🇨🇦" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://medium.com/the-black-box-of-product-management/a-bad-product-decision-340ee680fa0c" target="_blank">A bad product decision</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>32. <a href="https://medium.com/@ellenchisa" target="_blank">Ellen Chisa</a></strong><br />
We’re big <a href="https://twitter.com/ellenchisa" target="_blank">Ellen Chisa</a> fans around here. In fact, we recently interviewed her about <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/writing-for-product-strategy-alignment/" target="_blank">the role of writing in product management</a>. Ellen has gained a strong following for her insightful writing on some the challenges associated with working in both product and tech, including career frustration and issues of gender diversity.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://medium.com/@ellenchisa/networking-for-introverts-926489e34d2" target="_blank">Networking for introverts</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>33. <a href="https://medium.com/@lulu_cheng" target="_blank">Lulu Cheng</a></strong><br />
Pinterest’s <a href="https://twitter.com/lulu_cheng" target="_blank">Lulu Cheng</a> recently pivoted into product management from marketing, and has documented her transition. She’s probably been the most successful writer yet to tackle the perennial question: How technical does a product manager really need to be?</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://medium.com/@lulu_cheng/getting-to-technical-enough-as-a-product-manager-5b372513cd1c#.bcpa49b02" target="_blank">Getting to “technical enough” as a product manager</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>34. <a href="https://medium.com/@Bosefina" target="_blank">Bo Ren</a></strong><br />
Tumblr’s <a href="https://twitter.com/Bosefina" target="_blank">Bo Ren</a> uses Medium to chart her personal journey in product management—but with a caveat: <a href="https://medium.com/@Bosefina/from-liberal-arts-to-product-management-c4015edfb166#.d54iurybl" target="_blank">“This is not a how-to guide.”</a> Bo’s writing exemplifies a growing trend in the PM community. Often pointing a spotlight on issues of diversity, she doesn’t just talk about how to develop a PM skill set, but rather offers a series of essays and critiques on the field itself.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://medium.com/@Bosefina/confessions-of-a-pm-10-ways-to-disarm-the-impostor-syndrome-6219242a79bb#.wt8u79tvk" target="_blank">Confessions of a PM: 7 ways to disarm the impostor syndrome</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>35. <a href="https://medium.com/@mattlemay/latest" target="_blank">Matt LeMay</a></strong><br />
A big reason we like <a href="https://twitter.com/mattlemay" target="_blank">Matt LeMay</a>: he revamped that totally over-shared <a href="https://medium.com/on-human-centric-systems/a-new-skill-model-for-product-managers-71769a2de7b7#.dobt81dcq" target="_blank">product management Venn diagram</a>. Another reason: his blogs are fun to read and actually helpful. He doesn’t just talk about how to <em>be</em> a product manager, but how it <em>feels</em> to work in product.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://medium.com/on-human-centric-systems/against-self-deprecation-1d73bbe1dd96#.dr6mkcdvp" target="_blank">Against self-deprecation</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>36. <a href="https://medium.com/@jessratcliffe" target="_blank">Jess Ratcliffe</a></strong><br />
We like <a href="https://twitter.com/jessratcliffe" target="_blank">Jess Ratcliffe</a>’s product management blog so much, <a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/jessica-ratcliffe/" target="_blank">we interviewed her about it</a>. Each week, Jess grabs coffee with an awesome woman working in product, and publishes their conversation on Medium. A great way to (vicariously) get to know your product heroes.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://medium.com/coffee-with/coffee-with-merci-grace-b9f148185e19" target="_blank">Coffee with Merci Grace</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>37. <a href="https://medium.com/@johnpcutler" target="_blank">John Cutler</a></strong><br />
A prolific Medium contributor, <a href="https://twitter.com/johncutlefish" target="_blank">John Cutler</a> is an awesome source for fast tips and light-a-fire-under-your-ass inspiration. Oh, and he recently published <a href="https://medium.com/personal-growth/10-things-i-learned-by-doodling-for-100-days-straight-a802753c5a25#.va4j7iavp" target="_blank">amazing pictures of his 100-day doodle challenge</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first: </strong><a href="https://medium.com/@johnpcutler/how-to-tame-engineers-be-a-rockstar-and-ship-ing-product-f24f059d4a7#.93wa9w7cc" target="_blank">How To Tame Engineers, Be A Rockstar, and Ship ****ing Product</a></li>
</ul>
<h1><img class="alignnone wp-image-1168" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/design_icon.png" alt="design_icon" width="100" height="117" /></h1>
<h1 id="design">Design &amp; UX</h1>
<p><strong>38.<a href="https://medium.com/@joulee" target="_blank"> Julie Zhuo</a></strong><br />
Facebook product design VP <a href="https://twitter.com/joulee" target="_blank">Julie Zhuo</a> was named the #1 product management influencer in <a href="http://datastories.com/product-management-landscape-in-medium" target="_blank">NomNom and Data Stories recent analysis of PM content on Medium</a>. Not only is her writing extremely insightful, Julie herself just seems straight-up cool.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://medium.com/the-year-of-the-looking-glass/design-illustrated-in-3-charts-128ae8ff22fe#.lgbl3r1xx" target="_blank">Design, illustrated in 3 charts</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>39. <a href="http://www.usersknow.com/blog/" target="_blank">Users Know</a></strong><br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/lauraklein" target="_blank">Laura Klein</a> has made it her mission to help startups master UX. Her recent book, <a href="http://www.usersknow.com/books/" target="_blank"><em>UX for Lean Startups</em></a>, gives startup product leaders the tools to connect with their users. Prefer a shorter read? Her blog is a great source for user-focused research and ideas.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.usersknow.com/blog/2016/7/28/the-right-deliverables" target="_blank">The right deliverables</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>40. <a href="http://www.useronboard.com/" target="_blank">UserOnboard</a></strong><br />
UserOnboard is like Pop-Up Video for the app age. In his signature “<a href="http://www.useronboard.com/onboarding-teardowns/" target="_blank">teardowns</a>,” Portland-based designer <a href="https://twitter.com/samuelhulick" target="_blank">Samuel Hulick</a> walks readers through the onboarding process for various apps, dishing out sassy commentary along the way. Helpful UX lessons PLUS comedy. Can we be his friend?</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.useronboard.com/how-kimoji-onboards-new-users/" target="_blank">How Kimoji onboards new users</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>41. <a href="http://www.cindyalvarez.com/" target="_blank">Cindy Alvarez</a></strong><br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/cindyalvarez" target="_blank">Cindy Alvarez</a> is a longtime leader in user experience and customer development. Director of UX at Yammer, she blogs about nurturing customers, honing communication, and product design. She has also tackled issues surrounding workplace culture—including the less-fun parts.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.cindyalvarez.com/lean/5-ways-to-ensure-usability-testing-results-arent-ignored" target="_blank">5 ways to ensure usability testing results aren’t ignored</a></li>
</ul>
<p><img class="alignnone wp-image-1169" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/startup_icons.png" alt="startup_icons" width="100" height="119" /></p>
<h1 id="startups">For Startups</h1>
<p><strong>42. <a href="https://hunterwalk.com/" target="_blank">Hunter Walk</a></strong><br />
A partner at <a href="https://twitter.com/homebrew" target="_blank">Homebrew</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hunterwalk" target="_blank">Hunter Walk</a> focuses on growing startups—and their products. His hugely popular product management blog is part tech criticism, part knowledge-sharing, plus interviews with super-smart people working in PM.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://hunterwalk.com/2016/09/03/google-finds-that-successful-teams-are-about-norms-not-just-smarts/" target="_blank">Google finds that successful teams are about norms not just smarts</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>43. <a href="https://steveblank.com/" target="_blank">Steve Blank</a></strong><br />
Steve Blank&#8217;s 2005 book, <a href="https://www.amazon.ca/Four-Steps-Epiphany-Successful-Strategies/dp/0989200507" target="_blank"><em>The Four Steps to the Epiphany: Successful Strategies for Products that Win</em></a>, lay the groundwork for how we see and engage customer development today. On his blog, Blank continues to write about customer-driven entrepreneurship and disrupting big companies.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://steveblank.com/2016/02/23/the-mission-model-canvas-an-adapted-business-model-canvas-for-mission-driven-organizations/" target="_blank">The mission model canvas – an adapted business model canvas for mission-driven organizations</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>44. <a href="http://www.startuplessonslearned.com/" target="_blank">Startup Lessons Learned</a></strong><br />
If you’re in product at a startup and you haven’t read <a href="https://twitter.com/ericries" target="_blank">Eric Ries</a>’ hugely influential 2011 book <a href="http://theleanstartup.com/book" target="_blank"><em>The Lean Startup</em></a>, don’t bother reading ANY of these blogs until you have. After that, spend some time on Startup Lessons Learned, Ries’ ongoing blog.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.startuplessonslearned.com/2015/11/how-lean-startup-helped-serve.html" target="_blank">How lean startup helped serve communities in Kenya</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>45. <a href="http://ben-evans.com/" target="_blank">Benedict Evans</a></strong><br />
Another Andreessen Horowitz partner, <a href="https://twitter.com/BenedictEvans" target="_blank">Benedict Evans</a> mixes tech commentary with entrepreneurial advice on his fun blog. Less tactical, his writing examines major tech trends and how they fit into the startup/business landscape.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://ben-evans.com/benedictevans/2015/11/7/mobile-ecosystems-and-the-death-of-pcs" target="_blank">Mobile, ecosystems and the death of PCs</a></li>
</ul>
<h1><img class="alignnone wp-image-1170" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/misc_icon.png" alt="misc_icon" width="100" height="128" /></h1>
<h1 id="misc">Misc. but not least</h1>
<p><strong>46. <a href="http://www.sachinrekhi.com/" target="_blank">Sachin Rekhi</a></strong><br />
What’s great about so many product management blogs is that they’re not self-promotional—it’s really all about knowledge-sharing. <a href="https://twitter.com/sachinrekhi" target="_blank">Sachin Rekhi</a> exemplifies that attitude. In his essays (which he also delivers via a weekly newsletter), he shares ideas and observations from over a decade working as a PM in Silicon Valley.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.sachinrekhi.com/product-management-career-ladders-at-8-top-technology-firms" target="_blank">Product management career ladders at 8 top technology firms</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>47. <a href="https://tpgblog.com/" target="_blank">The Product Guy</a></strong><br />
Product manager and <a href="https://twitter.com/theproductguy" target="_blank">friendly floating head Jeremy Horn</a> has been writing The Product Guy blog since 2007. One of its most fun features: <a href="https://tpgblog.com/tbpp/" target="_blank">The Best Product Person</a> (TBPP for short), an annual competition “honoring excellence in product management.”</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://tpgblog.com/2016/01/25/becoming-a-truly-customer-centric-product-manager-with-the-job-to-be-done-framework/" target="_blank">Becoming a truly customer-centric product manager with the &#8220;jobs to be done&#8221; framework</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>48. <a href="http://christophercummings.com/" target="_blank">Product Management Meets Pop Culture</a></strong><br />
Boston-based product manager <a href="https://twitter.com/chriscummings01" target="_blank">Christopher Cummings</a> uses analogies to Pokémon, Batman, and a range of fun pop culture touchpoints to explore important (and sometimes complicated) PM topics. A must-read for comic-book fans. A fun read for everyone.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://christophercummings.com/2016/07/11/pokemon-go-a-mobile-product-managers-perspective/" target="_blank">Pokémon Go: A Mobile Product Manager’s Perspective</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>49. <a href="https://pmblog.quora.com/" target="_blank">The Art of Product Management</a></strong><br />
Asana PM <a href="https://twitter.com/jackiebo" target="_blank">Jackie Bavaro</a> doesn’t just use Quora to answer questions—it’s where she hosts her insightful blog, The Art of Product Management. Her posts are encouraging, detailed, and introvert-friendly.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="https://pmblog.quora.com/3-Easy-Exercises-to-Improve-Your-Customer-Focus" target="_blank">3 easy exercises to improve your customer focus</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>50. <a href="http://www.cleverpm.com/" target="_blank">The Clever PM</a></strong><br />
The Clever PM is the anonymous advice column for the product management world. Written by a mysterious, <a href="https://twitter.com/thecleverpm" target="_blank">Seattle-based product manager</a> (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ctgilley">Cliff Gilley</a> in real life—according to LinkedIn), the site provides handy tips and inspiration for fellow product managers.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Read this first:</strong> <a href="http://www.cleverpm.com/2016/06/23/just-because-youre-delighted-by-your-product-doesnt-mean-your-users-are/" target="_blank">Just because you’re delighted by your product doesn’t mean your users are!</a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p><em>Don&#8217;t just read about product management, put it into practice! Visit our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=pmblogs" target="_blank">template library</a> today to get started on your product roadmaps. </em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-blogs/">50 product management blogs you should be reading</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
