<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Latif Nanji &#8211; Roadmunk Blog</title>
	<atom:link href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/author/latifnanji/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog</link>
	<description>Product Management and Product Roadmaps</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 19:44:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.7.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/favicon.png</url>
	<title>Latif Nanji &#8211; Roadmunk Blog</title>
	<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>How to meet a technical co-founder</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/technical-co-founder/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 18:18:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Latif Nanji]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[co-founder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[entrepreneur]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[entrepreneurship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[growth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmunk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[startup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[startup culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technical co-founder]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2080</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>There are many paths to finding a technical co-founder, none of which are easy. And none of which are quick. Here are some steps for finding the right person for the job. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/technical-co-founder/">How to meet a technical co-founder</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s probably the most common question I hear from young entrepreneurs. They’re looking for that elusive developer who doesn’t just know how to scale a code base—they can also scale a team. All while balancing the business priorities. </span></p>
<p><strong>So how did I find my co-founder Tomas? </strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Finding a technical co-founder was not easy. Not only do you have to share ideas about how to grow a company, you also need to agree on what you want from </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">your particular </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">company. Do you want the pressures (and potential payoffs) of venture funding, or would you prefer to build a lifestyle business? What kind of culture do you want to create? What’s the end-game? Those are deep questions that relate to your <strong>values</strong>, <strong>life stage</strong>, and <strong>prior experience</strong>. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So here goes. My thoughts on finding a technical co-founder.</span></p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<h1>Step 1: Learn the language</h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you move to Spain and want to make friendly with the locals, what’s the very first thing you need to know? Spanish. Otherwise, they won&#8217;t understand a thing you’re saying. Likewise, <strong>a developer speaks a different language from you</strong>. They use words like EC2, client and server, iterations, ruby on rails and refactoring. You use words like product discovery, revenue, inbound generation and pricing strategy.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Now you want to get married for the next 7 years and make an exit of $1 billion? Comprendo? No entiendo. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Learning their language isn’t hard, but it’s not something you can do in an hour. I don&#8217;t mean look these words up on Google. I mean really know them. Spend a few months in your evenings learning how to code. You will get to know the basics, but more importantly appreciate what a developer does. I spent five years in product management, which gave me a shoe in the door and <strong>a lot of empathy</strong> <strong>for the development process</strong>.</span></p>
<p><center><img class="alignnone wp-image-2128" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Latif.gif" alt="Technical co-founder - Latif GIF" width="350" height="232" /><img class="alignnone wp-image-2117" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Tomas.gif" alt="Technical co-founder - Tomas GIF" width="350" height="233" /></center></p>
<h1>Step 2: Errr, dating?</h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Great, you&#8217;ve now missed a bunch of weekend socials because you were trying to hit level 3 on </span><a href="https://www.codecademy.com/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">code academy</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">At this moment of time you realized you (and me!) picked the wrong degree in university. Oops. If you&#8217;re lucky enough to still be in school, stop reading this and find the class schedule for computer science. Go and meet people and start making friends. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But what if you&#8217;re past that phase in life?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You might find yourself on co-founder dating sites. I will save you the trouble: <strong>it’s a big waste of time</strong>. I interviewed over 50 developers, whether it was online or in person, and none of them had put in the time to understand what a startup </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">actually</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> involves in terms of the dedication and hard work required over the course of 7 to 10 years. Most were also very green when it came to coding and building a product company.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>The only way to know their true colors is to actually start working together.</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=The%20only%20way%20to%20know%20their%20true%20colors%20is%20to%20actually%20start%20working%20together.&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2080' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Next you might try going to local networking events. I recommend </span><a href="https://www.nextcanada.com/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Next36</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, where they curate a list of potential founders and matches based on preferences. Many successful startups have been born out of this organization. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So get your idea out. <strong>Tell people about your challenges</strong> <strong>and see if they can connect you with someone they recommend</strong>. Heck, build a small demo and show it off to developers. (You did finish level 3, right?) This will show them you understand code and that there are fun technical challenges ahead. That’s what they want to work on. Give them a little rope to pull on. Now you’ve got the ball rolling.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-2158 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Technical_co-founder-Tomas_working.jpg" alt="Technical co-founder - Tomas working" width="1500" height="1000" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Technical_co-founder-Tomas_working.jpg 1500w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Technical_co-founder-Tomas_working-300x200.jpg 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Technical_co-founder-Tomas_working-768x512.jpg 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Technical_co-founder-Tomas_working-1024x683.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1500px) 100vw, 1500px" /></p>
<h1>Step 3: Sure, “date” one!</h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">At this point your </span><a href="https://www.google.ca/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjoiYzcyJXTAhWk5IMKHbKwDgsQFggdMAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.paulgraham.com%2Frelres.html&amp;usg=AFQjCNFqFcBqwIbEGxsvlRIxAUOXNgU7MQ&amp;bvm=bv.152174688,d.amc" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">relentless resourcefulness</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> should start paying off. You’ll find yourself having intellectual conversations with developers and motivating them towards a project you’ve been stewing on. (If you can’t get to this step, perhaps this isn’t the road for you.)</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Before getting overly excited, here is a short and brutally honest list of things to find out early on. Keep in mind you&#8217;re effectively looking to “marry” this person for the years to come. </span></p>
<ol>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Do they want to earn a salary or are they <strong>willing to work for free</strong> <strong>for a period of time</strong>?</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Do you share a worldview when it comes to <strong>work ethic</strong>? If you want to go all-in on business, while they want to start a family, how will that jive?</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Are they <strong>able to move</strong> if you got into an incubator for 3 months?</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Are they <strong>excellent communicators</strong>? (They need to manage a huge team when your idea scales.) </span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Do they have a sense of <strong>design</strong>? (Ask them what websites and products they admire from a UX/UI perspective.)</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Do they understand <strong>agile development</strong>?</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Can they manage all aspects of the <strong>tech infrastructure</strong> early on?</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> What are their <strong>values</strong> and <strong>ambitions</strong>?</span></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lastly, are they <strong>reliable</strong>? This is by far the most important one. They may </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">seem</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> perfect, but the only way to know their true colors is to actually start working together.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>The best technical co-founder is a friend you have had a relationship with for some time</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=The%20best%20technical%20co-founder%20is%20a%20friend%20you%20have%20had%20a%20relationship%20with%20for%20some%20time&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=2080' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So how do you mitigate the risk that they’ll build your code base then run off to Australia because the surf waves are looking mighty high? You do a pilot project with them. Something that shows you can stick out a few weeks of late nights with mac and cheese (sharp cheddar flavor). After that, build your flagship product. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In many cases, it doesn&#8217;t work out with a particular developer. That’s when a lot of people end up giving up on entrepreneurship altogether. <strong>The cycle of finding and working with a developer can take months</strong>. And when it crashes and burns, it fucking sucks.</span></p>
<h1>So what’s the best way?</h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It&#8217;s rather obvious. In my opinion, <strong>the best technical co-founder is a friend you&#8217;ve had a relationship with for some time and worked on a project with</strong>. Heck, it doesn&#8217;t even have to be software-related.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I met Tomas in November 2008 when we were early-stage employees at a startup called </span><a href="https://miovision.com/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Miovision</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. We sat next to each other, and before long we were automating complex financial revenue recognition workflows and onboarding sales and marketing into an ERP that we championed. Between him and Colin (another engineer who now works at Roadmunk), I learned </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">so much. </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">I was incredibly hungry to understand how engineering teams think about problems, operate their teams, and scale software. Over countless projects, <strong>we built a mutual respect and enjoyment for solving problems together</strong>. It was on that foundation that we launched Roadmunk (btw, check out our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=technicalcofounder" target="_blank">template library</a> if you haven&#8217;t already!).   </span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-2137 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Latif-Tomas-Co-founders.gif" alt="Technical co-founder - Latif and Tomas GIF" width="480" height="320" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The main reason Tomas wanted to do a startup with me came from our working experience together. We could build and launch FAST. We also shared wisdom from our domains of expertise which made it even more fun. So we knew it was our time. </span></p>
<h1>No silver bullet (as Tomas would say)</h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are many paths to finding a technical co-founder, none of which are easy. And none of which are quick.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Finding a job in product management or at a software startup, building relationships with developers (and learning from them), applying to programs that connect smart people—these initiatives all take a serious commitment, focus, investment in learning, and perseverance. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Because Tomas and I worked together at a previous company, it may have looked like I “stole” him. The truth is that as startups turn into real businesses, early-stage employees want to go back to the start. <strong>Young startups are all about speed, control and luck</strong>—it’s exhilarating. And it’s why we try so damn hard to find that right person to build a business with.</span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/technical-co-founder/">How to meet a technical co-founder</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Are product roadmaps counterintuitive to agile?</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-roadmaps-counterintuitive-to-agile/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2017 19:35:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Latif Nanji]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[agile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[agile product roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[agile roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[roadmapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[what is an agile product roadmap]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1779</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Why a product roadmap fits nicely into agile environments—and how to create one.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-roadmaps-counterintuitive-to-agile/">Are product roadmaps counterintuitive to agile?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As the founder of a company that creates a tool </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">specifically</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for roadmapping, I’m very familiar with the mixed opinions surrounding agile product roadmaps. As a methodology, agile says: forget about planning on timelines—they’re unhelpful and hard to meet. On the other hand, roadmaps help you visualize your plans, often on a timeline. <strong>So is the idea of an agile product roadmap counterintuitive? </strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Let’s take a look at the facts. Agile is used as a term to indicate that teams are very flexible and willing to change their plans on a daily or weekly basis. </span><b>That means your project deadlines and dates are pretty insignificant.</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Yeah, you can add dates to your plans, but if you’re being truly agile (i.e. flexible) expect those dates to change.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Meanwhile, a roadmap usually asks: “Where the heck are we going to be in x amount of time?” </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/create-product-roadmap/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">As we’ve written about before</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, <strong>not everyone roadmaps along a timeline.</strong> But a roadmap almost always looks to the future beyond the day-to-day and week-to-week, even if you’re not visually presenting a timeline. A roadmap is a communication tool for aligning your teams, departments and company, so it will usually function on a</span><b> longer-term view beyond short-term cycles</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br />
</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>A roadmap is a statement of intent. Not a literal roadmap.</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=A%20roadmap%20is%20a%20statement%20of%20intent.%20Not%20a%20literal%20roadmap.&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1779' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So you’ve got one concept (agile) that sheds the constraints of time and another (roadmapping) that can often seem inherently time-based. Seems pretty counterintuitive. </span><b>But I’m going to have to respectfully disagree. </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">An agile product roadmap </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">is</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> a valuable tool and quite frankly, the concept of roadmapping fits rather nicely in an agile environment. Here are some reasons why a roadmap <em>does</em> work for agile—and why you should be creating one.</span></p>
<p><img class="wp-image-1832 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-2-300x23.png" width="400" height="30" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-2-300x23.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-2-768x58.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-2-1024x77.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-2.png 1515w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why roadmaps are NOT counterintuitive to agile</span></h1>
<p>If we look at the defining characteristics of both agile and roadmapping, as well as the <strong>realities of the real world</strong>, the concepts actually fit nicely together. Here&#8217;s why.</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">1. Roadmaps change as often as the agile world</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While there’s this basic understanding of agile, at the end of the day, it’s an umbrella term. You’ve got your scrum shops, your extreme programming teams, your kanban processes and so on. They all fall under “agile.” Each of these methodologies have their own nuances and ways of operating, but ultimately they all share a few major themes:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">You’re operating in short cycles.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Change comes quickly, so you </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">always </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">have to be prepared for it. </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">There is a ton of feedback because you’re operating in cycles that include checkpoints for evaluating your work.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These themes are all rooted in the core idea that when functioning in agile </span><b>you must be flexible</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Adaptability is the key to thriving in agile because you’re always being thrown something new, whether it’s a new cycle, fresh feedback, or the introduction of a competitor to the market.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>Just as agile functions on transparency, roadmaps create transparency.</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=Just%20as%20agile%20functions%20on%20transparency%2C%20roadmaps%20create%20transparency.&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1779' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As we’ve stressed many, </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">many</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> times before </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/what-is-a-product-roadmap/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">a roadmap is a statement of intent</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s not a literal roadmap</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Your roadmap should not be an amalgamation of hard deadlines that </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">must be met</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. It should be an incremental plan that openly embraces change. Nobody has ever created a roadmap that they’ve followed through-and-through. </span><b>Plans can and will alter, and as a result so will your roadmap. </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This flexibility of a roadmap (i.e. statement of intent) pairs extremely well with the very nature of agile methodologies. Roadmaps change frequently, allowing them to easily fit into agile settings—which also get reoriented often.</span></p>
<p><img class="wp-image-1831 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-1-300x23.png" width="399" height="30" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-1-300x23.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-1-768x58.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-1-1024x77.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-1.png 1515w" sizes="(max-width: 399px) 100vw, 399px" /></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">2. Roadmapping and agile both cut the bullshit</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Agile is all about the hard truth—whether you like it or not. Agile methodologies provide realistic versions of how projects are going to play out. If that means a project is going off the rails, you’re told straight up it’s going off the rails. This transparency is part of the reason agile has picked up so much steam: it cuts the bullshit about what can or cannot be delivered. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Just as agile settings function on transparency, </span><b>roadmaps create transparency</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">. You build a roadmap to be clear with anyone interested in knowing where the hell you’re going. It’s a communication asset designed specifically to align various parties on the what, when and how of your project. And when that plan changes, you present a shiny, updated version. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A roadmap’s function (<strong>showing transparency</strong>) directly ties into one of the major motivations of adopting an agile methodology (<strong>operating with transparency</strong>). They’re not in conflict; they fit nicely together.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1833" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-3-300x23.png" width="399" height="30" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-3-300x23.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-3-768x58.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-3-1024x77.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-3.png 1515w" sizes="(max-width: 399px) 100vw, 399px" /></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">3. You can’t escape long-term planning</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the things I’ve noticed when speaking to PMs from different companies is that many of those who claim to be operating in agile environments actually aren’t. Okay, they are operating in </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">some</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> form of agile, but there are still waterfall elements mixed in—so it’s not </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">purely </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">agile. The reason: <strong>as your company grows, the harder it gets to ignore long-term planning</strong>. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A lot of startups have successfully adopted an agile mentality that dismisses long-term timelines. But as these companies expand, their stakeholders increase, budgets change, sales targets differ and the need to communicate with more people arises. PMs start juggling </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">way</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> more variables which means there needs to be a <strong>deeper degree of planning</strong>.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>As your company grows, it gets harder to ignore long-term planning.</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=As%20your%20company%20grows%2C%20it%20gets%20harder%20to%20ignore%20long-term%20planning.&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1779' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Your dev and product teams may be operating in a super-speedy cyclic fashion, but the rest of the growing company is probably not. <strong>The rest of those stakeholders don’t give a damn about this day-to-day or week-to-week psychology.</strong> They want longer-term visions to plan out hiring, budgeting, resource allocation and more. A roadmap comes into play to address these <strong>long-term goals</strong>. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Like I mentioned, roadmaps often look beyond a short-term cycle even if they&#8217;re not plotted along a timeline. A roadmap is your opportunity to let stakeholders know how you plan on <strong>supporting your daily or weekly operations as the company evolves</strong>. You get to say, “Look, we have a plan for this company growth we’re experiencing. This is how we foresee the business evolving to support the daily/weekly tactics for building a better product.” A roadmap helps tackle the pressures of planning that inevitably creep up on your growing company.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1834" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-4-300x24.png" width="395" height="31" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-4-300x24.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-4-768x60.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-4-1024x80.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-4.png 1515w" sizes="(max-width: 395px) 100vw, 395px" /></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">What does an agile product roadmap look like?</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are many different ways to structure an agile product roadmap. But having spoken to countless product managers, I’ve noticed a few trends. Here are a few quick agile product roadmap examples. (You can find and customize all these examples in our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates/agile-roadmap?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=counterintuitive" target="_blank">template library</a>.) </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Swimlane-style roadmaps are especially effective for agile PMs.</strong> For the teams operating in pure agile (i.e. the ones that aren’t concerned with </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">any </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">dates), it’s common to organize a roadmap by theme. This means the headers might relate to different areas of product development.</span></p>
<h3 id="theme" style="text-align: center;">Theme-Based Roadmap</h3>
<p><img class="alignnone wp-image-1829 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Theme-View.png" alt="theme-based agile product roadmap" width="1173" height="646" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Theme-View.png 1173w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Theme-View-300x165.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Theme-View-768x423.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Theme-View-1024x564.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1173px) 100vw, 1173px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you work in a more structured agile environment, another option is to structure your roadmap by cycle or sprint—and not link those sprints to specific dates.</span></p>
<h3 id="sprint" style="text-align: center;">Sprint Roadmap</h3>
<p><img class="alignnone wp-image-1828 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Sprint-View.png" alt="spring agile product roadmap" width="1180" height="838" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Sprint-View.png 1180w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Sprint-View-300x213.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Sprint-View-768x545.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Sprint-View-1024x727.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1180px) 100vw, 1180px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many agile teams also organize their roadmaps according to “fuzzy time.” This means that rather than stating explicit dates, their roadmap might include loose time buckets like </span><b>In Progress</b>,<span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><b>Future </b>and <strong>Completed</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">. (</span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/create-product-roadmap/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">See here</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for an example that takes this structure one step further, inserting loose dates by month or quarter.)</span></p>
<h3 id="fuzzytime" style="text-align: center;">Fuzzy Time Roadmap</h3>
<p><img class="alignnone wp-image-1826 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Fuzzy-Time-View-1.png" alt="fuzzy time agile product roadmap" width="964" height="841" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Fuzzy-Time-View-1.png 964w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Fuzzy-Time-View-1-300x262.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Fuzzy-Time-View-1-768x670.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 964px) 100vw, 964px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And if you’re an agile-</span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">ish</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> team that’s still incorporating waterfall elements, your roadmap tends to have dates </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">with a caveat</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Your dates closer to the present tend to be more granular, whereas the further along you go the more abstract (i.e. fuzzy) the time headers become. It wouldn’t be agile if the dates were the be-all-end-all.</span></p>
<h3 id="agileish" style="text-align: center;">Agile-ish Roadmap</h3>
<p><img class="alignnone wp-image-1824 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Agileish-View-1.png" alt="quarterly agile product roadmap" width="1196" height="849" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Agileish-View-1.png 1196w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Agileish-View-1-300x213.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Agileish-View-1-768x545.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Agileish-View-1-1024x727.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1196px) 100vw, 1196px" /></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why you need a roadmap, </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">especially</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for your agile environment</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I’ve debunked the argument that roadmaps don’t <strong><em>belong</em></strong> in agile environments, but why do you actually <strong><em>need</em></strong> one? Some thoughts for the not-yet-convinced:</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">1. Align better with your &#8220;makers&#8221;</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When you say you’re operating in agile, you’re most likely referring to your team of &#8220;</span><a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">makers</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.&#8221; These are your <strong>developers</strong>, <strong>product team</strong> and <strong>designers</strong>—the ones who put your product together piece-by-piece. Long-term plans are not a pressing priority for a maker. They’re dedicating big chunks of their workday to building, usually along short(er) delivery cycles. This means they&#8217;re more concerned with what they can accomplish in the next hour, day or week than long-term horizon.</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>An agile roadmap better aligns your makers with teams that are working along different timelines.</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=An%20agile%20roadmap%20better%20aligns%20your%20makers%20with%20teams%20that%20are%20working%20along%20different%20timelines.&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1779' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">By presenting an agile product roadmap, you signal to your makers that you understand how they function. You’re committing to short-term priorities, but also pointing out that the future is “fuzzy.” It will be much easier to align with your makers if you position your roadmap as </span><b>a living document that aligns short-term priorities and embraces the future’s unpredictability.</b></p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1831 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-1-300x23.png" alt="" width="300" height="23" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-1-300x23.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-1-768x58.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-1-1024x77.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-1.png 1515w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">2. More cohesion across your company</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While your makers are embodying agile principles, other departments and teams are probably not. Your sales team is working in lengthy sales cycles, your marketing team is concerned about your next release, your customer success team has quarterly goals to hit. <strong>You’ve got this mishmash of timeframes across the company.</strong> And guess who has to align these different psychologies of time? You got it—the PM! (Yay…)</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">An agile product roadmap better aligns your makers with teams that are working along different timelines. Teams working under more traditional time constraints may have a lot of questions for the teams that are operating in agile. “Why isn’t this done?” “When should we expect this?” “Where is my release?!” Having a roadmap adapted for the agile environment </span><b>communicates realistic goals to internal stakeholders</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> that may be prying for answers.   </span></p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1833 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-3-300x23.png" alt="" width="300" height="23" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-3-300x23.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-3-768x58.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-3-1024x77.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-3.png 1515w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">3. Managing ALL the expectations </span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I think one of the main fears PMs have about roadmapping is that it’ll be a plan they’ll be held to—particularly by internal and external stakeholders. That’s why we constantly push the &#8220;<a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/what-is-a-product-roadmap/" target="_blank">statement of intent</a>&#8221; definition for roadmaps. But even then, we understand some people will always choose to take things </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">too</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> literally. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">That’s the beauty of the agile product roadmap—</span><b>it gives a PM more flexibility</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Not only does it encompass the intent of a typical roadmap, it also captures the flexibility of the agile methodology. A PM can whip out their roadmap and set expectations more easily. “This isn’t set in stone and it will probably change, but it’s what we’re proposing.”</span></p>
<blockquote><hr /><p><em>The key is to treat your roadmap as a living document that can and will change.</em><br /><a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=The%20key%20is%20to%20treat%20your%20roadmap%20as%20a%20living%20document%20that%20can%20and%20will%20change.&amp;via=RoadmunkApp&amp;related=RoadmunkApp&amp;url=https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1779' target='_blank' class='bctt-ctt-btn'></a><br /><hr /></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With this baseline understanding established from the start, PMs’ lives are made a hell of a lot easier in the long run. When those unavoidable changes start to happen and the PM is forced to make a tough decision, people will cause less of a fuss because, well, <strong>their expectations were managed at the start</strong>. This reduces the amount of conflict that can come down the pipeline and prepares team members for periods of change.</span></p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1834 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-4-300x24.png" alt="" width="300" height="24" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-4-300x24.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-4-768x60.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-4-1024x80.png 1024w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/agile-dividers-4.png 1515w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Remember: Your agile product roadmap is still a statement of intent</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Most companies nowadays are operating in some form of agile, whether it’s a purely agile structure or a hybrid of agile principles. Whatever your agile style, a roadmap has solid benefits that fit really nicely into any agile environment. The key is to treat your roadmap as <strong>a living document that can and will change</strong>. In short: a statement of intent.</span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-roadmaps-counterintuitive-to-agile/">Are product roadmaps counterintuitive to agile?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>7 essential design principles for product managers</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-design-principles/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 16:48:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Latif Nanji]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Product Strategy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product designer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product manager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product managers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[product strategy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ui]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[user experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[user interface]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ux]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=1597</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Design is a specialized skill, and as a product manager, it can be intimidating—especially if it’s not your forté. These are seven essential design principles that every PM should internalize and evangelize to make design a priority. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-design-principles/">7 essential design principles for product managers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><b>About 50% of all design firms sold in the last ten years were acquired in the last 24 months.</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> And they weren’t bought by Amazon or Facebook or Google. They were bought by the banks and consulting firms—the BIG financial institutions. These organizations don’t have the most innovative reputations (after all, they’re referred to as “</span><a href="http://www.ondigitalmarketing.com/learn/odm/foundations/5-customer-segments-technology-adoption/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">laggards</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">”), so when even </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">these companies</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> are adopting design firms it says something drastic. It says: </span><b>design should be a product priority.</b></p>
<blockquote><p>Design is a specialized skill, and as a PM, it can be intimidating—especially if it’s not your natural inclination.</p></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Having spent most of my career as a product manager, I’ve stated clearly—and to a lot of pushback—that </span><b>design should always be a priority for product managers</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Design is a specialized skill, and as a PM, it can be intimidating—especially if it’s not your natural inclination. (Plus, there’s usually a design team to deal with that stuff, right?) But that mentality is a missed opportunity; it’s equally important for PMs to keep design top-of-mind when making decisions. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Product design was one of our key differentiators when we founded Roadmunk. </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/poker-product-management/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">As I’ve previously written about</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, we didn’t necessarily have the data to back up that decision at the time. But look at these new statistics and tell me design isn’t rising in importance.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1642 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Design_blog-Metrics.png" alt="Product management design statistics" width="717" height="771" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Design_blog-Metrics.png 717w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Design_blog-Metrics-279x300.png 279w" sizes="(max-width: 717px) 100vw, 717px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The laggards are waking up and savvy PMs are </span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/8-product-managers-share-trends-goals-2017/#matt" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">talking about how crucial design has become to the product development process</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Now it’s time to integrate some concrete methods for bringing design more deeply into the PM process.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are </span><b>seven product design principles that I believe all product managers should follow</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Blending my first-hand experience and observations, these are the essential design principles that I think </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">every </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">product manager must internalize and evangelize—especially if design is not your forté.</span></p>
<h1>1. Tell users what to think</h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This first principle is an </span><a href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/don-t-make-me-think-key-learning-points-for-ux-design-for-the-web" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">evolutionary design concept from engineer Steve Krug</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. It states that when designing, </span><b>we should listen to our users’ needs to the point that </b><b><i>we know and tell them what they should be thinking</i></b><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Basically,</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">you should understand your users’ workflow so much so that you can determine what they’re attempting to do. (Like an *actually* perceptive fortune teller!) </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This example might help you visualize what I mean. Below, you’ll see flight search engine </span><a href="https://www.kayak.com" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kayak</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. It’s really well-designed, simple and easy to use. The problem, though: </span><b>I’m not sure where exactly to focus.</b></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1622 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Kayak.jpg" alt="Kayak UI" width="1154" height="758" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Kayak.jpg 1154w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Kayak-300x197.jpg 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Kayak-768x504.jpg 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Kayak-1024x673.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1154px) 100vw, 1154px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While the UI is fantastic (the important things stand out, like the calls to actions and filters), I can’t confidently say the same for the user experience—which is just as critical as the UI. I see way too much competition between the various colors, equal priority given to all the filters, multiple lines of information in each section&#8230; It’s a lot.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Enter </span><a href="https://www.google.com/flights/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Google Flights</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. On an aesthetic level it doesn’t compare to the best websites you’ve ever seen—let alone Kayak—but they’ve done a really important thing: </span><b>they’ve established the priority in which they want you to think about things</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1623 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Google-Flights.png" alt="Google Flights UI" width="706" height="667" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Google-Flights.png 706w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Google-Flights-300x283.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 706px) 100vw, 706px" /></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">You like nonstop flights? </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bam! There they are at the top of the list. </span></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Price is a big influencer for you? </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Awesome—here are the lower prices first. </span></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Airlines and WiFi are deal breakers? </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Okay</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> then, here’s that information upfront. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">They’ve taken into account what they already know about their users and told them, </span><b>“This is what we know you want.”</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Google Flights is </span><b>showing what matters</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">. They’ve reduced the clutter by honing in on the key user needs and hiding/putting aside the other features. The filters are all still there; they’re just greyed out or lightened to improve the user experience. This to me is a great example of a company knowing their users and empathizing with them thoughtfully.</span></p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<h1>2. Minimize cognitive load</h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A basic but easily overlooked concept is that a user experience should be simple; </span><b>your design should make the user think </b><b><i>as little as possible</i></b><b>. </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">“That’s got too much cognitive load” is probably a phrase you’ve heard from almost </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">every product designer ever</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Okay, that might be an exaggeration, but the term cognitive load has become a keeper in the PM and design space. It’s a fancy way to say “cut the clutter.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Let’s take the below example of an early version of the password program </span><a href="https://www.lastpass.com/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">LastPass</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. I use this program all the time for its super-practical functionality, but looking at this early design, I’m overwhelmed for many reasons. For example:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">There is no focal point. Where the hell do I even start? </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Almost </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">every </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">button has the same degree of importance. Since when do edit, share and delete have the same weight as a </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">user manual</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">?!</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The icon colours don’t match at all. Like at all.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1624 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Last-Pass-old-version.png" alt="Last Pass' old UI" width="952" height="474" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Last-Pass-old-version.png 952w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Last-Pass-old-version-300x149.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Last-Pass-old-version-768x382.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 952px) 100vw, 952px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Compare this version to the site’s latest design and you’ll notice a </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">huge</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> improvement. They’ve </span><b>designed for the user’s core action</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> of searching for a program-specific password to change, edit or delete. So that means:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Brand logos were expanded and put front and center</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">A hover effect was added to each brand for the secondary options (edit, delete, etc.)</span></li>
</ul>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1625 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/LastPass-New-Version.png" alt="Last Pass' new UI" width="1423" height="694" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/LastPass-New-Version.png 1423w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/LastPass-New-Version-300x146.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/LastPass-New-Version-768x375.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/LastPass-New-Version-1024x499.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1423px) 100vw, 1423px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While the design may look significantly different, it was fueled by simple tweaks that drastically reduced the thinking on the user’s part and provided a </span><b>cleaner emotional experience</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<h1>3. Three-click mentality</h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Simple exercise for you. Pick a website or app you love and see how many clicks it takes to get to a core action. Users don’t want to click on endless buttons to reach their destination; they want short and sweet. One core design principle PMs should internalize is that </span><b>every single core action should be achievable within 3 clicks</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Granted, not every application can do this, but this is a great opportunity to challenge yourself. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Let’s take </span><a href="https://www.amazon.com/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Amazon</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. It’s a huge site. Imagine I bought something, I really love it, and now I want to tell the seller how I feel. How many clicks would it take to complete that task?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Let’s see!</span></p>
<p><b>Step 1: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">‘Your Account’ would be the natural first step to view past purchases. I hover over it—which we’ll consider half a click.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1628 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Amazon-Step-1.png" alt="Step 1 of Writing a Product Review on Amazon" width="406" height="353" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Amazon-Step-1.png 406w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Amazon-Step-1-300x261.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 406px) 100vw, 406px" /></p>
<p><b>Step 2: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Click on ‘Your Orders.’</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1629 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Amazon-Step-2.png" alt="Step 2 of Writing a Product Review on Amazon" width="406" height="353" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Amazon-Step-2.png 406w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Amazon-Step-2-300x261.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 406px) 100vw, 406px" /></p>
<p><b>Step 3: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Scroll down the list and click on “Write a product review.”</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1630 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Amazon-Step3.jpg" alt="Step 3 of Writing a Product Review on Amazon" width="1921" height="925" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Amazon-Step3.jpg 1921w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Amazon-Step3-300x144.jpg 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Amazon-Step3-768x370.jpg 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Amazon-Step3-1024x493.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1921px) 100vw, 1921px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Done. In 2.5 clicks I’ve reached my destination and can perform my core action. Despite being one of the biggest websites in the world, Amazon has taken into serious consideration how to streamline my user process. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Again, I understand this isn’t </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">always </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">possible, but I think the 3-click mentality can serve as </span><b>a litmus test to see how friendly your application really is</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<h1>4. Reversible design</h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We all make mistakes—which is why product people designed the Undo button. Users can get </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">pissed</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> when they can’t undo an action (I’ve been there!). Yet so many of the products in market still don’t offer reversible options for certain actions.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Reversible design is more than simply clicking an undo button. Here are some examples of reversible designs from the tools I use every day:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The little ‘x’ that lets me delete a filter on <a href="https://www.intercom.com/" target="_blank">Intercom</a></span></li>
</ul>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1634 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Reversible-Design-Intercom.png" alt="Deleting filters on Intercom" width="258" height="532" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Reversible-Design-Intercom.png 258w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Reversible-Design-Intercom-145x300.png 145w" sizes="(max-width: 258px) 100vw, 258px" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Deleting or removing files from <a href="https://www.google.com/drive/" target="_blank">Google Drive</a></span></li>
</ul>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1635 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Reversible-Design-Google-Drive.png" alt="Undoing a file deletion in Google Drive" width="860" height="579" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Reversible-Design-Google-Drive.png 860w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Reversible-Design-Google-Drive-300x202.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Reversible-Design-Google-Drive-768x517.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 860px) 100vw, 860px" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Moving a <a href="https://trello.com/" target="_blank">Trello</a> card—then being able to drag it back to its original place</span></li>
</ul>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1636 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Reversible-Design-Trello.png" alt="Moving a Trello card" width="566" height="184" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Reversible-Design-Trello.png 566w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Reversible-Design-Trello-300x98.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 566px) 100vw, 566px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If your support center is frequently inundated by questions from users who have lost files or accidentally changed work they didn’t actually want to change, you’re probably going to want to give them a way to backtrack. Where would we be without Command+Z?</span></p>
<h1>5. Use verbs with context</h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If your dialogue boxes are bogged down with words like </span><b>Yes</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">, <strong>No</strong>, </span><b>Cancel</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and </span><b>Save</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">, your users might be a little muddled. This vague terminology only increases cognitive load. Half the time you’re not sure you’re taking the right action, prolonging a process that should have taken little thought and even less time.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1644 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Dialogue-Box-Example-1.png" alt="Dialogue box example" width="454" height="229" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Dialogue-Box-Example-1.png 454w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Dialogue-Box-Example-1-300x151.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 454px) 100vw, 454px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Skilled designers have now narrowed down the options and provided </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">context</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Instead of a bevy of vague button choices, you get specific instructions: verbs/phrases like </span><b>Cancel</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> or </span><b>Yes, delete this message</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Simple. And on top of that, you get context telling you why these verbs are here (e.g. deleting the highlighted message). </span><b>Already you’ve reduced ambiguity and cognitive load.</b></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1645 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Dialogue-Box-Example-2.png" alt="Dialogue Box Example" width="561" height="232" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Dialogue-Box-Example-2.png 561w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Dialogue-Box-Example-2-300x124.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 561px) 100vw, 561px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sometimes it really comes down to something as easy as changing the text on the screen to significantly improve a user’s experience. </span></p>
<h1>6. White space is your friend (a.k.a. Use white space to disrupt your competitors)</h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This dead-simple design principle can elevate your design from clunky to slick. When done well, it really </span><b>eases the emotional experience for users</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Designers tout this principle </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">a lot</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, but there is still often a struggle to integrate the concept of white space.<br />
</span><br />
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Take a look at <a href="https://wordpress.com/" target="_blank">WordPress</a>. Yes, everything you see on this screen is something you’ll need to use at some point in the blogging process. But when you’re actually writing (i.e. performing the software’s core activity), this UI is very disruptive. It comes off as heavy and messy. Only 25% of the real estate is allocated to the white space for writing. </span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1637 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Wordpress.png" alt="Wordpress UI" width="1420" height="812" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Wordpress.png 1420w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Wordpress-300x172.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Wordpress-768x439.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Wordpress-1024x586.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1420px) 100vw, 1420px" /></p>
<p>The site has caught on to this criticism by providing a &#8220;Distraction-free writing mode&#8221; (the small button at the far right of the text editing toolbar) in their latest versions. Temporarily removing all the sidebars, this mode puts the writing space/white space as the central focus of the page.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Compare this to <a href="https://medium.com/" target="_blank">Medium</a>, which has always been pretty much just white space. It provides a space to write your post, then add social widgets, type some tags and publish. Essentially they’ve made the process much easier for someone who might be jarred by WordPress or similar publishing platforms. And it hasn’t reduced functionality!</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1638 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Medium.png" alt="Medium UI" width="1047" height="532" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Medium.png 1047w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Medium-300x152.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Medium-768x390.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Medium-1024x520.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1047px) 100vw, 1047px" /></p>
<h1>7. Design in MSP (Minimum Saleable Product)</h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So far, I’ve mentioned common design principles you’ll hear as a PM, but a less-talked-about principle is having your team design in </span><b>MSP (minimum saleable product)</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I stay away from language like MVP (minimum viable product)—unless it’s an infrastructure-related product—because to me that ignores user experience. It puts it as this far-off goal&#8230;a “nice-to-have” rather than a “must-have.”<br />
</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br />
</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Take the image below. The pyramid on the left shows that designing in MVP starts from the bottom (i.e. the pink) and works its way up the pyramid addressing emotional design as the last “need” of the product. Whereas on the right, you see that designing in MSP tackles all the “needs” in the pyramid—including emotional design—simultaneously from the start (i.e. why the pink component covers the entire height of the pyramid).</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1639 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Product_management_design-MSP_MVP.png" alt="Designing in MVP vs. MSP" width="1192" height="567" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Product_management_design-MSP_MVP.png 1192w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Product_management_design-MSP_MVP-300x143.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Product_management_design-MSP_MVP-768x365.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Product_management_design-MSP_MVP-1024x487.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1192px) 100vw, 1192px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">MVPs encourage teams to get something out there that is functional. It can break, but as long as the functionality and workflow are available, it’s solid. That, to me, is a “no.” What about the </span><b>usability</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">? Or </span><b>emotional connection</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Think about any product you’ve ever encountered. When you first enter an application or product, you have an emotional reaction based on the design alone, which either does or does not spur you to click around and see if it’s usable. A product&#8217;s design is<strong> the </strong></span><strong>first thing a user acknowledges before anything else; </strong>it&#8217;s the first impression.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A product&#8217;s design is<strong> the </strong></span><strong>first thing a user acknowledges before anything else; </strong>it&#8217;s the first impression.</p></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Yes, the product needs to be functional, but my sales team also needs to be able to sell to users. And not just to the early adopters and innovators: we need to sell this to the early majority. If these terms are unfamiliar, check out the </span><b>Technology Adoption Lifecycle Model </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">below. The model includes five stages of how a product gets adopted and the different customer segments within each stage. (</span><a href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/create-product-roadmap/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">More detail on those segments here!</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">) </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In his hugely popular 1991 book </span><b><i>Crossing the Chasm</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">, author </span><b>Geoffrey Moore</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> explained that for products to be successful, they must cross a </span><b>chasm</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> that exists between early adopters and the majority of the market.</span></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1641 size-full" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Product_management_design-Crossing_the_Chasm.png" alt="Crossing the Chasm diagram" width="1192" height="567" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Product_management_design-Crossing_the_Chasm.png 1192w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Product_management_design-Crossing_the_Chasm-300x143.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Product_management_design-Crossing_the_Chasm-768x365.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Product_management_design-Crossing_the_Chasm-1024x487.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1192px) 100vw, 1192px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Crossing the chasm is difficult, since the early majority is vastly different (i.e. pickier) than the first two groups, who are more willing to put up with bugs and reliability issues. </span><b>The way we cross the chasm is through designing an MSP. </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">How? Because pickier audiences in the early majority will overlook faults that may exist when you offer a product with superior design elements.  </span></p>
<blockquote><p><b>&#8230;the more you focus on packaging saleable features with compelling, user-friendly design, the more disruptive you can be to the market</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Take my team at Roadmunk, which focuses on UX and users’ emotional responses. We find that our users aren’t gathering their pitchforks and starting a manhunt when there&#8217;s an issue, because we’ve designed in MSP to ensure that our app is kinda really pretty (#shamelessselfpromotion). Don’t get me wrong, functionality is still key, but </span><b>the more you focus on packaging saleable features with compelling, user-friendly design, the more disruptive you can be to the market</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">. For example, our <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=design" target="_blank">customizable template library</a> is one such saleable functionality that&#8217;s hit the mark with our users largely due to its user-friendliness and design focus. </span></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Final words: Let design be your secret weapon</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Design has become more and more of a priority at product organizations, and it can be your secret weapon for standing out in a sea of competitors and changing the market. It doesn’t matter whether you’re working with your first prototype or the thousandth iteration of your product, </span><b>your product’s design should always be on your mind.</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Don’t just leave design in the hands of your design team; PMs should be living and breathing it, too. Take the time to put design at the forefront of your product strategy and see how your users become emotionally invested. </span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/product-management-design-principles/">7 essential design principles for product managers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How poker helps you win at product management</title>
		<link>https://roadmunk.com/blog/poker-product-management/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 17:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Latif Nanji]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Influencers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://roadmunk.com/blog/?p=593</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>My poker story started the same way as many others: a bunch of dudes playing for $5 in my friend Dustin’s basement.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/poker-product-management/">How poker helps you win at product management</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A lot of product managers start their careers as engineers or MBAs. I started my career as a poker player. I wasn’t poker player then a product manager. Poker directly inspired me to launch my first product: an online poker community. And while Roadmunk has nothing to do with poker, I would never have leveled up if it weren’t for the game.</p>
<p>My poker story started the same way as many others: a bunch of dudes playing for $5 in <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dumann" target="_blank">my friend Dustin’s</a> basement. But as I honed my game and started to win big online tournaments, I also honed a lot of the skills I now use daily as an entrepreneur and product manager.</p>
<p>Some of the similarities between poker and product are obvious. (And <a href="https://twitter.com/BrandonMChu" target="_blank">Shopify&#8217;s Brandon Chu</a> has already written <a href="https://medium.com/@brandonmchu/product-management-is-a-lot-like-playing-poker-a1f3b00dcbe" target="_blank">an awesome post on the same topic</a>.) Both require endurance, risk calculation and chill under pressure. But I wanted to share some of the other, less-obvious facets of poker that have shape my career in product.</p>
<p><strong><big><img class="aligncenter wp-image-701" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/poker-chips-300x51.png" alt="poker chips" width="400" height="68" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/poker-chips-300x51.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/poker-chips.png 750w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></big></strong></p>
<h1>#1 Nurturing luck through collaboration and feedback</h1>
<p>Poker players aren’t always straight-faced loners. In fact, poker is insanely collaborative.</p>
<p>I met Steve B., one of my poker mates, through a mutual friend in biology class at the University of Waterloo. Steve gave me the lowdown on how to win—and consistently exploit opponents. <strong>Hand analysis</strong>, <strong>habit-building</strong> and <strong>pattern recognition</strong> were all quickly part of my repertoire. Steve was about my age, but he had a few extra years of poker under his belt. It was largely thanks to him that I won my first tournament in 2004 after only 6 months of play—and took home a tidy 30K score.</p>
<p>My poker friendships taught me a counterintuitive lesson: <em><strong>luck isn’t pure luck</strong></em>. It can be nurtured—you can actually grow your luck. Both product management and poker require a mix of luck and skill. There’s certainly an element of “getting lucky”—but you can cultivate good luck through constant collaboration. What I loved most was how feedback was often conflicting. I had to learn when to follow advice—and when to forget it.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-718" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/mentor-whiplash-300x86.png" alt="mentor whiplash" width="550" height="158" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/mentor-whiplash-300x86.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/mentor-whiplash-768x220.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/mentor-whiplash.png 958w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></p>
<p>In the business world, we call that <a href="http://avc.com/2013/07/mentorinvestor-whiplash/" target="_blank">mentor whiplash</a>. When you take bad poker advice, the stakes aren’t usually disastrous—losing a single hand or tournament may sting, but there’s always the next one. In business, on the other hand, it can take weeks (or months) to course-correct after making a bad decision.</p>
<!-- This site is converting visitors into subscribers and customers with OptinMonster - https://optinmonster.com :: Campaign Title: Blog signup inline --><div id="om-ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg-holder"></div><script>var ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg,ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll=function(){var r=0;return function(n,l){clearInterval(r),r=setInterval(n,l)}}();!function(e,t,n){if(e.getElementById(n)){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg_poll(function(){if(window['om_loaded']){if(!ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg){ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();return ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});}}},25);return;}var d=false,o=e.createElement(t);o.id=n,o.src="https://a.optnmstr.com/app/js/api.min.js",o.async=true,o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=function(){if(!d){if(!this.readyState||this.readyState==="loaded"||this.readyState==="complete"){try{d=om_loaded=true;ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg=new OptinMonsterApp();ytoapcdbhazgdychkbmg.init({"u":"25630.595075","staging":0,"dev":0,"beta":0});o.onload=o.onreadystatechange=null;}catch(t){}}}};(document.getElementsByTagName("head")[0]||document.documentElement).appendChild(o)}(document,"script","omapi-script");</script><!-- / OptinMonster -->
<p>Since my poker years, I’ve learned to nurture luck by surrounding myself with smart people and reading tons of books. (I tend to devote about <strong>25% of my energy to books</strong>, <strong>25% to mentorship</strong> and <strong>50% to actually doing it</strong>.) By the time I became a product manager, any ego had been replaced with a humble understanding of my own ignorance. Poker had set me up for a product management career filled with healthy collaboration—which increases your chances of success.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-719" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/cards-300x75.png" alt="cards" width="400" height="100" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/cards-300x75.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/cards.png 750w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<h1>#2 Optimizing for states of flow</h1>
<p>I had my all-time best poker day during a tournament in Aruba in 2006. Even though I didn’t win, my focus was powerful. I could basically <em>feel</em> everything that was going on at the table. <strong>All my reads were perfect.</strong> And I recognized that if you can attain that level of concentration, you won’t always win, but you will get closer to your goal.</p>
<p>Poker is a discovery of different states of mental solitude. Initially, there are hurdles—you swing a lot between winning and losing. But along the way, your focus gets deeper as you hone your skills and build confidence. You learn to ignore everything that’s going on outside the table. Given the nature of the game, this does not guarantee success—but it definitely increases your chances of winning.</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-721 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/flow-300x86.png" alt="flow" width="550" height="158" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/flow-300x86.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/flow-768x221.png 768w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/flow.png 958w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></p>
<p>Building a product requires countless states of <strong>flow</strong>. (Be sure to check out <a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/mihaly_csikszentmihalyi_on_flow?language=en" target="_blank">Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi’s work on flow</a>.) Email, conversations, snacks, last night’s fourth beer—you need to be able to shut that out, clear your desktop, and concentrate. (Personally, I like to avoid email for the first two hours in the morning and tackle at least one “boulder” task per day.) With flow comes deeper insights that enable us to move faster and make better decisions. Regardless of whether you happen to be winning or losing on any particular day, you need to be able to quiet the noise and zoom in on your goal.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-607" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/pokertable-300x51.png" alt="pokertable" width="400" height="68" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/pokertable-300x51.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/pokertable.png 750w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<h1>#3 The data is a story, not an answer</h1>
<p>In online poker, especially, your ability to read your opponent is correlated to your ability to read data. Poker players use something called a <a href="https://www.pokertracker.com/guides/PT3/hud/basic-hud-user-guide" target="_blank">HUD (i.e. “heads-up display”)</a> that aggregates players’ stats and hand history. High-value stats includes an opponent’s VPIP (how often they voluntarily put chips in the pot) and their AF (aggression factor).</p>
<p>The challenge is that the numbers are not always straightforward. If an opponent knows your stats (which they do, because they’re always using a HUD, as well), their behaviour will change. Their actions might also be affected by table stakes, game type and their mood on any given day. So while the numbers tell one story, the reality can vary wildly. You need to be able to read the numbers <em>within the context of the moment</em>. Just how in business, you must understand (and predict) how a market or competitor will respond to certain activities.</p>
<blockquote><p>While the numbers tell one story, <strong>the reality can vary wildly</strong>. You need to be able to read the numbers within the context of the moment.</p></blockquote>
<p>In both poker and product, <strong>no amount of data can replace instincts</strong>. In the early days, PMs often don’t have a lot of data—they <em>just</em> have instinct. They must extrapolate from users’ anecdotes and opinions to create an early vision for the product. And even when you have tons of data, it can’t be your only reference point. When we started Roadmunk, my instincts told me to emphasize design. There was no quantitative evidence saying we should be a design-led organization. I just knew, intuitively, that design was going to be very compelling. I may not have trusted that feeling if it weren’t for poker.</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-702 aligncenter" src="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/aviators-300x51.png" alt="aviators" width="450" height="76" srcset="https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/aviators-300x51.png 300w, https://roadmunk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/aviators.png 750w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /></p>
<h1>#4 Emotional Intelligence</h1>
<p>The final piece of the puzzle seems to be the never-ending virtue of emotional intelligence. <strong>The idea of a “poker face” kind of misses the point</strong>. Being a great player doesn’t mean masking your emotions, but learning to harness them. Remaining stoic at the table requires a deep well of confidence, humility and determination. For most, early on, it’s just about winning <em>that one game</em>. Then it’s about continuous flow and ultimately growing to be the best.</p>
<blockquote><p>To be present to that fire, understand how big it is, and be objective towards it—<strong>that’s where the 0.01% live and breathe</strong>.</p></blockquote>
<p>In business and poker, leaders lose years due to internal stress because they have to remain outwardly calm. To bridge the gap between internal and external realities, you must have emotional intelligence. <strong>The fire will always be burning.</strong> Sales will always be yelling for the “next thing,” engineering will always be under pressure, and product managers will always have to be the go-between. To be present to that fire, understand how big it is, and be objective towards it—that’s where the 0.01% live and breathe.</p>
<p>For product managers, getting to that level is incredibly challenging because you need to fail and learn from mistakes made with REAL businesses in REAL markets that cost a lot money. Much like poker, it’s not for the faint of heart.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>If you&#8217;re a product manager looking to mitigate risks, a roadmap might be your best bet. <a href="https://roadmunk.com/roadmap-templates?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_content=poker" target="_blank">Click here to try one of our 20+ customizable roadmap templates</a>!</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog/poker-product-management/">How poker helps you win at product management</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://roadmunk.com/blog">Roadmunk Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
